<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Most excellent and approved medicines &amp; remedies for most diseases and maladies incident to man's body, lately compiled and extracted out of the originals of the most famous and best experienced physicians both in England and other countries, by A. R. Doctor in Physick decesased. And since revised by an able practitioner in the same science, and now published for the universall good and benefi [sic] of this Common-wealth.</title>
            <author>Read, Alexander, 1586?-1641.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 211 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 81 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92202</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R434</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1301_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209005</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867916</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867916</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169737</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92202)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169737)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 174:E1301[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Most excellent and approved medicines &amp; remedies for most diseases and maladies incident to man's body, lately compiled and extracted out of the originals of the most famous and best experienced physicians both in England and other countries, by A. R. Doctor in Physick decesased. And since revised by an able practitioner in the same science, and now published for the universall good and benefi [sic] of this Common-wealth.</title>
                  <author>Read, Alexander, 1586?-1641.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 144 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.C. for George Latham Junior, and are to be sold at the signe of the Bishops head in St. Pauls Church-yeard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652 [i.e. 1651]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A. R. = Alexander Read.</note>
                  <note>Thomason received his copy in September 1651.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Septemb. 7."; 2 in imprint date crossed through and '1' written in.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169737:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MOST EXCELLENT And approved <hi>Medicines &amp; Remedies</hi> For moſt Diſeaſes and Maladies Incident to Man's Body, Lately compiled and extracted out of the Originals of the moſt Famous and beſt Experienced Phyſicians both in <hi>England</hi> and other Countries,</p>
            <p>By <hi>A. R.</hi> Doctor in Phyſick deceaſed.</p>
            <p>And ſince reviſed by an able Practitioner in the ſame Science, and now Publiſhed for the univerſall good and benefi of this Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vita ſine Valetudine Odium eſt, non Vita.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eccleſ. 38.1, 2, 4.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Honour the <hi>Phyſician</hi> with that honour that is due unto him becauſe of <hi>Neceſſity:</hi> for the <hi>LORD</hi> hath created him. For of the moſt <hi>HIGH</hi> cometh <hi>healing.</hi>—</p>
               <p>The <hi>LORD</hi> hath created <hi>Medicines</hi> of the Earth, and he that is <hi>Wiſe</hi> will not abhor them.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J.C</hi> for <hi>George Latham Junior,</hi> and are to be ſold at the ſigne of the Biſhops head in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yeard 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:169737:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:169737:2"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>COURTEOUS READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T's a very ſad and lamentable thing, even againſt the <hi>Courſe</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> and a way to tempt the very <hi>GOD</hi> of Nature, wilfully to impead and hinder our <hi>Health,</hi> or not to ſeek <hi>Meanes</hi> to continue it when we have it, or not to recover it when it's lost and gone. God ſends ſeverall <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> and <hi>Sickneſſes,</hi> and hath appointed ſeverall <hi>Medicines</hi> or <hi>Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi> to encounter them; Therefore <hi>honour the Phyſician,</hi> and with <hi>Ezekiah, Lay a plaiſter up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Boil.</hi> Say not, <hi>Man hath his period as well as the Sea it's bounds, which it cannot paſſe. What God hath decreed, is already done in Heaven, and ſhall alſo undoubtedly
<pb facs="tcp:169737:3"/>
be done in Earth. Who hath ever reſiſted his will?</hi> Rom. <hi>9.19.</hi> Say not, <hi>Life and death is not in our own hand; for ſome ſeek death in miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, yet finde it not; others meet with it at Feaſts and</hi> Gaudies, <hi>and where they would faine forget it.</hi> Say not, <hi>When the Glaſs is run, do what we can, we can ſtay no longer, and the Clock will ſtrike when the minutes be paſt. That which muſt be, ſhall be, what ſhall means do?</hi> For, by the like reaſon thou maiſt excuſe thy wickedneſſe, and be deſperate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly careleſs. But in matters of <hi>Hope</hi> where the <hi>End</hi> is not known, uſe <hi>Meanes</hi> with <hi>Aſa,</hi> though relye not upon them, (as he did:) Although ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times they avail not, yet notwithſtanding take we all the faireſt wayes of all lawfull <hi>Remedies,</hi> when Gods <hi>Determinations</hi> and <hi>Purpoſes</hi> are concealed from us. Thou haſt <hi>(Courteous Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der)</hi> in this little Book, moſt exquiſite <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines</hi> and Remedies preſented to thy view, for divers (if not all ſorts of) <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> and <hi>Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi> incident to Mans fraile and weak Body; It's therefore thy duty to make a right and dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous uſe thereof. Here is a <hi>Price</hi> (a precious Jewel) <hi>put into thine hand,</hi> God grant <hi>thou want not an heart,</hi> to lay bold of it. Thou needeſt not waſte thy Eſtate, or <hi>ſpend all thou haſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Phyſicians, and yet be ne're a whit the better for't,</hi> as ſhe in the Goſpell is ſaid to have
<pb facs="tcp:169737:3"/>
done, Mar. <hi>5:16.</hi> Lo, here is <hi>Phyſick</hi> for every <hi>Patient,</hi> a <hi>Salve</hi> for every <hi>Sore,</hi> a <hi>Cure</hi> for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very <hi>Wound,</hi> a <hi>Medicine</hi> for every <hi>Diſeaſe,</hi> and a <hi>Receipt</hi> or <hi>Remedie</hi> for every <hi>Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die;</hi> and it to be had at a very cheap and eaſie rate: So that even the meaner and poorer ſort of People, who for want of ability, cannot go to the Phyſicians for cure in time of Sickneſs and Viſitation, may finde eaeſe and comfort by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſing this ſmall Treatiſe, as well as thoſe that are of greater abilities. But to what purpoſe do I ſpend time, or waſte paper in praiſing or commending this little Book? The thing is able ſufficiently to ſpeak for, and to commend it ſelfe. It was truely and wiſely ſaid of one that was a moſt learned Phyſician, That <hi>Morbi non cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantur eloquentiâ, multò minùs loquentiâ: Diſeaſes are not healed with Eloquent ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches or Rhetoricall flaſhes, much leſs with vaine babling or multiplicity of words.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not to inſiſt too long upon Introductions or Preambles, leſt it ſhould be ſaid to me as once a flouting <hi>Cynick</hi> ſaid to the Citizens of <hi>Myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,</hi> a little City with great Gates: <hi>Shut your Gates leſt your City run out;</hi> I take my leave, and reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in all Offices of Love and Service</hi> T. A.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="index">
            <pb facs="tcp:169737:4"/>
            <head>An Alphabeticall TABLE Directing to the Principall Matters contained in this Book.</head>
            <list>
               <head>A</head>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or an <hi>Ach</hi> in the Back. <hi>Pag. 59.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For the <hi>Head-ach. p. 27, 88.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For the <hi>Tooth-ach. p. 72, 111</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For an <hi>Ague. p. 67, 79.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For a Tertian <hi>Ague. p. 60.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For a Quartan <hi>Ague. p. 86.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An <hi>Almond-milk</hi> to cool and induce ſleep. <hi>p. 68.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For an <hi>Apoplexie. p. 45.65,</hi> See Palſie</item>
               <item>How to make <hi>Aqua-vitae. p 63.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>B.</head>
               <item>FOr the heat of the <hi>Back. p. 77</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For Pain in the <hi>Back. p. 59</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A ſoverain <hi>Balſam</hi> for <hi>22.</hi> ſeveral diſeaſes <hi>p. 86</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to make a <hi>Barley</hi> Cream. <hi>p. 68.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A <hi>Bath</hi> to cleanſe the skin of Scabs, Scurf, Maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gineſſe. <hi>p. 28.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A <hi>Bath</hi> for cold Diſeaſes or Palſies. <hi>p. 30</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:169737:4"/>To bind the <hi>Belly</hi> in Fluxes, or to ſtop or ſtay the looſenes of the Belly. <hi>p. 32, 43, 51, 81.</hi> See <hi>Looſeneſs, Scowring.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To looſen the Body of one that is hard bound in the <hi>Belly. p. 36, 39.</hi> See <hi>Looſen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For young children that are hard bound in the <hi>Belly</hi> and troubled with Wormes. <hi>p. 100.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To ripen and ſupporate <hi>Biles</hi> and Tumors. <hi>p. 33</hi> See <hi>Fellon, Swelling, Whitflaw.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Againſt the <hi>Biting</hi> of a mad Dog. <hi>p. 87. 95.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Againſt the <hi>Biting</hi> or ſtinging of any Venemous Beaſt <hi>p. 95.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For one that <hi>Bleedeth</hi> inwardly. <hi>p. 104.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To aſtringe in <hi>Bleeding,</hi> or to ſtay &amp; ſtanch <hi>Blee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. p. 44, 94.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To ſtanch the <hi>Bleeding</hi> of any VVound. <hi>p. 44, 94.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To ſtanch <hi>Bleeding</hi> at Noſe. <hi>p. 44, 94, 104, 105.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Tor thoſe that ſpit <hi>Blood. p. 93,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To reſtore good <hi>Blood. p. 1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Againſt congealed <hi>Blood. p. 15.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To cleanſe, temper, and purifie the <hi>Blood. p. 52. r53, 54, 55, 59, 84.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For the <hi>Bloody-Flux p. 67, 74.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For cold Diſeaſes of the <hi>Brain</hi> and Sinews. <hi>p. 57.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To comfort the <hi>Brain. p. 14, 15.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To cleanſe and purge the head or <hi>Brain</hi> by the
<pb facs="tcp:169737:5"/>
Noſe. <hi>p. 45, 128.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To make a ſweet <hi>Breath,</hi> and to cure a ſtinking and unſavory <hi>Breath. p. 14, 15, 36.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For ſhort-<hi>Breathing. p. 56.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For a VVoman that hath great <hi>Breſts. p. 125.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For a VVomans ſore <hi>Breaſt. p. 126.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To increaſe or procure Milk in a Womans <hi>Breſt p. 49, 126.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To dry up Milk in a Womans <hi>Breſt. p. 49.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For <hi>Bruiſes p. 15, 33, 87. 99.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For a <hi>Burning</hi> or ſcalding. <hi>p. 74, 87, 110.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For one that is <hi>Burſt</hi> in the Belly or Cods. <hi>p. 96.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>C.</head>
               <item>FOr the <hi>Canker</hi> upon a Mans Yard. <hi>pag. 100</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For the <hi>Canker</hi> in a Womans Breſt. <hi>p. 129.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For a <hi>Canker</hi> in the Mouth. <hi>p 130, 131.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For a <hi>Canker</hi> in any part of the body. <hi>p. 88, 130.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To purge <hi>Choler. p. 1, 9, 10. 43.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An opening and cooling Julip for <hi>Choler,</hi> and burnt humors. <hi>p. 11.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To draw downe <hi>Choler. p. 45.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Carminative or <hi>Collick</hi>-Gliſter. <hi>p. 40.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For the <hi>Collick</hi> and Stone. <hi>p. 115, 116.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For the Wind <hi>Collick. p 76, 88.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To help or amend <hi>Concoction. p. 14, 15, 21, 65.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For weak and <hi>Conſuming</hi> bodies. <hi>p. 61.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For a <hi>Conſumption. p. 118, 119, 137, 138, 139</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To <hi>Coole</hi> the Liver. <hi>p. 26, 27. 68, 81, 123</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cooling</hi> Medicines. <hi>p. 11 12, 20, 26, 27, 38, 68 81, 123.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:169737:5"/>A <hi>Cordial</hi> againſt Melancholick vapours and palpitations of the heart. <hi>p. 49.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Temperate <hi>Cordial</hi> Julip. <hi>p. 50.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cordials</hi> to be taken after Phyſick. <hi>p. 52.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For <hi>Corns</hi> on the feet or Toes. <hi>p. 134:</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For the <hi>Cough. p. 56, 78.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For the <hi>Cough</hi> of the Lungs. <hi>p. 116.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To provoke or bring downe Womens monethly <hi>Courſes,</hi> Termes, or Flowers. <hi>p. 23, 25, 51, 85, 89.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For the <hi>Cramp. p. 68, 79.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to make <hi>Cynamon-water. p. 66.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>D.</head>
               <item>FOr the <hi>Deafneſſe</hi> of the Eares <hi>p. 90, 133.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To hinder <hi>Dinting. p. 29.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For cold <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> or Palſies. <hi>p. 26.30.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For cold <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> of the Brain and Sinews. <hi>p. 57</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Cooling Gliſter in hot <hi>Diſeaſes. p. 38.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A <hi>Diet-Drink</hi> to open and temper the Liver. <hi>(p. 61.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A <hi>Diet-Drink</hi> to cleanſe and temper the blood. <hi>(p. 54.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to make the <hi>Salſaperilla-Drink,</hi> which is marvelous good for the French Pox. <hi>p. 82</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An Excellent <hi>Drink</hi> for divers Diſeaſes, viz.</item>
               <item>Dropſie, Yellow Jaundice, Itch, Scabs, Maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gineſs, &amp;c <hi>p. 84.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A very cooling and pleaſant Water to <hi>Drink in</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:169737:6"/>
Summer. <hi>p. 123.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A <hi>Poſſet-Drink</hi> to cool the Liver. <hi>p. 81</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A gratefull <hi>Drink</hi> or Potion to purge or cleanſe the Spleen. <hi>p. 56</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A pretious <hi>Diet-Drink</hi> againſt any deſperate diſeaſe that is curable. <hi>p. 85.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For the <hi>Dropſie. p. 51, 81, 84.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For <hi>Dyſenteries. p. 42.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>E.</head>
               <item>FOr the <hi>Epilepſie p. 14. See Falling-ſicknes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For Sore <hi>Eyes. p, 22, 69</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For the Rheum in the <hi>Eyes,</hi> and the Redneſſe of them. <hi>p. 72.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To clear and preſerve the <hi>Eye-ſight,</hi> and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover it being gone. <hi>p. 22, 69, 70, 71</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For a Weft or Pearl in the <hi>Eye. p. 71.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To take away a Weft from the <hi>Eye. p. 134.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>F.</head>
               <item>TO make the <hi>Face</hi> faire and clear. <hi>p. 84, 127.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To take away red ſpots, freckles &amp; pimples in the <hi>Face. p. 44, 127.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For heat in the <hi>Face. p. 78.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For the <hi>Falling-ſickneſſe. p. 14, 57, 89, 113.</hi> See <hi>Epilepſie.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For <hi>Fatneſs</hi> about the Heart. <hi>p. 117.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For a <hi>Fellon. p. 108, 128.</hi> See <hi>Swelling, Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flaw.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For the Burning <hi>Fever p. 16, 26.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:169737:6"/>For hot peſtilent <hi>Fevers. p. 16.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For a Tertian <hi>Fever. p. 60.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For a <hi>Fiſtulo. p. 88.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To purge <hi>Fleam. p. 3, 8, 43, 52.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To purge both Choler and <hi>Fleam. p. 10.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Gargle to draw <hi>Fleam. p. 35.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Liquid Naſals for <hi>Fleam. p. 45.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>G.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>DIvers ſorts of</hi> Gargles <hi>for divers Diſeaſes.</hi> (pag. 35, 36, 127.)</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Divers ſorts of</hi> Gliſters <hi>for divers Diſeaſes.</hi> p. 37 38, 39, 40, 41, 42, 43, 44.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For the</hi> Gowt. p. 80, 88, 102, 113.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For the</hi> Gravel <hi>or Stone.</hi> p. 75.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For the</hi> Green-ſickneſs. p. 19, 20, 84, 89</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For a</hi> Green Wound: p. 85, 87.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>H.</head>
               <item>TO purge the <hi>Head</hi> or brain by the Noſe. <hi>p. 45, 128.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For fatneſſe about the <hi>Heart. p. 117</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To put away Venome from the <hi>Heart. p. 123</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For the Gnawing about the <hi>Heart p. 123</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For the <hi>Heart-burning p. 105</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For the Palpitations, beatings, or tumblings of the <hi>Heart p. 49, 106</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For the <hi>Heat</hi> of the back <hi>p. 77</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To allay <hi>Heat</hi> and Inflammation in any part <hi>p. 11 12, 20, 26, 27, 33.</hi> See <hi>Cool.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:169737:7"/>To reſtore the ſpirits conſumed with <hi>Heat,</hi> in hot peſtilent Fevers. <hi>p. 16</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For <hi>Heat</hi> in the Mouth or Throat <hi>p. 77</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For <hi>Heat</hi> in the face <hi>p. 78</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For the <hi>Hemorrhoides. p. 62, 105.</hi> See <hi>Piles.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For the <hi>Hickup p. 80</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>I.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>FOr the black and yellow</hi> Jaundice, pag. 84. 113.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For an</hi> Impoſtume. p. 132</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Againſt the</hi> Inflammations <hi>and Obſtructions of the Liver</hi> p. 26, 27, 53, 55, 61, 68, 81-</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For an</hi> Inflamation <hi>in the Throat or parts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts</hi> p: 34</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>To make an</hi> Iſſue p. 80</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For the</hi> Itch, <hi>Scabs, breaking out, Maungineſs, &amp;c.</hi> 28, 73, 74, 84, 108.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Divers kinds of</hi> Julips p. 11, 12, 20, 27, 50, 60</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>K:</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>FOr the</hi> Kings-Evill. p. 131</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>L.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>FOr the</hi> Legs <hi>that do rankle or feſter.</hi> p. 110</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For the</hi> Lethargie <hi>or ſleepie Diſeaſe</hi> p. 45, 65</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>To deſtroy</hi> Lice p: 96</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For a hot</hi> Liver, <hi>and to cool and temper the</hi> Liver, <hi>and to open the obſtructions of it</hi> p. 26, 27, 53 55, 61, 68, 81.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:169737:7"/>
                  <hi>To preſerve the</hi> Liver p. 75</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>To</hi> Looſen <hi>the body of one that is hard bound.</hi> p: 36. 93. <hi>See</hi> Belly:</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>To ſtop or ſtay a</hi> Looſeneſſe p. 32, 43, 57, 81. <hi>See</hi> Belly, Scowring.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>To open the</hi> Lungs <hi>ſtopt with ſoil</hi> p: 12, 13, 84, 117:</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>M.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>FOr the</hi> Meaſels. p. 91.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Againſt</hi> Melancholy <hi>and</hi> Melancholick <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours.</hi> p. 18, 49:</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>To purge and draw down</hi> Melancholy p. 7, 9, 44, 46, 52.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For the</hi> Morphew p. 81, 109</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For the</hi> Mother p. 23, 25, 76.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For a ſore</hi> Mouth p. 35, 77, 112, 127.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>To cleanſe the</hi> Mouth p. 101.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>N.</head>
               <item>DIvers kinds of <hi>Naſals p. 45, 46, 128</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To purge the Head by the <hi>Noſe. p. 45, 128</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Nouriſhing</hi> Gliſters for weak perſons <hi>p. 37</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>O.</head>
               <item>OPening <hi>Medicines</hi> p. 11, 12, 13, 20, 27, 61, 81, 117.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>To</hi> Open <hi>the</hi> Obſtructions <hi>of the Liver,</hi> p. 27, 55, 61, 81, 84.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For</hi> Oppilations <hi>or Stopping of the Breſt.</hi> p. 84, 140.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:169737:8"/>
               <head>P.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>TO ceaſe</hi> Pain p. 37</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For</hi> Pain <hi>in the Back</hi> p. 59.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For the</hi> Palſie p. 30, 57, 77. <hi>See</hi> Apoplexie.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For the</hi> Piles, p. 28, 62, 92, 93, 105. <hi>See</hi> Hemor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhoides.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the</hi> Pills <hi>called</hi> de tribus Fernelii p. 67</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the</hi> Pills <hi>of Roſetta, for quitting the ſtomach of ſoil, &amp;c.</hi> p. 21</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For the</hi> Plague p. 89, 90, 120, 129, 141.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For the</hi> Plureſie p. 88, 136</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For the</hi> French-Pox p. 82. 117, 135</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For the</hi> Small-Pox p. 29, 91, 114.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>How to make purging Pruines, Raiſins, &amp;c.</hi> p. 61</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Several</hi> Purgations <hi>for ſeverall Diſeaſes.</hi> 1, 3, 7, 8, 9, 10, 39, 43, 44, 45, 52, 53, 60, 128.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>R.</head>
               <item>REſtoratives <hi>for weak perſons</hi> p. 30, 49, 61.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For the</hi> Running <hi>of the</hi> Reins. p. 89.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>S.</head>
               <item>SAlves <hi>or Ointments curing any wounds or Sores.</hi> p. 105, 121, 122</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For a</hi> Scald head p. 80</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For the</hi> Sciatica. p. 89, 101. 114.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For a greevouus</hi> Scowring p. 43. <hi>See</hi> Belly, Looſenes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For the</hi> Scurvy p. 52</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For the</hi> Spraining <hi>of the</hi> Sinews. p. 88, 99.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>To cauſe or provoke</hi> Sleep. p. 28, 30, 68, 78, 89.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For an ill</hi> Smell <hi>coming from the Noſe.</hi> p. 49</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:169737:8"/>
                  <hi>For foul and eating</hi> Sores. p. 34</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For the</hi> Spleen p. 54, 56, 82, 89</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Againſt the</hi> Stinging <hi>by Waſpes or Bees.</hi> p. 95</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For the Pain or</hi> Stitch <hi>in the</hi> Side. p. 17, 125</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>To clear the</hi> Stomach <hi>of ſoil</hi> p. 21, 75</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>To comfort &amp; ſtrengthen the</hi> Stomach p. 57. 77.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For a cold and weak</hi> Stomach. p. 16, 18, 26</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Againſt wind in the</hi> Stomach p. 21</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For the</hi> Stone <hi>or Gravel.</hi> p. 40, 41, 59, 75, 88 115, 11<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For the</hi> Stoppings <hi>in the Breſt</hi> p. 84, 140: <hi>See</hi> Oppilations, Tiſick</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For the</hi> Stoppings <hi>of the Lungs</hi> p. 12, 13, 84, 117</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For the</hi> Strangury p. 98</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For the</hi> Swelling <hi>of the Legs</hi> p: 108</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>To ſoften the hard</hi> Swelling <hi>of the Liver and Splen</hi> p. 32</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For all manner of</hi> Swellings p. 88</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For the</hi> Swelling <hi>of the Yard or Cods</hi> p. 103</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Divers ſorts of</hi> Syrops <hi>for divers Diſeaſes.</hi> p. 18 55, 57.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Divers ſorts of</hi> Suppoſitories <hi>for divers diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> p. 36, 37.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>T.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>FOr a ſore</hi> Throat p. 34, 35, 77, 112, 127.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For the</hi> Tiſick p. 140</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For a hollow</hi> Tooth p. 112</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>To faſten he</hi> Teeth p. 101.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:169737:9"/>
               <head>V.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>TO put away</hi> Venome <hi>from the Heart.</hi> p. 123</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For an</hi> Ulcer p. 88</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>How to make</hi> Unguentum-Nutritum. p. 122</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Receipts for</hi> Vomits, p. 24</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A</hi> Vomiting-Water p. 51</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>W.</head>
               <item>WArming <hi>Medicines for cold Diſeaſes</hi> p. 26, 38.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>To take away</hi> Warts, p. 107</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For thoſe that cannot hold their</hi> Water, p. 125</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For thoſe that cannot void</hi> Water. p. 97. 98, 125.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For</hi> weak <hi>&amp; convaleſcent perſons</hi> p. 30, 37, 49, 61</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For young Children that are</hi> Weak <hi>in their Limbs, &amp;c.</hi> p. 124</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>To heal a</hi> Whitflaw p. 108. See Biles, Fellon.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For</hi> Wind p. 14, 15, 21, 31, 36, 58, 76, 77.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For the</hi> Wind-Collick p. 76. 88</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>How to govern a</hi> Woman with Child <hi>before, in, and after the great work or Travel, and to cauſe an eaſie and quick Deliverance.</hi> p. 46</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For the</hi> Wormes. p. 13, 42, 88, 100</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For a</hi> Green-wound p. 85, 87</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>To oure all manner of Sores and</hi> Wounds. p. 105, 21</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Y.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>FOr the ſwelling of the</hi> Yard <hi>or Cods</hi> p. 103</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>For the Canker upon the</hi> Yard p. 100</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>To incarnats the skin of the</hi> Yard <hi>within</hi> p. 104.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:169737:9"/>
            <head>Moſt Excellent and approved MEDICINES AND REMEDIES For divers <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> and <hi>Maladies.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of <hi>Medicines</hi> that purge <hi>Choler.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Loes</hi> is the Juice of an <hi>Herb,</hi> The <hi>Doſe</hi> is from one dr. to two dr. in <hi>Subſtance;</hi> but in <hi>Infuſion</hi> from one dr. to three dr. It pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth <hi>Choler</hi> and <hi>Fleam,</hi> and helps the <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> of the <hi>Stomach</hi> and <hi>Head:</hi> but hurts the <hi>Hemorrhoides</hi> and <hi>Fundament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caſſia</hi> is a long, black, <hi>fiſtulous,</hi> round fruit, having a black ſubſtance within, it muſt by
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:169737:10"/>
freſhly extracted when it is uſed: and it is given to all Ages, to the weaker in one ounce and a half, to the ſtronger in 2. ounces, or 10. drachmes in the morning, and before Supper, in <hi>Bolus</hi> or <hi>Potion.</hi> It purgeth gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly without any offence, <hi>Choler</hi> and <hi>Fleam</hi> from the <hi>ſtomach,</hi> in the firſt waies; and is good in <hi>hot Fevers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Manna</hi> is a dew falling on <hi>Herbs, Trees, Stones:</hi> the beſt is of <hi>Calabria.</hi> The <hi>Doſe</hi> is from 6. drachmes to 2. ounces, or 3. ounces. It purgeth very gently <hi>fleam</hi> and <hi>yellow Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cytrine Mirabolins</hi> is a <hi>Fruit</hi> of the <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bians:</hi> the <hi>Doſe</hi> is from 2. drachmes to half an ounce in ſubſtance; but in infuſion from half an ounce to 2. ounces. They purge <hi>Choler</hi> from the <hi>Stomach,</hi> and are good in <hi>Fluxes,</hi> when moderate <hi>Aſtriction</hi> after purging is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired. They are naught in <hi>obſtructions;</hi> and their <hi>obſtruction</hi> is let, if they be rubbed with <hi>Oyl of ſweet Almonds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scammony</hi> is the <hi>Juice</hi> of an <hi>Hearb,</hi> the <hi>Doſe</hi> is from 5. grains to 12. grains. It worketh upon all <hi>humors</hi> ſtrongly; but eſpecially up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Choler</hi> and <hi>water.</hi> It hurteth the <hi>Heart, Liver, Stomach,</hi> out of his innate property; but is corrected with <hi>Aniſe-ſeeds, Dragant,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:169737:10"/>
Maſtick,</hi> the juice or infuſion of <hi>Damaſk Roſes,</hi> and the <hi>Conſerve</hi> of it is given from 1. ounce to 2. or 3. ounces. It purgeth <hi>Choler.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rhubarb</hi> is a thick <hi>Root</hi> from the <hi>Indies,</hi> dying like <hi>Saffron.</hi> It is corrected with the ſixth part of <hi>Spica Indica,</hi> or <hi>Cynamon;</hi> and is ſafely given without any <hi>Corrective.</hi> The <hi>Doſe</hi> is in ſubſtance from 2. drachmes to 3. and 4. drachmes. It purgeth gently <hi>Choler</hi> from the <hi>Stomach</hi> and the <hi>Liver,</hi> and taketh away <hi>Obſtructions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tamarindes</hi> are tart <hi>Dates,</hi> the <hi>Fruit</hi> of a wild <hi>Palm-Tree</hi> in the <hi>Indies,</hi> the neweſt are the beſt. The <hi>Doſe</hi> in infuſion or <hi>decoction</hi> in <hi>Whey</hi> is from 2. ounces to 5. ounces. It pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth <hi>yellow Choler,</hi> quencheth <hi>Thirſt,</hi> &amp; cures acute <hi>Fevers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whey</hi> is a <hi>Lenient</hi> and <hi>Laxative Medicine.</hi> The <hi>Doſe</hi> is 4. ounces to half a pound, and a pound.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of <hi>Medicines</hi> that purge <hi>Fleam.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>AGarick</hi> is growing on the <hi>Trunks</hi> or <hi>Bodies</hi> of <hi>Trees,</hi> as <hi>Toadſtooles.</hi> It is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe to the <hi>Stomach</hi> by reaſon of his lightnes. It ſwims uppermoſt, and ſo will provoke to <hi>vomit:</hi> But this ill quality is bridled by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:169737:11"/>
a third part of <hi>Ginger</hi> or <hi>Salgem.</hi> It is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken either in ſubſtance or in infuſion. In ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance it is taken from 1. drachme to 2. dr. And in infuſion from 2. drachmes to 3. dr. It purgeth groſſe roping <hi>Slyme,</hi> and tough <hi>Fleam,</hi> as alſo <hi>yellow Choler.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mechoacan</hi> an <hi>Indian Root,</hi> a kind of <hi>Bry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ony Root,</hi> which ſome call <hi>White Rhubarb.</hi> It is taken in powder, or grated from one drachm and a half, to 2 drachmes: It purgeth <hi>Fleam</hi> and <hi>watry humours</hi> without griping. It is good in old <hi>Head-aches, Feavers, intermit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Cholicks</hi> and <hi>Aſtinatical diſpoſitions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jalap</hi> is a kind of <hi>Mechoacan,</hi> and hath the ſame vertues. The <hi>Doſe</hi> is from one ſcruple to 2. ſcruples in ſtrong bodies. If one ſcruple or half a drachm be finely ſearced, it pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth very pleaſanty without griping, &amp; hath no taſte. When any other purge worketh ſlowly, give 1. ſcruple of this after it, and it will forward the other plentifully and ſafely.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Turbit</hi> is a <hi>Gum,</hi> and <hi>white Root,</hi> given in ſubſtance, and in infuſion, as <hi>Agaricks.</hi> His <hi>Correction</hi> is a third part of <hi>Ginger.</hi> It pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth tough and thick <hi>Fleam,</hi> and cures long <hi>Flegmatick Diſeaſes,</hi> as <hi>Apoplexies, Epilep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, Madneſs, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:169737:11"/>The <hi>Seeds</hi> of <hi>Carthamus</hi> or <hi>Lincus</hi> is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven from 2. drachmes to 5. drachmes. It pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth <hi>Fleam</hi> and <hi>Water.</hi> It is a friend to the <hi>Stomach.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Colocynthis</hi> is the <hi>Fruit</hi> of a <hi>wild Gourd:</hi> his <hi>Pulp</hi> which is in uſe muſt be <hi>white,</hi> and <hi>freſh.</hi> It is corrected with <hi>Ginger, Cynamon, Cloves, Maſtick, Dragant.</hi> It is ſeldom given alone, but in infuſion with other <hi>purging decoctions,</hi> or added to <hi>Pills.</hi> It purgeth <hi>Fleam, Choler, mucous humours.</hi> It is good in great and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veterate <hi>Head-aches, Megrims, Epilepſies, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poplexies, Vertigoes,</hi> or <hi>Giddineſs, Gout, Sciati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca, Aſthyma, Flegmatick Cough,</hi> and <hi>difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> of <hi>breathing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Harmodactils</hi> is a known <hi>Root.</hi> The <hi>Doſe</hi> is one drachm, or one dr. and a half; his <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections</hi> are <hi>Cynamon</hi> or <hi>Ginger.</hi> It is more u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with <hi>Decoctions,</hi> with other <hi>Purges,</hi> then alone. It purgeth <hi>groſſe Fleam</hi> from the <hi>Joynts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Elacerium</hi> is the <hi>Juice</hi> of <hi>Wild Cowcum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</hi> The <hi>Doſe</hi> is from one grain, to one grain and a half, or 2. grains or 3. grains in robuſt bodies. It purgeth <hi>Water, Fleam</hi> and <hi>Choler</hi> ſtrongly, but churliſhly. It is <hi>corrected</hi> with <hi>Tragacanth, Maſtick, Cynamon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euphorbium</hi> is a <hi>Gum:</hi> the <hi>Doſe</hi> is from one grain to a drachm, and in mixtures with <hi>Pills</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:169737:12"/>
to 10. grains. This is rarely uſed alone, but in <hi>Pills</hi> called <hi>Pills</hi> of <hi>Euphorbium.</hi> The <hi>Doſe</hi> is one dr. It helps <hi>Cholicks,</hi> and very cold <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> of the <hi>Belly, Head</hi> and <hi>Joynts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mirabolana Chebula</hi> drawes away <hi>Fleam.</hi> The <hi>Doſe</hi> in ſubſtance is from 2. drachmes to 4 drachmes; in infuſion from 1. dr. to 6. dr. They purge <hi>Fleam,</hi> are good for the <hi>Sinews,</hi> and againſt <hi>Viturnas,</hi> and <hi>ſleep-Diſeaſes:</hi> they whet the <hi>Wit,</hi> and comfort the <hi>Stomach.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mirabola Bellerica</hi> muſt be uſed as <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blica.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Apopanas</hi> is a <hi>Liquor ferule:</hi> the beſt is white within, and yellow without. It is given from 1. drachm to 2. drachmes. It is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected with <hi>Mastick</hi> and <hi>Spike.</hi> It purgeth rough <hi>Fleam</hi> from the <hi>Brain, Sinews,</hi> and <hi>Breſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vitrum Antimonii</hi> the <hi>Glaſſe</hi> of <hi>Antimony,</hi> purgeth and vomiteth and avoideth <hi>Water</hi> and <hi>Fleam</hi> very much; beſides other humors. It is given in ſubſtance finely powdered from 1. grain to 2. grains rubbed in a <hi>Morter</hi> with <hi>Oyl</hi> of <hi>Nutmeg:</hi> in infuſion from 4 grains to 7. grains, in <hi>White wine, Claret</hi> or <hi>Sack.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:169737:12"/>
               <head>Of <hi>Medicines</hi> purging <hi>Melancholy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sena</hi> is the beſt from <hi>Alexandria,</hi> with green Leaves and thin, and a little whitiſh. The <hi>Doſe</hi> in powder is one drachm, in infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or decoction half an ounce or 6. dr. It is corrected with <hi>Ginger, Cloves,</hi> and a ſprig of <hi>Time, Aniſe-ſeeds,</hi> and ſweet <hi>Fennel-Seeds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Epithymum</hi> is given in powder to 2. dr. in decoction, from half an ounce to 2. ounces. It muſt be but little boyled, nor given in the heat of Summer. It is corrected with <hi>Salgem,</hi> and purgeth <hi>black Choler,</hi> and <hi>Hypocondriacal winds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Black Helebore,</hi> it ſhould have a black root full byting. The <hi>Doſe</hi> is in powder from half a ſcruple to a ſcruple, or more. It purgeth black or yellow <hi>Choler</hi> from all the body, and that ſtrongly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fumitary</hi> evacuates <hi>melancholy humours.</hi> The juyce is given to 2. ounces in decoction. The Hearb is put from 3. ounces to 5. or 6. ounces in <hi>Whey:</hi> you may ſtrengthen his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration with a little <hi>Wormwood</hi> put to it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:169737:13"/>
                  <hi>Mirabolans Indian</hi> ſo called, it purgeth black <hi>Choler</hi> and burnt. The <hi>Doſe</hi> is in ſubſtance from 2 dr. to 4 dr. in infuſion from 4 dr. to 10 drachmes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lapis Aramenus</hi> purgeth black <hi>Choler,</hi> and all groſſe, thick, clammy, muddy <hi>humours.</hi> It is given from 1 dr. to 3 dr.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lapis Lazuli aſtillatus</hi> is prepared as <hi>Lapis Armenus,</hi> which muſt be by waſhing them 20 times with water in a Morter: after be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing powdered, rub the ſame, and waſh it 10. times with <hi>Roſe-water.</hi> The <hi>Doſe</hi> of <hi>Lapis Lazuli</hi> waſhed is from 1 drachm to 2 dr. It purgeth <hi>Melancholy</hi> plentifully; but troubles more the body then <hi>Lapis Aremenus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Polipodie</hi> of the <hi>Oak</hi> freſh gathered, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth the Belly, but floweth. If the Roots be boyled, it purgeth burnt <hi>Choler</hi> and <hi>Fleam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>Polipodie</hi> is corrected with <hi>Aniſe-ſeeds, Ginger, Cloves</hi> and <hi>Cynamon.</hi> The <hi>Doſe</hi> is from half an ounce to an ounce.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An <hi>Infuſion</hi> Purging <hi>Fleam.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke of the five opening roots of <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pody</hi> of the <hi>Oak,</hi> of each 2. drachmes, of <hi>Hyſop, Camphery</hi> Flowers, of <hi>Roſemary, Stachadoes,</hi> of each 2. little handfuls, of <hi>Aniſe-ſeeds,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:169737:13"/>
Fennel-ſeeds, Carua-ſeeds,</hi> of each 1. drachm, <hi>Licoriſh</hi> 3. drachmes, <hi>Raſins</hi> ſtoned 2. drachmes: boyl them in a Pinte of water; to half of this take 4. or 6. ounces <hi>Agarick</hi> 1. dra. and half, or 4. ſcruples of <hi>Ginger</hi> 1. dr. of <hi>Salgem</hi> 5. grains: Infuſe it all night warm, in the morning ſtrain it out hard, and put to it 2. drachmes of <hi>Diaphenicon,</hi> half an ounce of <hi>Syrrop</hi> of <hi>Violets,</hi> or <hi>Syrrop</hi> of <hi>Roſes,</hi> of which <hi>Agarick</hi> 1. ounce mingle, make a <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> this will purge <hi>Fleam</hi> plentifully.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An <hi>Infuſion</hi> purging <hi>Choler.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke of <hi>Damask Roſes</hi> 2. ounces, of <hi>Rhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barb</hi> 2. dr. and half, of <hi>Spikenard</hi> 1. ſcruple, of <hi>Orcyn</hi> 1. ſcruple: Cut all ſmall and infuſe them in a <hi>Quart</hi> of <hi>Clarified-Whey,</hi> all night; and in the morning ſtrain it gently, and put to it 1. oun. of the <hi>Syrrop</hi> of <hi>Roſes</hi> or <hi>Violets.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An <hi>Infuſion</hi> Purging <hi>Melancholy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Fumetary, Epithymum, Flowers</hi> or <hi>Leaves</hi> of <hi>Burrage</hi> and <hi>Bugloſſe,</hi> of each half a good handfull, <hi>Polypodie</hi> of the <hi>Oak</hi> 1. ounce, <hi>Sena</hi> half an ounce, <hi>Fennel ſeeds</hi> 2. d. <hi>Whey</hi> three <hi>Pintes:</hi> Infuſe, and boyl it to a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:169737:14"/>
                  <hi>Quart:</hi> whereunto add 2. ounces of the <hi>Syr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rop</hi> of <hi>Roſes</hi> ſolutive. The <hi>Doſe</hi> is half a pound: you may quicken a draught with 1. dra. of <hi>Electuary</hi> of <hi>Roſes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An <hi>Infuſion</hi> Purging both <hi>Choler and Fleam.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke of <hi>Rhubarb</hi> 1. dra. of <hi>Agarick</hi> freſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly trochiſcated 2. ſcru. <hi>Cynamon</hi> 1. ſcruple <hi>Ginger</hi> half a ſcruple: Infuſe them all night in 2. ounces of <hi>Endive-water,</hi> and 1. ounce of <hi>White wine:</hi> In the morning ſtrain it out hard, and add <hi>Caſſia,</hi> or the <hi>Lenitive Electuary</hi> of <hi>Diacatholicon,</hi> or <hi>Diaphenicon</hi> half an ounce, <hi>Syrrop</hi> of <hi>Violets,</hi> 2. drachmes: mingle them and make a Potion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An <hi>Infuſion</hi> Purging all <hi>Humors.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke of <hi>Sena</hi> 3. drachmes, <hi>Ginger, Epithy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum,</hi> of each 1. d. <hi>Fennel-ſeeds</hi> 2. ſcruples, <hi>Mary-gold-Flowers</hi> a ſmall handfull: infuſe them in 6. ounces of <hi>Water:</hi> after boyl them to 4. ounces, and ſtrain them: In which infuſe <hi>Rhubarb, Agarick</hi> 4. ſcruples, <hi>Cynamon,</hi> and <hi>Ginger,</hi> of each 1. ſcruple: after a gentle Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phering on the fire, ſtrain them again, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:169737:14"/>
add thereunto <hi>Manna</hi> half an ounce, <hi>Syrrop</hi> of <hi>Roſes</hi> with <hi>Agarick</hi> 1. ounce: mingle them and make a Potion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An Opening and Cooling <hi>Julip,</hi> for <hi>Choler</hi> and <hi>burnt Humors.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke of <hi>Barly</hi> 2. ſmall handfuls, <hi>Savory</hi> with the <hi>Roots, Maiden-hair, Liverwort, Sorrel,</hi> of each half a good handfull, of <hi>Roots</hi> of <hi>Graſſe,</hi> and <hi>Fennel,</hi> of each half an ounce, of the <hi>Flower cold Seeds</hi> of each 2. drachms: boyl them in <hi>Water</hi> unto 16. ounces; in which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe <hi>Sena,</hi> half an ounce, <hi>Tamarinds, Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>podie,</hi> of each 3. drachmes, <hi>Mechoaean, Jalop</hi> and <hi>Hermodactils,</hi> of each 2. drachmes, <hi>Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, Aniſe-ſeeds</hi> and <hi>Licoriſh,</hi> of each 1. drachm, <hi>Currents bruiſed</hi> half an ounce, of <hi>Burrage, Bugloſſe</hi> and <hi>Roſemary-flowers</hi> a ſmall handful: infuſe theſe warm; then boyl them untill 5. ounces of <hi>Succory-water</hi> be conſumed: then ſtrain them, and add the expreſſion of 4. ſcruples of <hi>Rhubarb</hi> infuſed in 3. ounces of <hi>Manna,</hi> and <hi>Syrrop</hi> of <hi>Roſes,</hi> of each 1. ounce, of the <hi>Chriſtalls</hi> of <hi>Tarter</hi> 1. dra. mingle them: The <hi>Doſe</hi> is 4. or 5. ounces every morning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:169737:15"/>
               <head>A Cooling Opening <hi>Julip.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke 4. ounces of <hi>Succory-water,</hi> 2. ounces of <hi>Roſe-water,</hi> of <hi>Syrrop</hi> of <hi>Violets,</hi> and <hi>Syrrop</hi> of <hi>Roſes</hi> ſolutive, of each half an ounce, <hi>Oyl</hi> of <hi>Vitriol</hi> two or three drops; to make a <hi>Julip</hi> of a gratefull tartneſſe: take hereof two or three ſpoonfuls at a <hi>Time.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the <hi>Lungs</hi> ſtopt with <hi>Soyl.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Elycampany Roots</hi> well dryed, <hi>Licoriſh</hi> and <hi>Aniſe-ſeeds,</hi> of each an ounce, <hi>Flowers</hi> of <hi>Brimſtone</hi> half an ounce, <hi>Sugar-Candy</hi> 6. ounces: make it all into powder, and eat half a ſpoonfull or more thrice a day. Alſo take this direction as followeth: Boyl in a Pottle of water, of <hi>Hyſop, Maiden-hair, Scabeous, Foal-foot, Horehound,</hi> of each a good hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, of <hi>Aniſe ſeed</hi> bruiſed, <hi>Licoriſh</hi> ſliced, <hi>Raſins</hi> ſtoned, and <hi>Dates,</hi> of each 3 ounces: boyl it to a Quart, and ſweeten it with <hi>Sugar,</hi> whereof take a little draught warm three or four times a day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:169737:15"/>
               <head>Another for the ſame purpoſe.</head>
               <p>TAke half a Pinte of <hi>Hyſop-water,</hi> and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much <hi>Aquavitae,</hi> which put in a diſh over the fire, on a Chafindiſh of Coles; whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to add 1. ounce of <hi>Sugar-Candy</hi> beaten, and ſtir it often with a ſpoon; and take thereof a ſpoonfull in a day warm:</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A Mead</hi> for the ſame.</head>
               <p>BOyl one Gallon of <hi>Honey</hi> with half a Pinte of <hi>Water,</hi> and skim it; then with four Gallons of <hi>Water,</hi> ſtill skiming for two hours gently; and with it <hi>Raſins</hi> ſtoned 4. oun. <hi>Elycampany-roots</hi> 2. oun. <hi>Fennel-Roots, Althea, Polypodie,</hi> of each 1. ounce, <hi>Maiden-hair, Foal-foot,</hi> of each a like quantity, <hi>Sage, Betony, Scabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, Hyſop,</hi> of each a good handful, <hi>Aniſe-ſeeds</hi> 1. oun. If an Eg fall to the bottom, it is ſtrong enough; Cool, and turn it into wooden veſſell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A Powder</hi> to kill and purge forth <hi>Worms.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke of <hi>Wormſeed</hi> 2. ounces, of <hi>Sena</hi> half an ounce, of <hi>Corianders</hi> prepared, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:169737:16"/>
                  <hi>Harts-horn</hi> of each 1. dra. <hi>Rhubarb</hi> 2. drachmes, dry <hi>Rue</hi> 3. drachmes: mingle them together. The <hi>Doſe</hi> is 2. drachmes at a time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A very good <hi>Powder</hi> to be taken Evening and Morning and at Bed-time againſt the <hi>Epilepſies.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Pyony-ſeed,</hi> and <hi>Miſtletoe</hi> of the Oak, of each 1. dra. of the <hi>great beaſt</hi> an ounce and half, <hi>Red Corall, Nutmegs, Muſtard-ſeed</hi> Clarified, and the Root of <hi>white Dictamne,</hi> and <hi>Corianders</hi> prepared, of each 1. drachm: mingle them and take a little at a time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A <hi>Powder</hi> or groſſely prepared <hi>Dredge</hi> to be taken in the Morning, and after meales, to help <hi>Concoction,</hi> to comfort the <hi>Brain,</hi> to break <hi>Wind,</hi> and to make a <hi>ſweet Breath.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Licoriſh</hi> cut ſmall, <hi>Aniſe-ſeed-Comfets</hi> with one <hi>skin of Sugar,</hi> of each 2. ounces, <hi>Comfets of ſweet Fennel-ſeeds</hi> with one <hi>skin of ſugar, Coryanders</hi> prepared and <hi>Carua-ſeeds,</hi> of each 1. ounce, <hi>White Ginger, Cynamon, Calamus Aromaticus, Nutmeg,</hi> of each 1. dra.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:169737:16"/>
cut very ſmall, of the <hi>Lozanges of acomaticum roſarum,</hi> of <hi>Manus Chriſti</hi> with <hi>Chymical Oyl of Cynamon</hi> &amp; <hi>Cloves,</hi> and <hi>Lozanges of Dyam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra,</hi> of each alike cut into ſmall peeces half an ounce, to be taken about a ſpoonfull at the times aforeſaid.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A Confection</hi> for the ſame.</head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Aniſe-ſeeds, Fennel-ſeeds, Carua-ſeeds, Coriander-ſeeds, White Ginger,</hi> of each 3. Drachmes and half, <hi>Calamus aromaticus, Nutmeg,</hi> of each 1. drachm, <hi>Cynamon, Licoriſh,</hi> ſmall cut, of each 2. drachmes, <hi>White-ſugar</hi> diſſolved with <hi>Roſe-water</hi> one pound and half, <hi>Musk</hi> 2. grains: Make hereof <hi>a Confection</hi> to take in little morſels.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Powder <hi>for</hi> Bruiſes <hi>and againſt</hi> Congealed blood.</head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Mummy</hi> and <hi>Dragons blood</hi> and <hi>Terra ſigillata</hi> or <hi>Lemnia,</hi> of each two drachmes, <hi>Sperma Caeti</hi> 1. dra. <hi>Rhubarb</hi> half a drachm. Make hereof a <hi>Powder.</hi> The doſe is 1. drachm, 4. ſcruples.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:169737:17"/>
               <head>A good <hi>Conſerve</hi> in hot <hi>Peſtilent Fevers</hi> reſtoring the <hi>ſpirits conſumed with heat.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke the tart fleſh of <hi>Cytrons</hi> quite from the <hi>ſeeds</hi> with a wooden Inſtrument 3. pound, <hi>Water</hi> 1. pound, <hi>Sugar</hi> well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined 3. pound and a half: Boyl it in a glazed Pipkin, ſtirring it with a wooden Spatter untill it comes to the conſiſtance of a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A Phyſicall Bag</hi> to dry up and ſtay <hi>Rhumes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Milletſeed</hi> half a pound, <hi>Aniſe-ſeeds, Fennel-ſeeds, Carua-ſeeds, Comin-ſeeds, Camomile-flowers, Tops of Dill,</hi> of each 1. oun. make them hot in a pot, and put them into a Bag, and apply it hot to the head, or any part that hath a cold <hi>Rhume</hi> to trouble or <hi>Palſey</hi> it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A Phyſicall Bag</hi> or <hi>Quilt</hi> for a <hi>cold Stomach.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>dry Wormwood, Mints Aniſe-ſeeds</hi> 2. ounces, <hi>Rynds of Cytrons</hi> half an ounce,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:169737:17"/>
                  <hi>Galange, Cipporus, Cloves,</hi> of each alike, <hi>Maſtick Corall, Aniſe-ſeed-rootes,</hi> of each 2. drachms: make a <hi>Quilt</hi> for the <hi>Stomach.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For a <hi>Pain</hi> in the <hi>Side.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke one Pint of the <hi>Carminative Decocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> of <hi>Diacatholicon</hi> half an ounce, of <hi>Kitchin Sugar</hi> 3. ounces, of <hi>Oyl of Camomile</hi> 2. oun. of <hi>Salt</hi> a ſmall handfull: wherewith make a Gliſter; at night, take half an ounce of <hi>London-Treakle,</hi> diſſolve it in a draught of <hi>Camomile</hi> or <hi>Carduus-Poſſet,</hi> ſo drink it bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and ſweat after it: In your ſweating now and then drink a little <hi>Mace-Ale;</hi> alſo anoint the pained ſide with <hi>oyl of Dill</hi> hot, or make a <hi>quilt</hi> of <hi>Camomile</hi> or <hi>Mellilot-flowers,</hi> alſo the <hi>herb</hi> of <hi>Camomile</hi> and <hi>Pellitory of the wall,</hi> of each 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> good handfuls, of <hi>Dill-ſeed</hi> 4. ounces, of the <hi>ſeeds of Aniſe, Fennel, Comin,</hi> of each 2. ounces: make a <hi>quilt</hi> about the bigneſſe of two Trenchers ſquare. Then boyl this <hi>quilt</hi> in <hi>milk</hi> for half an hour; after preſſe it very well between two Trenchers; ſo apply it as hot as may be endured to the <hi>pained ſide</hi> all night.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:169737:18"/>
               <head>An Excellent <hi>Syrrop</hi> for a weak <hi>Stomach.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Cynamon</hi> groſſely bruiſed, <hi>Sea-worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood,</hi> of each a quarter of a pound, <hi>Red-Roſes</hi> 1. ounce, the <hi>Juyce of Quinces,</hi> and <hi>Sherry Sack</hi> one pint and 3. quarters: put them into a ſtone-bottle cloſe ſtopt, and ſet them to infuſe in a pot of warm water four and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hours: then take them out and give them one boyling or two: then ſtrain them, &amp; after boil the ſame into a Syrrop with a pound and a quarter of <hi>fine Sugar.</hi> Take hereof every morning two or three ſpoonfulls; ſo likewiſe in the Evening, either alone or in a little <hi>Mint-water.</hi> This Syrrop is very effectuall to ſtrengthen a weak <hi>Stomach</hi> &amp; <hi>Liver,</hi> to excite a dejected <hi>Appetite,</hi> to make the <hi>Bowels</hi> hardy and ſtrong, and to take away their weak weariſh tenderneſſe, and comfort their reten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive faculties.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A comfortable <hi>Syrrop</hi> to be taken againſt <hi>Melancholy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke the clear juyce of <hi>Burrage, Bugloſſe,</hi> and <hi>Pippins,</hi> of each half a pound.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:169737:18"/>
The Juyce of <hi>Sorrel, Endive</hi> and <hi>Hops,</hi> of each 2. ounces; <hi>Cynamon</hi> and <hi>yellow Sanders,</hi> of each 1. drachme: clarifie them with the white of an <hi>Eg,</hi> and boyl them into a <hi>Syr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rop</hi> with a pound and half of fine <hi>Sugar:</hi> then hang therein this tied in a Button, <hi>Saffron</hi> half a drachm, of <hi>Scarlet-Dye</hi> one drachm, 6. grains of <hi>Ambergreaſe,</hi> of <hi>Lignum Aloes</hi> one ſcruple.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the <hi>Green-Sickneſs.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke of <hi>Sena</hi> half a pound, <hi>Polipodie</hi> 4. ounces, <hi>Epithymum</hi> 2. ounces, <hi>Agarick, Rhubarb,</hi> of each one ounce, ſweet <hi>Fennel</hi> and <hi>Aniſe-ſeeds,</hi> of each an ounce &amp; half, <hi>Salſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perilla</hi> 5. ounces, <hi>Saſſafras</hi> one ounce. Make a Bag for three Gallons of new <hi>Ale;</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 2. or 3. dayes after it hath done work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, drink of it both evening and morning, without intermiſſion, the quantity of 5. ounces: about 2. or 3. dayes after the ending of this, bleed in the Arm; then reſt one day; after take the <hi>Steel-wine</hi> for a fortnight: then reſt for 2. or 3. dayes. Laſtly, take the <hi>Pills de tribus Farnelii,</hi> the quantity of half a drachm or ſomewhat more at a time, one hour at leaſt before Supper, thrice a week.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:169737:19"/>
               <head>Another for the <hi>Green-ſickneſſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FIrſt vomit; then for four or five dayes take <hi>Worm-wood-beer,</hi> and <hi>Conſerve</hi> of <hi>Worm-wood;</hi> afterwards purge as before once; then take the <hi>Steel-Electuary,</hi> or <hi>Steel-wine,</hi> uſing after that great exerciſe; after the <hi>Electuary</hi> uſe <hi>Worm-wood-beer,</hi> or <hi>Wine:</hi> and once in five or ſix dayes purge with the <hi>Extract Rhudius,</hi> a <hi>Pill</hi> ſo called; or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe as before; and ſeven or eight dayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the time of the Courſes, or towards the new Moon, bleed in the foot; uſe the <hi>Steel-wine</hi> ſet down in <hi>London-diſpenſitory,</hi> taking from half an ounce to an ounce, or the <hi>Steel-wine</hi> thus: In a quart of <hi>White-wine</hi> put half an ounce of prepared <hi>Steel,</hi> and 1. drach. of <hi>Cloves</hi> and <hi>Mace,</hi> and more of this, take 2. ounces at the firſt according by degrees un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to 6. ounces.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Cooling Julip.</head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Barly-water, Sorrel-water,</hi> of each half a pound, <hi>Julip</hi> and <hi>Syrrop of Violets, Syr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rop of the Juice of Cytrons,</hi> of each 1. ounce, <hi>Oyl of Vitriol</hi> two or three drops: mingle them, make <hi>a Julip</hi> very pleaſing to Cool.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:169737:19"/>
               <head>To make the <hi>Pills of Roſetta</hi> for Quitting the <hi>Stomach</hi> of <hi>ſoil,</hi> and for helping <hi>Concoction.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke one pound of pure <hi>Aloes</hi> powdered and ſearced, and put it into an Earthen veſſel glazed, whereunto put ſo much <hi>Juice</hi> of <hi>Damask-Roſes,</hi> or <hi>Roſe-water</hi> as to make it of the conſiſtance of <hi>Honey:</hi> Then ſet it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a gentle fire of ſmall coles, in a glazed Pipkin: So let it vapour away til it be too thick to ſtir with a Spatter: Then put more <hi>Juice</hi> of <hi>Damask-Roſe,</hi> or <hi>Roſe-water</hi> to it, and do as is already ſaid; ſtill reiterating the ſame till ſeven pounds of the <hi>Juice</hi> or <hi>Roſe-water</hi> it ſelf be ſpent, and the Maſſe at laſt conduced keep for uſe. The <hi>Doſe</hi> is from 1. ſcruple, to 2. or 3. ſcruples.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Againſt <hi>Winde</hi> in the <hi>Stomach:</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke a pound of <hi>Sugar,</hi> a quarter of a pound of <hi>Aniſe-ſeeds,</hi> and the like quain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of <hi>Coriander-ſeeds:</hi> beat the ſeeds to a powder, and ſift them through a fine ſearcer: Then take four or five ſpoonfuls of <hi>Roſe-water;</hi> and boyl theſe to a Paſte: ſo make them up in the manner of <hi>Lozenges.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:169737:20"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>A Water</hi> for <hi>Sore Eyes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FIll a ſhell with <hi>white</hi> or <hi>Red-roſe-water,</hi> and therein diſſolve four graines of white <hi>Copperas</hi> over the fire, &amp; put therein ten ſeeds of <hi>Comin,</hi> and keep it for uſe, dropping now and then two or three drops in the <hi>Eyes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A Phyſicall Courſe</hi> for <hi>Sore Eyes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke of the <hi>Pils</hi> of <hi>Aureae Lucis,</hi> and <hi>Cochiae,</hi> of each 1. ſcruple, mingled well together. In the Morning and Evening eat the powder of <hi>Olibanum,</hi> and <hi>Maſtick</hi> in the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ap</hi> of an <hi>Apple,</hi> or <hi>Olibanum</hi> with the <hi>Conſerve</hi> of <hi>Roſes:</hi> Alſo waſh the <hi>Eyes</hi> with <hi>Eye-water,</hi> made with <hi>Tutty,</hi> quenched in <hi>Eye-bright-water,</hi> and a little <hi>Sugar-Candy.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another approved <hi>Water</hi> for the <hi>Eyes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke halfe a quarter of <hi>Red-roſe-water,</hi> and five <hi>Kirnels</hi> of a <hi>Quince</hi> ſliced very thin. Let them lie in the water two hours: then ſtrain the water, and put therein half a dra. of <hi>Tutty</hi> prepared, and two ſpoonfulls of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:169737:20"/>
                  <hi>Womans Milk:</hi> Drop a little now and then into the eyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A Receipt</hi> for the <hi>Mother.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke 2. ounces of <hi>Bayberries,</hi> the outward rinde being taken off, and being dryed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them into a fine powder, which mingle with half a Pint of <hi>honey,</hi> and ſo take morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Evening a ſpoonfull at a time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A Phyſical Courſe</hi> for provoking the <hi>Courſes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FIrſt purge thus, Take of the <hi>Powder</hi> of <hi>Hiera Picra ſimplex,</hi> of the <hi>Pilles de tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Fernelii,</hi> of <hi>Agarick trochiſcated,</hi> of each 1. ſcruple, of <hi>Caſtorium</hi> half a ſcruple, of <hi>Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical Oyl</hi> of <hi>Time</hi> four drops; make theſe up into <hi>Pilles</hi> with the <hi>Syrrop</hi> of <hi>Mogwort,</hi> to the number of ſix or ſeven: Let the Patient take them immediately after her firſt ſleep; Then ſleep again; The next day after let her take this <hi>Decoction:</hi> Boyl in <hi>Ale</hi> and <hi>white-wine,</hi> of each a Pinte, half <hi>unſet Hyſop, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet Time, Penny-royall, Mugwort, Germander,</hi> of each a good handfull, <hi>Madder, Smalledge, Parſley</hi> and <hi>Fennell-rootes</hi> ſteeped in <hi>wine,</hi> of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:169737:21"/>
each an ounce, <hi>Juniper</hi> and <hi>Cynamon,</hi> of each half an ounce. After they be well boyled, ſtrain them hard, and ſweeten the ſame with 3. ounces of the <hi>Syrrop of Mugwort,</hi> drink of this twice a day in the morning, and after noon about four of the clock, and four dayes after their accuſtomed time of flowing, open the <hi>Saphaena vein,</hi> and bleed the quantity of three or four ounces, to incite them down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; The <hi>Saphaena vein</hi> is running about the Inner Anckle; upon the foot towards the great Toe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Receipts</hi> for <hi>Vomits.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke of the <hi>Glaſſe of Antimony,</hi> pounded as ſmall as may be 5. grains: Infuſe the ſame all night in 4. ounces of <hi>White-wine,</hi> ſhaking it divers times, early in the morning pour out all the cleer part, whereunto add one ounce of <hi>Oxmiel Julinizans:</hi> ſo take it, drinking after every vomit a draught of <hi>Poſſet-Ale:</hi> Or take of <hi>Mercurius <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>itae</hi> 5. graines in a ſpoonfull of <hi>White-wine:</hi> Or take 2. ounces of the infuſion of <hi>Crocus Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tallorum:</hi> or take <hi>Warm-water</hi> wherein a <hi>Red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh-root</hi> hath been boyled, adding to it a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle <hi>Sallet-oyl,</hi> alſo a little <hi>Oxmiel of the ſquill</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:169737:21"/>
may be added. This vomit is taken ſpecially for the weakneſſe of the <hi>Stomach</hi> and for four or five dayes together; it is taken for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling the <hi>Flegmatick,</hi> and <hi>Malign humours.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A Receipt</hi> of a <hi>Peſſary</hi> for the <hi>Mother.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Benjamin, Storax, Cloves,</hi> of each 1. dr. <hi>Musk</hi> 6. graines, <hi>Civet</hi> 4. graines, powder them, &amp; with <hi>Bumbaſt</hi> make <hi>a Peſſary,</hi> anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with oil of <hi>Maſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A Fomentation</hi> to provoke the <hi>Courſes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke the <hi>Rootes</hi> of <hi>Madder, Eringus, Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, Smalledge, Parſley, Graſſe, Lillies,</hi> and <hi>Marſh-Mallowes,</hi> of each 4. ounces, <hi>Penny-royall, Fetherfew,</hi> of each a good handfull, of <hi>Parſley, Smalledge, Ceſſely, Feune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeke, Althea,</hi> of each one ounce of <hi>Comin, Flowers</hi> a good handfull: boyl theſe in two parts, one part <hi>Water,</hi> and one part <hi>Wine,</hi> Foment the region of the Womb very well.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:169737:22"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>An heating Fomentation</hi> for a cold <hi>Stomach.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Red-roſes, Mints, Worm-wood, Time, Sage, Marjorum,</hi> of each a good handfull, <hi>Ginger, Cloves, Cynamon,</hi> of each 2. ounces, <hi>Citron-Pilles</hi> half an ounce: boyl theſe in a quart of <hi>Red-wine,</hi> and foment the <hi>Stomach</hi> with it hot, dipping in the ſame a piece of <hi>ſcarlet-cloth,</hi> preſſing out the Liquor with two Trenchers. Alſo this may be made more comfortable by putting to it 1. drachm of the <hi>Spices</hi> of <hi>Aromaticum roſatum.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A Cooling Fomentation</hi> for an hot <hi>Liver.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke of <hi>Oyl of Roſes</hi> 2. ounces, <hi>Oyl of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>momile</hi> 1. ounce, <hi>Juice of Succory</hi> and <hi>Orenges,</hi> of each 1. ounce and half, <hi>Claret-tart-wine</hi> 1. ounce: mingle theſe, and with a ſpunge or linen clout foment the region of the <hi>Liver;</hi> it's good in hot <hi>Fevers.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:169737:22"/>
               <head>An <hi>Epithem</hi> for the <hi>forehead</hi> to drive away <hi>head-aches.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Roſe-water</hi> four ounces, <hi>Oyl</hi> of <hi>Roſes</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. ounce, <hi>Roſe-vineger</hi> half an ounce, the <hi>white of an Eg</hi> beaten in the ſame, wherein dip <hi>Linen clothes</hi> cold, or but milk warm, and apply them to the <hi>forehead</hi> to aſſwage <hi>head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aches,</hi> and repell hot <hi>vapours.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An <hi>Epithem</hi> to <hi>Cool</hi> and <hi>open Obſtructions</hi> of the <hi>Liver.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Agrimony, Endive, Succory</hi> with the <hi>roots,</hi> of each a good handfull, <hi>Wormwood</hi> half a handfull, <hi>Succory-Flowers</hi> 2. ſmall hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls, of the <hi>four cold great</hi> and <hi>leſſerſeeds,</hi> of each 1. drachm and half, <hi>Lupines</hi> 3. drachmes, <hi>Copper as</hi> all the <hi>Saunders</hi> of each 1. d. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odoratus</hi> 1. ſcruple: put theſe into a Bag, and boyl them in half a pinte of <hi>Endive-water,</hi> add 2. ounces of each <hi>Vineger,</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> and apply it to the <hi>Liver,</hi> luke-warm, preſſed with your hand.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:169737:23"/>
               <head>An <hi>Epithem</hi> to cauſe <hi>Sleep.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Henbane, Lettice-leaves, Flowers of water-Lillies, Violets,</hi> of each a good hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, <hi>ſeeds of Poppy, Lettice, Dill, Henbane,</hi> of each half an ounce: bruiſe all, and ſowe them between two linen clothes, and apply them to the <hi>forehead.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An <hi>Inceſſe</hi> for the <hi>Piles,</hi> ſwelling hard and painfull.</head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Henbane-Leaves</hi> 4. good handfuls; <hi>Mullet</hi> and <hi>Plantane,</hi> of each two good handfuls, <hi>Linſeed</hi> 2. ounces: boyl it in a Gallon of <hi>Milk,</hi> ſtrain it, and ſet the Fundament to bathe in it upon a cloſe-ſtool; afterwards ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply <hi>dubble clothes</hi> dipped therein.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A Bath</hi> to <hi>clenſe</hi> the <hi>skin</hi> of <hi>Scabbs, Scurſe,</hi> and ſuch like.</head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Red-dock-roots, Bryony-roots, Elycam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, Wake Robbin-roots, Serpentary</hi> or <hi>Dragon-roots,</hi> of each a pound, <hi>Mallowes, Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, Branck urcyn, Mercury, Beets, Scabius, Fumitary, Burrage, Sapomana, Haſtalaregis,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:169737:23"/>
Succory,</hi> of each a good handfull, <hi>Centary-flowers</hi> and <hi>roots,</hi> of each a good handfull, <hi>Lupines, Beanes</hi> and <hi>Peaſe,</hi> of each 2. ounces, <hi>Barly</hi> two good handfuls, <hi>Sena</hi> 4. ounces: boyl all in <hi>Water,</hi> for a Bath to bathe in, and give the Patient half a pound <hi>of each of Lupine Flower,</hi> and red <hi>Cycers</hi> into the Bath to rub himſelf withall.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A Receipt</hi> to bring out the <hi>Small Pox.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke two <hi>Figs</hi> ſliced, a ſpoonfull of <hi>Harts-horn</hi> ſteeped, a few <hi>Mary-gold-Flowers,</hi> and <hi>Tops,</hi> one <hi>Leaf of Carduus Benedictus,</hi> and a little <hi>Saffron:</hi> boyl them in <hi>Poſſet-Ale,</hi> and give the Patient to drink thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To hinder <hi>Dinting.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Beef-broth,</hi> and bathe the <hi>Scabs</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with; after take the <hi>Fat of Calves-Feet</hi> boyled and beaten white with <hi>May-dew</hi> and <hi>Roſe-water:</hi> anoint the face withall: Or take <hi>white-wine,</hi> and <hi>Butter,</hi> of each a quarter of a pound, boyl them together, and uſe to bathe the <hi>Face</hi> often, or melt <hi>ſalt-butter</hi> put into <hi>cold-water,</hi> &amp; ſo anoint the <hi>Face</hi> withall.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:169737:24"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>A Bath</hi> for <hi>cold Diſeaſes</hi> or <hi>Palſies.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BOyl <hi>Juniper-berries, Broom-ſeed</hi> 20. good handfuls, <hi>Penny-royall, Origanum, Hyſop, Time, Sage, Satureia, Bayberries, Roſe-mary, Camphery, Pellitory</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> of each 2. good handfuls, <hi>Guaicum, Saſſafraſs,</hi> of each 1. pound: boyl them in <hi>water</hi> enough to bathe them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A Lotion</hi> for the <hi>Feet</hi> to induce <hi>Sleep.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Malloes,</hi> and <hi>Lettice,</hi> of each 2. good handfuls, <hi>Poppy-heads,</hi> in number ten, the <hi>rindes</hi> of <hi>Mandrake-roots, Baum,</hi> of each 1. oun. <hi>Flowers of Water-Lillies, Mellilot,</hi> of each a good handful, <hi>Dil-ſeed</hi> half an oun: boyl them in water; wherein waſh and bath the feet bed-ward; but do not dry them, and wrap them up in a cloth wet in the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A good <hi>Reſtorative</hi> for weak Convaleſcent perſons after a long and tedious <hi>ſickneſſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Pine-Apple-Kirnels, Pyſtaches,</hi> of each 4. ounces, fine <hi>White-Sugar</hi> half a
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:169737:24"/>
pound, <hi>Red Corall</hi> 1. drachm and half, <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon</hi> 1. drachm, <hi>ſpecies de gemmis Frigide</hi> 2. drachmes, <hi>Nutmegs</hi> half a drachm, <hi>Mace</hi> 5. grains, <hi>Conſerve of Burrage, Cytron-Pils</hi> preſerved, of each 1. ounce and half, <hi>Pearl</hi> 1. dram and half, <hi>white Burrage-water;</hi> make paſte, and yce it over with <hi>Sugar,</hi> &amp; <hi>Cynamon.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To make a <hi>Caudle</hi> for reſtoring <hi>good Blood.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>white-wine</hi> and <hi>water,</hi> of each a like quantity, <hi>Roſe-water</hi> one ſpoonfull, two <hi>Yelks of Egs</hi> ſweetened wel with <hi>Sugar</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with ſome <hi>Cynamon:</hi> boyl it a while, ſo drink thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A Powder</hi> againſt the <hi>winde</hi> in the <hi>Womb.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Cynamon</hi> 1. dra. <hi>Saffron</hi> half a drachm, <hi>Caſſia Lignea</hi> 2. ſcr. <hi>white Amber</hi> 1. ſcruple: mingle them, make <hi>a Powder,</hi> and give it in <hi>white Lillie-water</hi> or <hi>Lark Spur.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Cynamon, Saffron,</hi> of each 1. ſcruple, <hi>Borax</hi> 4. ſcr. give it in <hi>Mugworth-water.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:169737:25"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>A Pultes</hi> to binde the <hi>Belly</hi> in <hi>Fluxes,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from a cold <hi>Cauſe</hi> to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to the <hi>Belly.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Toſtes of bread</hi> ſteeped in <hi>Vineger</hi> 6. ou. beat it in a morter, and add <hi>Mace, Maſtick, Mirtle-berries, Stones of Raſins, Cloves, Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany, Flowers of Pomgranats,</hi> of each 1. ounce, <hi>Oyl of Worm-wood,</hi> and <hi>Mints,</hi> of each 2. ounces: make a <hi>Cataplaſm.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A Pultes</hi> to ſoften the hard <hi>ſwelling of the Liver and Splene.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Marſh-Mallow-roots,</hi> of each 3. oun. <hi>Malloes, Violets Holy-oaks,</hi> or each 3 good handfuls, <hi>Flowers of Camomile, Mellilot,</hi> of each 1. good handfull, <hi>Figs</hi> ſix, <hi>Tops of worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood</hi> 2. ſmall handfuls: boil them in water untill they be tender, and ſtrain them in a courſe ſearce; then add <hi>Flower of the Flowers of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>momile, Aniſe-ſeeds,</hi> of each 1. ounce, <hi>Flowers of Lin-ſeed, Fenny-greeke, Gooſe-greaſe,</hi> and <hi>Oyl</hi> of <hi>Camomile, Lillies, Freſh-butter, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row</hi> of <hi>a Calf, Oyl</hi> of <hi>Flowers de Luce,</hi> of each 1. ounce: mingle them, make a <hi>Pultes,</hi> whereunto add a little <hi>Vineger.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:169737:25"/>
               <head>A Pultes <hi>to ripen and ſupporate</hi> Biles <hi>and</hi> Tumors.</head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Marſh-Mallowes</hi> and <hi>Mallow-Roots,</hi> half a pound, <hi>Mallowes</hi> 1. good handful<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Bread</hi> 1. pound: Boyl them in <hi>water,</hi> and ſtrain them through a ſearcer, and with 4. oun. of <hi>Barrowes-greaſe</hi> make a <hi>Pultes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Pultes <hi>for</hi> Bruiſes.</head>
               <p>TAke of both the <hi>Camphery-roots</hi> of each 3. ounces, <hi>Camomile</hi> and <hi>Mellilot,</hi> of each 2. good handfuls, <hi>Saffron</hi> 1. ſcruple, <hi>Bean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>-flowers</hi> 2. ounces, <hi>Fennegreek</hi> 1. ounce: boyl them in <hi>water</hi> and add <hi>Worm-wood</hi> and <hi>Comin-ſeed</hi> of each half an ounce: make <hi>a Pultes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Pultes <hi>to allay</hi> heat and <hi>Inflamma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in any part.</head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Marſh Mallow-roots</hi> 3. ounces, <hi>Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lowes</hi> with the <hi>roots, Violets, Blank <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, Chick-weed,</hi> of each a good handfull, <hi>Flowers of Camomile, Violets</hi> powdered<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and <hi>Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 1. ſmall handfull: boyl <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem in fat <hi>Mutter-broth,</hi> or <hi>water,</hi> and add <hi>Hoggs-greaſe</hi> half a pound, make <hi>a Pultes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:169737:26"/>
               <head>A <hi>Gargle</hi> for inflammation in the Throat, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Plantine, Cinque-foil, Bramble-Leaves, Columbine, Straw-berry-Leaves, Honey-ſuckles, Red-Roſe-leaves, Jewsears, Sage,</hi> of each half a good handful, <hi>Barley</hi> one ounce, <hi>Licoriſh</hi> half an ounce<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> boyl them in water, and to one pound ad <hi>Melcoſatum</hi> four ounces, <hi>Allom</hi> one dr: make a <hi>Gargle</hi> to be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed luke-warm. And for ſore throats you may put to the aforeſaid one dr. of <hi>Salpruneliae</hi> to cool, cleanſe and dry more. This <hi>Salpruneliae</hi> in <hi>Ale</hi> with <hi>Honey</hi> will cure <hi>Sore-throats</hi> very well: If the ſore in the <hi>Mouth,</hi> or <hi>Throat</hi> be <hi>foul</hi> and <hi>Sordid,</hi> to this <hi>Gargle</hi> you may add <hi>Aegyptiacum</hi> allayed firſt with <hi>Vineger,</hi> and <hi>Honey</hi> of <hi>Roſes,</hi> or take <hi>Plantine water</hi> half a pound, <hi>Syrrop</hi> of <hi>Mulberries</hi> 3 ounces, and a little <hi>Oyl</hi> of <hi>Vitriol,</hi> to make it a little tart.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>For</hi> foul <hi>and</hi> Eating Sores.</head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Sublimate</hi> 4 grains, <hi>Plantine</hi> &amp; <hi>Roſe-water,</hi> of each 3 ounces: diſſolve it, and touch the place and <hi>Gargle</hi> ſometimes luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warm.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:169737:26"/>
               <head>A <hi>Gargle</hi> to draw <hi>Fleam.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Sage, Roſe-mary, Time, Origan,</hi> of each one good handfull; boyl them very well, and to half a pound put <hi>Oxmiel</hi> three ounces, <hi>Muſtard</hi> one or two good ſpoonfuls; or elſe boyl <hi>Sage</hi> in <hi>Vineger,</hi> and put to it <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard</hi> and <hi>Honey.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A Gargle</hi> for <hi>Sore Throats,</hi> called in the ſhops <hi>Mouth-water</hi> made but once for all the year, in the ſpring.</head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Woodbine-leaves,</hi> and <hi>Flowers</hi> halfe a peck <hi>Salendine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Lawrell,</hi> or <hi>Spurge, Sage, Rue, Mary gold-tops, Cytron, Roſe-mary-tops, Cinquefoile, Valerian, Agrimony, Perry-winkle, St. Johns-wort, Veronica,</hi> or <hi>Speed-well, white Collumbine leaves, Scabious, Scrophu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lania,</hi> of each a good handfull; Boyl them in a Galon of <hi>running water</hi> to the Eaſt, into two parts, ſtanding firſt one night in infuſion; then being boyled ſtrain them hard, and adde one ounce of <hi>Alom of the Cork,</hi> and four ounces of <hi>Honey;</hi> Then boyl it again, and skim it as long as any that riſeth, afterward let it ſettle one night; In the morning pour out the clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, which keep for uſe, putting thereunto a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 4 ounces of <hi>Vineger.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:169737:27"/>
               <head>A Gargle <hi>for an</hi> unſavory breath.</head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Roſe-water, Mirtle water, Orenge-Flower-water,</hi> of each 2. oun; <hi>Musk</hi> 3. gra. <hi>Amber-greaſe</hi> 6. grains, <hi>Salt</hi> a little more; <hi>Musk</hi> and <hi>Amber-greaſe</hi> you may put in for greater perſons.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A Moderate</hi> ſuppoſitory <hi>to</hi> looſen <hi>the</hi> Body.</head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Honey</hi> thickned 1. ounce, <hi>hieriae ſpecies, Hierae picrae &amp; aloes,</hi> or <hi>Agarick</hi> 1. ſcruple, <hi>Salt</hi> half a ſcruple, or add <hi>Salgem,</hi> or <hi>Muſtard</hi> 2. ſcruples: make a <hi>Suppoſitory.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A ſtronger</hi> Suppoſitory.</head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Honey</hi> thickned half an ounce, <hi>Scamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, Salt,</hi> of each 1. ſcruple: or take <hi>Honey</hi> concrete 2. ounces, <hi>Euphorbium</hi> half a ſcruple, <hi>powder of Colloquintida</hi> 5. gra. <hi>powder of white Hellebore</hi> 2. ounces, <hi>Salt</hi> 1. ounce, <hi>Hierae picrae</hi> half an ounce: make a <hi>Suppoſitory.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Suppoſitory for <hi>Winde.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Honey</hi> congealed 1. ounce, <hi>ſeeds of Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, Rue, Comin, Aniſe, Carua,</hi> of each
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:169737:27"/>
1. ſcruple, <hi>Colloquintida</hi> half a ſcruple, <hi>Salt</hi> 1. drachm: Theſe will make a good <hi>Suppoſitory</hi> for <hi>winde.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Suppoſitory <hi>to ceaſe</hi> Pain.</head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Opium, Saffron, Caſtor,</hi> of each half a ſcruple, with boyled <hi>Honey</hi> or <hi>Wax,</hi> and <hi>Oil of water-Lillies;</hi> make <hi>Suppoſitories</hi> with long ſtrings to them, to draw them out at pleaſure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Nouriſhing Gliſters <hi>to be given to</hi> weak per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, <hi>or when they cannot ſwallow by reaſon of ſome impediment; or when they vomit up all they eat to the hazard of their ſtarving. They muſt be given after another</hi> Gliſter <hi>hath waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away the excrements, and towards bedtime. They are as followeth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Capon-broth,</hi> or <hi>diſtilled Capon-broth</hi> 1. pound and half, <hi>Sugar of Roſes</hi> 2. ounces Mingle them, make a <hi>Gliſter;</hi> Or take <hi>Barly-Creame</hi> 1. pound and half, <hi>Claret</hi> or <hi>White-wine</hi> 4. ounces: mingle and inject, or take <hi>Chicken-broth,</hi> or <hi>thick Barly-water</hi> 1. pound and half, three <hi>yolkes of Eggs, Wine</hi> 4. ounces: Mingle and inject. Theſe will nouriſh weak perſons exceedingly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:169737:28"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>An</hi> Heating <hi>and</hi> warming Gliſter <hi>for</hi> cold diſeaſes <hi>of the</hi> Head <hi>or</hi> Guts.</head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Mercury, Origan, Calamint, Rue, Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny royall,</hi> of each a good handfull, <hi>Flowers</hi> of <hi>Camomile, Mellilot, Dill, Stecado's,</hi> of each a good handful, of <hi>Fenne-greek, Carua Comia, Aniſe, Fennell</hi> of each halfe an ounce, <hi>Agarick</hi> tyed in a clout 2. drachmes: Boyl it in <hi>Tripe-broth</hi> or <hi>Sea water,</hi> diſſolve it in a pound and halfe of this <hi>Decoction, Benedicta Laxativae</hi> an ounce, <hi>Oyle of Dill.</hi> 3 ounces, <hi>Canar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>-ſack,</hi> make a <hi>Gliſter.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A</hi> Cooling Gliſter <hi>in hot diſeaſes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Mallowes, Violets, Lettice,</hi> of each a good handfull, of the <hi>four could ſeeds, great ſeeds,</hi> of each half an ounce: <hi>Prunes,</hi> 20. <hi>Violet,</hi> and <hi>Bugloſſe Flowers,</hi> of each a ſmall hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, boyl them to a Pinte, and put in <hi>Kitchin-ſugar,</hi> 1. ounce, and <hi>Oyl of Violets</hi> 3 ounces, or take <hi>Barley</hi> and <hi>Lin-ſeed,</hi> of each 2 ounces, boyl them, and to 1 pound, put <hi>Sugar</hi> 1 ounce and half, one <hi>yolk of an Egg, common Oyle</hi> 3 ounces, <hi>Salt</hi> one handfull, take <hi>Milk</hi> warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed one pound, <hi>Sugar</hi> and <hi>Syrrop of Violets</hi> of each two ounces: Make a <hi>Gliſter</hi> to cool.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:169737:28"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>An</hi> Emollient <hi>Gliſter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke the <hi>Common Decoction</hi> of <hi>Gliſters</hi> one pound, <hi>Common Oyl, Butter,</hi> or <hi>Barrowes-greaſe</hi> three ounces; make <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The <hi>Common Decoction</hi> for <hi>Gliſters</hi> is this; Take of <hi>Mallows, Violets, Pellitary of the wall, Beets</hi> and <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury,</hi> of each a good handfull, of <hi>Fennel ſeeds</hi> half an ounce, boyl all theſe in a ſufficient quantity of water to a Pint.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>An</hi> Emollient purging Gliſter:</head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Lillie</hi> and <hi>Mallow-roots,</hi> of each one ounce <hi>Mallowes, Marſh-Mallowes, Orah,</hi> of each a good handful, <hi>Lin-ſeed, &amp; Fen-greek</hi> of each an ounce, <hi>Flowers of Mellilot, Violets,</hi> of each a little handfull, <hi>Figs, Aniſe-ſeeds</hi> 2 drachmes, <hi>Prunes</hi> five; boyl theſe in <hi>water</hi> or fat <hi>broth,</hi> and to a pint put <hi>Caſſia</hi> extracted for <hi>Gliſters</hi> 1 ounce <hi>Hieraepicrae</hi> half an ounce, <hi>Butter, Oyl of Violets &amp; Lillies</hi> of each 1 ounce and half, inject this <hi>Gliſter</hi> three hours before <hi>Meat;</hi> To make this <hi>Gliſter</hi> more Stimulating and purging, put one ounce of <hi>Benedicta Lax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ative,</hi> or <hi>Diaphenicon,</hi> with a ſcruple, or halfe a drachm of <hi>Salgem,</hi> and a drachm of <hi>common Salt,</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:169737:29"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>A</hi> Carminative <hi>or</hi> Collick-Gliſter.</head>
               <p>TAke of the <hi>Carminative Decoction</hi> 1. pound, <hi>Canary-wine,</hi> and <hi>Oyl of Dill,</hi> of each 4 oun. inject the ſame. The <hi>Carminative Decoction</hi> is this: Take <hi>Aniſe-ſeeds, Fennel-ſeeds, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roway-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eeds, Commin-ſeeds, Carrot-ſeeds;</hi> of each 2. drachmes, <hi>Flowers of Camomile</hi> halfe a good handfull, <hi>Raiſins</hi> an ounce and half, boil them in 2. pound of <hi>water</hi> to a pound.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another <hi>Gliſter</hi> for the aforeſaid purpoſe.</head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Mallow-roots</hi> half a pound, <hi>Branch <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rein, Mallowes, Penny-royall, Hore-hound, Calamin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Origan, Wormwood,</hi> of each half a good handful, <hi>Figs</hi> 12. <hi>Lin ſeed</hi> 1. ounce, <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m n, Aniſe, Fennel,</hi> &amp; <hi>Carua ſeeds,</hi> of each half an ounce, Flowers of <hi>Comin, Mellilot, Lavender, Ste<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ado's,</hi> of each two ſmall handfuls: boyl theſe in <hi>water</hi> and <hi>old wine</hi> to a Pint, add <hi>Benedicta Laxativa</hi> 1. oun. <hi>Electuary of Bay berries</hi> half an ounce, <hi>Oyl of Comin,</hi> and <hi>Rue,</hi> of each 3. ounces: make <hi>a Gliſter.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A</hi> Gliſter <hi>for the</hi> Stone <hi>in the</hi> Kidneys <hi>and</hi> Bladder.</head>
               <p>TAke the <hi>roots of Althea, Graſſe, Sparagus, Licoriſh</hi> ſhaved, <hi>Pedis Columbini,</hi> of each
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:169737:29"/>
1. ounce, <hi>Betony, Linaria, Fennel,</hi> of each a good handful, <hi>Malloes</hi> with the <hi>Roots</hi> a good handful, <hi>Figs, Raiſins,</hi> of each 10. a peece, <hi>Seeds</hi> of <hi>Parſley, Malloes, Alhakengi, Grum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel, Smalledge, Linſeed,</hi> of each 2. ounces, <hi>Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berries,</hi> and <hi>Juniper-berries,</hi> of each 2. ounces, <hi>Flowers</hi> of <hi>Broom, Camomile,</hi> and St. <hi>Johns Wort,</hi> of each 2. ſmall handfulls, boyl them in <hi>Water</hi> and <hi>White-wine:</hi> and to a pint put <hi>Oyl</hi> of <hi>Lillies,</hi> bitter <hi>Almonds, Scorpions</hi> and <hi>Honey,</hi> of each 2. ounces, <hi>Turpentine</hi> 1. ounce: make a <hi>Gliſter</hi> for the <hi>Stone</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A</hi> Gliſter <hi>to break the</hi> Stone.</head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Roots</hi> of <hi>Graſſe, Smalledge, Parſley, Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragus, Althea, Licoriſh,</hi> of each 2. ounces, <hi>Leaves</hi> of <hi>Betony, Saxifrage, Sea-Fennel,</hi> of each a good handful, <hi>Seeds</hi> of <hi>Grummel, Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-Cherries,</hi> of each one ounce: boyl them, &amp; in a pint diſſolve <hi>juice</hi> of <hi>Raadiſh</hi> or <hi>Pellitory</hi> of the <hi>Wall,</hi> one ounce, <hi>Oyl</hi> of <hi>Scorpions</hi> 3. ounces: make a <hi>Gliſter.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A</hi> Deterging <hi>or</hi> waſhing <hi>Gliſter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Barley-water</hi> one pound, <hi>Red Sugar</hi> or <hi>Honey</hi> 2. ounces, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:169737:30"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>A</hi> Conſolidating <hi>or healing</hi> Gliſter <hi>in</hi> Dyſenteries.</head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Barley</hi> torrified two ſmall handfulls, <hi>Plantane, Mirtles,</hi> of each half a good handful, <hi>Comfery-roots,</hi> and <hi>Mullet,</hi> of each two ounces, <hi>Red Roſes,</hi> a ſmall handfull, boyle them in <hi>Steel-water,</hi> or <hi>Smiths-water,</hi> to ten ounces, then add <hi>juice</hi> of <hi>Plantine</hi> and <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlein,</hi> of each one ounce and a half, bole <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniack, Dragons-blood, Starch, Trochiſcarum albarum thaſis,</hi> of each one dr. <hi>Goats ſewet</hi> two ounces make a <hi>Gliſter.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A</hi> Gliſter <hi>to kill</hi> Wormes.</head>
               <p>TAke Roots of <hi>Gentian, Torrid Ariſtolochia</hi> a ſmall handfull and halfe, <hi>Tilochia</hi> one ounce, <hi>Wormwood, Fetherfew,</hi> of each a good handful, <hi>Peach-leaves,</hi> half a good handfull, <hi>Flowers</hi> of <hi>Centry</hi> two ſmal handfuls, <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines</hi> one ſpoonful; boyl them in <hi>Conduit-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> to a pound, and add <hi>Oyle</hi> of bitter <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds</hi> three ounces, make a <hi>Gliſter,</hi> and inject this twice in one hour for the ſmall <hi>Worms</hi> in the <hi>Guts.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A</hi> Gliſter <hi>for</hi> Worms <hi>in the</hi> Stomach.</head>
               <p>TAke of <hi>Barley</hi> two ſmall handfuls, <hi>Figs</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o <hi>Aniſe-ſeeds</hi> 1 drachme, boil them thick,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:169737:30"/>
make a <hi>Gliſter</hi> without <hi>Oyl</hi> or <hi>Salt,</hi> to invite them down-ward.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>An</hi> Aſtringent Gliſter <hi>in a</hi> Lientary Diarrhea <hi>or</hi> Scowring.</head>
               <p>TAke Roots of <hi>Biſtort, Tormentil, Mullet,</hi> of each a good handful, St. <hi>Johns Wort, Myrtles, Tops</hi> of <hi>Brambles,</hi> of each a good handful, <hi>ſower wild Peares</hi> to one <hi>Cypreſs-Nut, Red Roſes</hi> a good handful, boyl them in <hi>Steel water,</hi> or <hi>Smiths-water,</hi> and <hi>Red-wine</hi> to a pound, and <hi>Hipociſlis</hi> or <hi>Acathia, Ladanum,</hi> of each half an ounce; inject this after a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terging and aſtringent <hi>Medicine</hi> given by mouth of <hi>Rhubarb,</hi> and <hi>Mirabolans.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A</hi> Gliſter <hi>to purge</hi> Choler.</head>
               <p>TAke in any cooling or emollient Gliſter, <hi>Caſſia</hi> one ounce, <hi>Syrrop</hi> of <hi>Roſes Solutive</hi> three dr. make a <hi>Gliſter.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A</hi> Gliſter <hi>to purge</hi> Fleam.</head>
               <p>TAke one pound of the <hi>Common Decoction;</hi> whereunto put <hi>Benedicta Laxativa</hi> one ounce <hi>Diaphenicon</hi> one ounce, <hi>Honey</hi> of the <hi>Squil</hi> one ounce, <hi>Salt</hi> one dr. make a <hi>Gliſters</hi> Alſo the <hi>Corminative Decoction</hi> hath the ſame effect.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:169737:31"/>
               <head>A <hi>Gliſter</hi> to purge <hi>Melancholy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke one pint of the <hi>Common Decoction,</hi> wherein boyl <hi>Burrage, Bugloſſe, Fumitary, flowers</hi> of <hi>Camomil, Mellilot</hi> and <hi>Dill;</hi> to the which put <hi>Diacatholicon</hi> 1. ounce, <hi>Hamech</hi> half an ounce, <hi>Oyl</hi> of <hi>Dill, Violets,</hi> and <hi>Lillies,</hi> of each 1. ounce: make a <hi>Gliſter.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To ſtay bleeding at <hi>Noſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>PUt up <hi>Tents</hi> of <hi>Towe</hi> in powdered colcated <hi>Vitreol</hi> burnt red, with the <hi>white</hi> of an <hi>Egg,</hi> which doth preſently cauterize the vein, and ſear it up.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A</hi> Powder <hi>outwardly applyed to bind &amp; aſtringe in Bleeding.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke of <hi>Frankincenſe</hi> 1. dr. <hi>Aloes</hi> half a dr. make them into powder, which temper with the white of an <hi>Egg,</hi> to the conſiſtance of <hi>Honey:</hi> Then put thereunto the ſoft hairs of a <hi>Hare,</hi> and apply it to the bleeding wound, Sore or vein, plentifully, and tie it on.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>To take away</hi> red Spots, Freckles, <hi>and</hi> Pimples <hi>in the</hi> Face.</head>
               <p>TAke of <hi>Mercury Sublimate</hi> powdered 1. dr. the which diſſolve in half a pound of fair
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:169737:31"/>
                  <hi>water</hi> upon hot embers in a Pot; put to it the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uice</hi> of <hi>Lemmon;</hi> ſo uſe it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of <hi>Naſalls</hi> deterging, theſe are uſed to purge the <hi>Head</hi> by the <hi>Noſe,</hi> and are of excellent uſe <hi>in Apoplexical Diſeaſes, Lethar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies,</hi> or <hi>dead ſleep.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Barley-water</hi> a pound, <hi>Honey, Roſes,</hi> or <hi>Syrrop</hi> of <hi>Stecados,</hi> 4. ounces: mingle them, and ſnuf into the <hi>Noſe</hi> a moderate quantity at a time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Liquid</hi> Naſalls <hi>for</hi> Fleam.</head>
               <p>TAke the <hi>diſtilled water</hi> of <hi>Hyſop, Sage, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joram, Betony, Piony</hi> half a pound, <hi>White-wine</hi> 2. ounces, <hi>Juice</hi> of <hi>Mercury, Anagalis,</hi> of each 1. ounce, <hi>Honey</hi> or <hi>Oxmiel, Scilitium</hi> an ounce and half: for a <hi>Naſall</hi> to be ſnuffed up warm, will bring down <hi>Fleam</hi> in abundance; and to increaſe more the drawing down of <hi>Fleam,</hi> you may boyl in the <hi>waters</hi> 1. drachme and half of <hi>Agarick</hi> trochiſcated.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A <hi>Naſall</hi> to draw down <hi>Choler.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Barley-water,</hi> wherein you may put. 1 dr. of <hi>Diagredium,</hi> and 2. ounces of the <hi>Syrrop</hi> of <hi>Roſes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:169737:32"/>
               <head>A <hi>Naſall</hi> to draw down <hi>Melancholy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>USe the <hi>Naſall</hi> for the <hi>Fleam,</hi> wherein you may boyl <hi>Sena</hi> or <hi>black Hellebor,</hi> or <hi>Polipody,</hi> or <hi>Epithymum:</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A</hi> Naſall <hi>againſt an ill</hi> ſmell <hi>proceeding from the</hi> Noſe</head>
               <p>TAke the <hi>juice</hi> of <hi>Marjoram, Roſe water,</hi> of each 2 ounces, of the flowers of <hi>Oren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> one ounce <hi>Honey</hi> of <hi>Roſes</hi> ſtrained half a dram, <hi>Musk</hi> 1 grain, <hi>Amber-greaſe</hi> two grains mingle theſe together, and ſnuf them up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Noſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Directions how to Govern a Woman in her firſt conception, before, in, and after the great work of labour, that ſhe may know how to foſter it, and hold it faſt, till time of Maturity; then how with eaſe, and good ſpeed to bring it into the world; and after how to reduce her ſelfe to her wonted ſtate of health.</head>
               <p>THerefore to preſerve her <hi>Infant,</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent <hi>Abort</hi> or miſcarrying, this enſuing <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy</hi> is commended to be taken.</p>
               <p>Take of <hi>Coriander ſeed prepared</hi> 2 drachms, of the <hi>root of Biſtort,</hi> the <hi>ſhavings of Ivory</hi> and <hi>red Corrall,</hi> of each a drachm, of <hi>White Amber,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:169737:32"/>
Chriſtal,</hi> or each a ſcruple, <hi>Alkermes</hi> half a ſcruple, <hi>Sugar</hi> diſſolved in 4 ounces of <hi>Roſe-water:</hi> make <hi>Tabelets,</hi> each of them weighing a drachm. Let the patient take one every o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther day in the morning and in the Evening between whiles: Let her ſup up a rear new <hi>Egg,</hi> thickned a little with <hi>Magiſterium of Pearl,</hi> or fine <hi>Powder,</hi> or red <hi>Corral:</hi> But if her Breſts after their filling ſhould begin to leſſen and fall, it is a preſage of future <hi>Abort,</hi> ſhe muſt then apply theſe ſear-clothes hereafter following.</p>
               <p>Take the Root of <hi>Biſtort,</hi> of <hi>Corianders,</hi> of each t o dr. of unripened <hi>Gales,</hi> of red <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> and <hi>Hipeciſtidos,</hi> of each one dr. of <hi>Lada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> a <hi>Gum, Maſtick</hi> of each half an ounce, of choice <hi>Frankincenſe,</hi> of <hi>Bdellium</hi> (the Gum of a Tree in <hi>Arabia,</hi> of each two dr. of <hi>Coral, Amber,</hi> of each one dr. powder theſe which are to be powdered, and with Oyl of <hi>Maſtick Turpentine,</hi> and <hi>Wax,</hi> make two or three <hi>Searclothes:</hi> Apply them ſometimes to her <hi>Loyns</hi> and <hi>ſides,</hi> and ſometimes too under the <hi>Navil:</hi> ſhe muſt avoid all ſudden and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent motions both of the mind and body, as <hi>Coughs, Sneeſings, Frights,</hi> alſo <hi>Spices</hi> and ſtrong <hi>Wines,</hi> and thus much before labour.</p>
               <p>In Labour to procure eaſe and ſpeed, take of the <hi>Powder</hi> as followeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:169737:33"/>Take of the <hi>root of white Dictamne,</hi> of the <hi>Stones of Dates,</hi> of <hi>Borax,</hi> of each 2. ſcruples, of <hi>Cynamon, Caſſia Lignea, Amber, Fine Pearl,</hi> of each 1. ſcruple, of <hi>Saffron</hi> half a ſcruple: make a ſmall powder; which divide into two equall parts; and let her take one part in a draught of the <hi>Water</hi> of <hi>white Lillies</hi> or <hi>Poſſet-Ale,</hi> made with <hi>Reniſh Wine,</hi> and the other part let her take about ſix hours after, if need require, if ſhe ſhould be ſubject to fainting or ſwouning before or after Labor, take now and then a ſpoonfull of this excellent <hi>Cordiall,</hi> as followeth. Take of <hi>Borage-water, Roſe-water, Strawberry-water,</hi> and <hi>Reniſh-wine,</hi> of each 2. ounces, of the <hi>Species of Diamargari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum Frigidum</hi> 1. ſcruple, make a warm infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for the ſpace of an hour; then ſtrain and adde thereunto <hi>Manus Chriſti</hi> made with <hi>Pearl</hi> 4. ounces, of the <hi>Syrrop of Baum</hi> 1. ou. of the <hi>Syrrop of Lemons,</hi> and the <hi>Syrrop of Gilley-flowers,</hi> of each 2. ounces, <hi>of Oriental Beſar, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorns-horn</hi> and <hi>amber-greaſe</hi> of each 6. grains: make a <hi>Cordial Julip.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>After Labour.</hi> Many times great pains and panges do follow women newly delivered, for which this plain ſimple <hi>Remedy</hi> is very good. Drink a good draught of <hi>bear</hi> boyled with a ſpoonfull of <hi>Camomile-flowers,</hi> and in greater pains let her drink 6. ounces of the <hi>Oyl of ſweet Almonds</hi> freſh drawn.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:169737:33"/>To dry up Milk, a quick and ſafe <hi>Remedie</hi> is <hi>neu ſponges</hi> wet in <hi>vineger</hi> (wherein a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of <hi>comin-ſeed</hi> bruiſed is boiled) tyed cloſe to the <hi>Breſts,</hi> alſo anointing them with <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguentum populeum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To procure ſtore of Milk, uſe <hi>Poſſet-drink</hi> made and boiled with <hi>Fennel,</hi> and the <hi>ſweet ſeeds of Aniſe ſeeds,</hi> and <hi>Fennel.</hi> Alſo to cauſe ſpeedy Labour, take 3 or 4 drops of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilled <hi>Oyl of Nutmegs</hi> in a ſpoonfull of <hi>white-wine.</hi> Theſe <hi>Remedies</hi> are approved to be ſafe, ſure, and forceable to effect what is deſired.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A</hi> Reſtorative-broth for <hi>weak perſons.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke an ounce and half of very good <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaperilla,</hi> and half an ounce of <hi>China</hi> ſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, a ſpoonful of <hi>Hartshorn</hi> ſcraped, and a ſpoonfull of <hi>Ivory:</hi> Infuſe them 3 or 4 houres in 3 pints of <hi>chickin-broth</hi> upon hot embers and cloſe ſtopt; then boil it to a pint and a half with a few <hi>Raſins</hi> ſtoned, and two or three <hi>Dates:</hi> whereof drink every morning a glaſſefull. Adde towards the end of the boil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, half a ſpoonfull of <hi>Marigold-flowers.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A</hi> Cordial <hi>againſt</hi> Melancholy vapors, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>TAke of <hi>Baum-water</hi> half a pound, of <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage,</hi> and <hi>Roſe-water,</hi> of each 2 ounces;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:169737:34"/>
make it a little tart with a few drops of the <hi>oyl of brimſtone,</hi> in which infuſe cold 1 ſcruple of <hi>Saffron</hi> for 4 houres: then put to it half an ounce of <hi>Burrage,</hi> and <hi>Bugloſſe;</hi> which let ſtand for 4 or 5 houres more: then let it run tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row an <hi>hipocras bag,</hi> whereunto put dulcified <hi>Magiſterium of pearl</hi> 2 ſcruples, <hi>East-Indie-Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zer</hi> 6 ounces, as much <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorns horn, Syrop of Baum</hi> freſh made 1 ounce, <hi>Syrop of the rindes of cytrons,</hi> and good <hi>ſyrop of Gillyflowers,</hi> of each half an ounce, <hi>confection of Alkirmis</hi> 1 drachm <hi>Aqua caeleſtis</hi> one ſpoonful; ſo make it a <hi>Julip</hi> very cordial; whereof take a ſpoonfull now and then as occaſion requireth. Diſſolve in this Julip 1 ounce of <hi>Manus chriſti.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A temperate cordiall <hi>Julip.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke of <hi>Burrage, Sorrel, Scabious,</hi> and <hi>Roſe-water</hi> of each 2 ounces and half, of the <hi>ſpecies of Diamargarater frigidum,</hi> 1 ſcruple; give it a warm or two over the fire; Then turn it in an <hi>hipocras bag,</hi> to which adde <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus chriſti</hi> with <hi>pearl,</hi> 3 ounces, or 4 ounces, of <hi>ſyrop of Baum</hi> and <hi>Lemons,</hi> of each 1 ounce: Diſſolve the <hi>Manus chriſti</hi> on the fire, then take it off, and adde to it <hi>Bezer-ſtone,</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorns-horn,</hi> of each 4 grains, ſo make it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a <hi>Julip.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:169737:34"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>A distilled purging water to be uſed in</hi> Dropſies.</head>
               <p>TAke the <hi>berries</hi> or <hi>ſeeds of Elders of Dane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort,</hi> being ripe in the Autumn, a good quantity, preſſe out their juyce; then bruiſe the <hi>ſtones</hi> or <hi>kirnels,</hi> and pour on the <hi>juyce,</hi> and diſtill it: This water purgeth plentiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wateriſh humors in <hi>Dropſies</hi> given from 1 ounce to 2 ounces, being aromatized with <hi>Cynamon,</hi> and <hi>Corianders</hi> prepared.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A <hi>Vomiting</hi> Water.</head>
               <p>TAke of <hi>Crocus metallorum</hi> 1 ounce, of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duus Benedictus-water</hi> 2 li. <hi>Cynamon</hi> half a ounce: infuſe them for 3 or 4 days, then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>train them, and keep it for uſe. The <hi>Doſe</hi> is from 1 ounce to 2 or 3 ounces.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For provoking the <hi>Courſes,</hi> and curing <hi>Vapours hiſtericall</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Pils of Caſtorium</hi> with a little <hi>Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg, Caſtor</hi> powdered as much as will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ye upon a Groat taken often in Beer, provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth <hi>womens Courſes,</hi> and cureth <hi>Vapors hiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>icall.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:169737:35"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Cordials</hi> to be taken after <hi>Phyſick.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke of <hi>Alkermes,</hi> 1 drachm, and mingle it with 2 ounces of the <hi>Syrop of Gillyflowers</hi> or take the <hi>Conſerve of Gillyflowers</hi> 2 drachms and mingle it with <hi>Alkermes;</hi> Or take of <hi>Diacodium</hi> half an ounce, and <hi>Alkermes</hi> half a drachm, diſſolved in <hi>Strawberry,</hi> or <hi>Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice,</hi> or <hi>Carduus benedictus,</hi> or <hi>Roſewater.</hi> Of take of <hi>Mitridate,</hi> or old <hi>Conſerve of Roſes,</hi> of each the quantity of an hazle Nutt; Take it towards bed-time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A Purging</hi> Ale <hi>or</hi> Bear <hi>to clear</hi> Melancholy, Fleam, Choler, <hi>and all muddy and terreſtriall humors, to</hi> purifie <hi>the</hi> Blood, <hi>and quit the</hi> Scurvy, <hi>and the like.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke the depined <hi>juices of Apples, Fumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, Agrimony, Succory, Burrage, Baum, Scabius, Liverwort, Scurvy graſſe, Tops of Hops,</hi> all ſtampt together 2 pound, <hi>Roots of Polipody of the Oak,</hi> 2 ounces, <hi>roots of Graſs, Aſparragus, Sorrel, Bugloſſe, Succory, red Dock, Elycampany,</hi> of each half an ounce, <hi>rindes of Capers, Tamarisk,</hi> the <hi>inner rind of young ſprouts of Aſh,</hi> of each 3 drachms, <hi>Licoriſh,</hi> and <hi>Epithymum,</hi> of each 1
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:169737:35"/>
drachm &amp; half, <hi>Maidenhair, Agrimony,</hi> of each 2 good handful, <hi>Broom-flowers, Violets, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage,</hi> and <hi>Bugloſſe</hi> of each a good handfull: the <hi>foure greater,</hi> and <hi>foure leſſer cold-Seeds,</hi> of each 2 drachms, <hi>Sena</hi> 5 ounces, or half a li. <hi>Rhubarb</hi> 1 ounce, <hi>Mechoican</hi> 1 ounce and half, <hi>Seeds</hi> of <hi>Fennel, Carua, Aniſe,</hi> of each 6 drachms, <hi>Ivory, Harts horn, Yellow Sanders, Saſſafraſſe,</hi> of each half an ounce, <hi>Ginger</hi> 2 drachms, 1 <hi>Nutmeg,</hi> prepare all according to Art, and make a Bag to foment, and work in foure Gallons of <hi>Eight ſhillings Bear;</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it hath wrought put in the <hi>juices.</hi> Let all the Herbs be of equal quantity. Alſo this purgeth a duſt, burn, atrabilarious hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, openeth obſtructions of the <hi>Liver,</hi> and <hi>Spleen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Another Purging</hi> Ale.</head>
               <p>TAke of <hi>Sena</hi> 6 ounces, <hi>Polipody</hi> of the <hi>Oak,</hi> 4 ounces, <hi>Epithymum</hi> 2 ounces, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garick, Rhubarb,</hi> of each 6 drams, <hi>Ginger</hi> 1 ounce, <hi>Aniſe ſeeds, ſweet fennel-ſeeds,</hi> of each an ounce and half, <hi>Saſaparilla</hi> ſliced half an ounce, <hi>Dockroots, Madder roots, Succory,</hi> and <hi>Fennel roots,</hi> of each 1 ounce: and if <hi>green Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitary, Agrimony,</hi> and <hi>Succory</hi> be come up, take 2 good handfuls of each, of <hi>Harts-horn, Ivory,</hi>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:169737:36"/>
of each 2 ounces; <hi>yellow ſanders</hi> 1 ounce, make it into a Bag of 4 gallons of <hi>Ale,</hi> to which adde one pint and a half of the <hi>juyce of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cory, ſcurvy-graſſe:</hi> Let all work 3 days, and then drink of it twice a day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A <hi>Dyet-drink</hi> to clear, and temper the <hi>blood.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Scurvy graſſe</hi> half a peck, <hi>Brooklime, Watercreſſes, Agrimrny, Maidenhair, Liver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort, Burrage, Bugloſſe, Bettony, Sage, Sweet mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jorum, Sea-wormwood, tops of green hops, Fumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary,</hi> of each a good handfull, <hi>Ivory, Harts-horn,</hi> and <hi>yellow Sanders,</hi> of each one ounce, <hi>Red dock-roots,</hi> 2. ounces; <hi>Perſly, Fennel, Aſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragus-roots,</hi> of each 1. ounce, <hi>Raſins</hi> half a pound: boil theſe very well in a gallon of <hi>Beer,</hi> then ſtamp, and ſtrain them, and put it into three gallons more of <hi>Beer,</hi> to work to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A <hi>Cerote</hi> for the <hi>Splene.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke of <hi>Amoniack, Bdellium, Apapanax,</hi> of each 1. drachm, of the <hi>flowers of Mellilot, Camomile, Scolopend, Maidenhair,</hi> the <hi>Rindes of the roots of Tamarick, Capers, Plantin-ſeed, Lin-ſeed,</hi> and <hi>Fennegreek,</hi> of each two ſcruples: Of the <hi>oyl of Capers</hi> 2 ounces, of <hi>freſh Butter</hi> an
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:169737:36"/>
ounce and half, of <hi>Ship-pitch</hi> 1 ounce, mingle them, and make a <hi>Cerote</hi> to be applyed to the Region of the <hi>Spleen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A <hi>Decoction</hi> to be taken againſt the <hi>Inflamma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> and <hi>obſtructions</hi> of the <hi>Liver.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke of <hi>Burrage, Bugloſſe, Agrimony, Succo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Violets, Endive, Fumitory,</hi> of each a good handfull: of the <hi>roots of Parſley,</hi> and <hi>Fennel,</hi> of each 1. ounce, of <hi>Raſins</hi> ſtoned 4 ounces, of <hi>Dates</hi> 3 ounces, of <hi>Aniſ ſeeds</hi> 2 ounces, of <hi>Fountain-water,</hi> and <hi>White-wine,</hi> of each 3 li. of <hi>ſugar</hi> 1 li. of <hi>Licoriſh</hi> 1 ounce. Mingle all, and boil to the conſumption of half, &amp; ſtrain it very well. Take hereof every morning ſix ounces at a time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A <hi>Syrop</hi> to <hi>cleanſe</hi> and temper the <hi>Blood.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke of the <hi>Juice of Scurvy-graſſe, Brook-lime, Water-creſſes, Bugloſſe, Pippins</hi> or <hi>Pear-mains,</hi> of each half a li. of the <hi>Rinds of roots of Capers, tamarisk Aſh,</hi> of the <hi>roots</hi> of <hi>Elicam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany,</hi> of <hi>red dock-roots,</hi> of <hi>Polipody</hi> of the <hi>Oke,</hi> of each half an ounce, of <hi>Epithymum, Baum, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimony, Maidenhair, Broom Flowers, Burrage,</hi> of each half a handful, of the <hi>ſeeds of Cucumber,</hi> of <hi>Millions</hi> bruiſed, of each half an ounce,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:169737:37"/>
ſeeth all to a li. and half, ſtrain &amp; boil it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a <hi>Syrop</hi> with a ſufficient quantity of <hi>Sugar.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A gratefull <hi>Potion</hi> to purge and cleanſe the <hi>Spleen.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke of <hi>Sena</hi> 6 drathms, of <hi>Strawberry-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> made ſharp with the <hi>Juyce of Lemons</hi> half a li. a little ſtick of <hi>Cynamon:</hi> Infuſe it 24 houres, then boil it gently, and ſtrain it hard; to which expreſſion, add an ounce and half of the <hi>Juice of Pippins,</hi> or <hi>Pearmains,</hi> of <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar-candy</hi> half an ounce, clarifie it with the <hi>white of an egge.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A good <hi>Decoction</hi> againſt the <hi>Cough,</hi> and <hi>ſhort-breathing.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke of <hi>Baum, Maidenhair, Scabius, Hore-hound, Hyſop,</hi> of each a good handfull, of the <hi>flowers of Violets, Bugloſſe</hi> &amp; <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage,</hi> of each a good handfull; of the roots of <hi>Longdebeef</hi> 2 ounces, of <hi>Damask-Prunes, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibes</hi> 1 ounce and half; <hi>Sebeſten, Barly, Dates, dry figs,</hi> of each 1 ounce, of <hi>Licoriſh</hi> 10 ounces, <hi>Penedies</hi> 2 ounces and half, of <hi>Fennel</hi> 4 oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, of <hi>Honey</hi> half a li. Seeth all in ſufficient quantitie of <hi>water</hi> till half be conſumed, ſo uſe it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:169737:37"/>
               <head>A very good <hi>Syrrop</hi> to be taken againſt <hi>cold diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes</hi> of the <hi>Brain</hi> and <hi>Sinews,</hi> as the <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey, Falling-ſicknes,</hi> the <hi>Cramp,</hi> and water diſtilling out of the head lying.</head>
               <p>TAke of the <hi>Flowers of Stechados</hi> 4 ounces, of <hi>Time, Calamint, Origanum,</hi> of each 1. ounce and half, of <hi>Sage, Bettony-flowers,</hi> and <hi>Roſemary</hi> of each half an ounce, of the <hi>Seeds of Rue, Pyony, Fennel</hi> of each 3 drachms. Boil them in 10 pound of <hi>water</hi> till half be conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; When the <hi>decoction</hi> is ſtrained, boil it again to a <hi>ſyrrop</hi> with <hi>ſugar,</hi> and <hi>honey,</hi> of each 2 li. and candie it with <hi>Cynamon, Ginger, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamus aromaticus,</hi> or <hi>Nutmeg,</hi> of each two drachms, which being bound up in a courſe cloth with open threeds, muſt be hanged in the <hi>ſyrope.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To binde in <hi>Fluxes of the Belly,</hi> and to comfort withall the <hi>Stomack.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke a quarter of an ounce of <hi>Iſing-glaſſe,</hi> which lay to ſteep in <hi>water</hi> 12. houres, after boil the ſame in a quart of <hi>milk,</hi> wherunto put a ſlack or two of <hi>Mace,</hi>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:169737:38"/>
two <hi>Dates</hi> ſliced in the middle with the ſtones; keep it ſtirring till the one half be conſumed: take hereof 7. or 8. ſpoonfuls morning and evening: uſe to take the ſame for a week or ten days together, if occaſion ſo require; you may therefore provide a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter quantitie of the aforeſaid things, as 1. ounce of <hi>Iſing-glaſſe,</hi> half an ounce of <hi>Dates,</hi> 3. or 4. penyworth of <hi>Mace.</hi> So long as you may uſe hereof, take withall theſe Waters mixt together as followeth.</p>
               <p>Of <hi>Baum-water</hi> half a li. and a like quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of <hi>Hyſop-water;</hi> diſſolve therein, a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of <hi>Sugar</hi> over the fire; ſtrain, and take thereof five ſpoonfuls one houre after din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, wherunto put 4. or 5. drops of <hi>Cynamon-water.</hi> If the aforeſaid do not ſufficiently binde, put a little <hi>Cynamon,</hi> or the <hi>cups of Akhorns</hi> powdered therein.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Againſt <hi>Winde</hi> in the <hi>Body.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke of <hi>Ginger</hi> half a ounce, <hi>Aniſe-ſeeds</hi> 2 drachms, <hi>Coriander</hi> prepared 1. ounce and half, <hi>Mace, Galingale, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bebes,</hi> of each a drachm, make all into <hi>fine powder,</hi> well ſearced, adding as much <hi>ſugar</hi> as you pleaſe. Take 1 dram of this <hi>powder</hi> in
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:169737:38"/>
four ounces of <hi>ſweet wine,</hi> either <hi>Muſcadine</hi> or <hi>Malmſie</hi> in the morning faſting, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards walk awhile.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Againſt <hi>Pain</hi> in the <hi>Back.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke the ſlimie ſubſtance of the <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phery root</hi> in <hi>poſſet drink,</hi> and take the ſame 4. or 5. days together: Or take <hi>Knotgraſſe,</hi> ſhread it, and mix it with <hi>butter;</hi> make a tanſey with all. It much profiteth for the ſaid Cure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the <hi>Stone</hi> in the <hi>Kidneys.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke the <hi>diſtilled water</hi> of <hi>Parſeley</hi> what quantity you pleaſe for one draught, whereunto add half a ſpoonful of the <hi>whitest Snail-ſhels</hi> finely powdered, with 4. or 5. drops of the <hi>Oyl of Turpentine;</hi> drink it faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and walk after it for an houre or more.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For <hi>cleanſing</hi> the <hi>Blood.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke the <hi>leaves of Sena, Polypody,</hi> of each 3 ounces, <hi>ſeeds of Fennel</hi> and <hi>Aniſe,</hi> of each 1. ounce, <hi>Hermodactils</hi> 2. ounces and half, <hi>Salſaparilla</hi> 3 ounces, <hi>Saſſafraſſe</hi> thin
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:169737:39"/>
ſliced 2 ounces, <hi>Agarick</hi> ſliced 1 ounce, <hi>Rhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berb</hi> half an ounce, <hi>Ginger</hi> a quarter of an ounce, <hi>Scurvy-graſſe, Brooklime, Watercreſſes,</hi> of each 3 good handfuls; <hi>Red dock-roots</hi> 2 oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, put theſe into a Boultering-bag, and boil it in 4. gallons of <hi>Ale,</hi> or <hi>Bear,</hi> and let the bag hang in the veſſel. Take every morning the quantitie of 4 ounces or more, according to the nature and condition of the body.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A <hi>Julip</hi> for a <hi>Tertian Fever.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Endive, Succory, Sorrel, Strawberry-leaves, violet-leaves,</hi> of each a good hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, <hi>French barley</hi> a good handfull, <hi>Raſins</hi> ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned half a pound, <hi>Aniſeſeeds</hi> 1 ounce, one ſtick of <hi>Licoriſh:</hi> decoct theſe in a pottle of <hi>faire water,</hi> to the conſumption of half. Take hereof 7 or 8 ounces in the morning at a time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A <hi>Purge</hi> for the ſame.</head>
               <p>TAke the <hi>Pills of Cochi aureae,</hi> of each half an ounce, mix theſe together, and make a Maſſe, and take the weight of nine pence for the <hi>Doſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:169737:39"/>
               <head>A <hi>Dyet Drink</hi> to open and temper the <hi>Liver.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke the <hi>Roots of Fennel, Parſly Dock, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roch, Knee-holm,</hi> of each half a good handfull, the <hi>leaves of Endive, Bugloſſe, Fumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, Harts-tongue, Agrimony, Garden worme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, Cetrach,</hi> of each a good handfull, the <hi>back</hi> of the <hi>roots of Capers,</hi> half an ounce. Boyl theſe in a convenient quantity of <hi>Whey,</hi> till a third part be ſpent, then clarifie the ſame, whereof drink in the morning faſting, at the leaſt half a pound at a time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A <hi>Receipt</hi> to make <hi>purging Prunes, Raſins,</hi> and <hi>Currents.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke of <hi>Prunes</hi> half a li. of <hi>Sena</hi> 1 ounce, <hi>Mechoacon</hi> 3 drachms, <hi>Turbeth</hi> 3 dr. of <hi>Borage-water, Baum water,</hi> and <hi>Roſe-water</hi> of each 4 ounces: boyl them a little, then ſtrain them; whereunto add <hi>Manna</hi> 2 oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Sugar a ſufficient quantity, to make the Liquor into a Syrope.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A <hi>Reſtorative Broth</hi> for <hi>weak</hi> and <hi>conſuming</hi> Bodies.</head>
               <p>TAke half an ounce of the beſt <hi>China</hi> thin ſliced, infuſe the ſame the ſpace of foure
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:169737:40"/>
and twenty houres in four Pintes of <hi>fair Spring-water,</hi> in a Pipkin cloſe ſtoped, ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon hot Embers; Then put therein a ſmall <hi>Chickin,</hi> or a little peece of the <hi>Rack of Veal,</hi> and ſo ſet it over the fire made of <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coals,</hi> to boyl gently, and put therein a <hi>Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cory-root,</hi> the pith taken out, of the <hi>Leaves</hi> of <hi>Agrimony, Bugloſſe, Cetrach,</hi> and <hi>Edive,</hi> of each a good handfull, of <hi>Hartshorn</hi> a quarter of an ounce at the leaſt ſcraped, and a <hi>cruſt</hi> of <hi>White bread;</hi> the which boyl, till half the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor</hi> be conſumed; then ſtrain it, and with a convenient quantity of <hi>fine Sugar,</hi> make the ſame fit for the taſte. Hereof let the party take in the morning early, and in the afternoon about four of the clock, at every time the third part of a pinte warm, and ſo every day for the ſpace of three weeks.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Remedies</hi> for the <hi>Hemorrhoids.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke the third part of a pinte of <hi>Milk,</hi> and ſo much of <hi>Smiths-water,</hi> wherein quench <hi>Gads of Steel:</hi> Oftentimes put into the ſame 2 ounces of the <hi>juice</hi> of <hi>Clary;</hi> ſo inject luke warme. Take a pinte of <hi>Milk</hi> and boyl it, in boyling ſlack it often when it riſeth with <hi>Plantine-water,</hi> ſo continue doing till a pinte of <hi>Plantine-water</hi> be put in, about the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:169737:40"/>
ſlacking of the <hi>Milk;</hi> Then take it off the fire, and put thereunto 3 ounces of <hi>Mel roſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> wherof drink at your pleaſure.</p>
               <p>Take the <hi>white of an Egge,</hi> 4 ounces of <hi>Freſh Butter</hi> out of a Chirne well waſhed, and of <hi>Saffron</hi> a ſcruple, work theſe together, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of at times put up a little into the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for ceaſing paine; but if the pain con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, to the aforeſaid add 2 good handfulls of <hi>Night-ſhade,</hi> and then it will be much more effectuall for the ſaid purpoſe.</p>
               <p>Alſo take <hi>Mastick,</hi> and <hi>Frankincenſe,</hi> of each a good handfull, powder and ſtraw it upon coals of fire in a Chafindiſh, put it into a cloſe ſtool, ſo fit over it to take the fume thereof, and apply an <hi>Hagtaper-Leaf</hi> to the place.</p>
               <p>Alſo take the <hi>Roots of Pilewort,</hi> and <hi>Mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton-ſuet,</hi> and ſhred them both together ſmall, then boyl the ſame and ſtrain them, ſo keep them for uſe to anoint the <hi>Piles</hi> withall.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſpeciall <hi>Receipt</hi> for the making of <hi>Aquavitae.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke of <hi>Tops of Roſemary, Sage, Marjorum, Origaum, Time, Wormwood, Sparemints, Baume,</hi> of each a good handfull, of <hi>Ginger</hi> ſcraped clean 1 ounce, of <hi>Nutmegs</hi> and <hi>Cyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:169737:41"/>
of each half an ounce, of <hi>Cloves, Mace, Pepper,</hi> and <hi>Graines,</hi> of each a quarter of an ounce, of <hi>Galleangle-Roots</hi> ſliced 1 ounce, of the <hi>Raſins of the Sun</hi> cut through the middle 1 pound, of <hi>Fennel-ſeeds,</hi> and <hi>Anniſe-ſeeds,</hi> of each 2 ounces of <hi>Licoriſh</hi> ſcraped clean, and cut into thin ſlices, half a pound. Bruiſe the Spices, and the Seeds a little, and break the Herbs between your hands; then put all together into a Gallon or two of <hi>Muskadine, Sack,</hi> or ſuch like <hi>ſtrong Wine;</hi> and ſo let them infuſe in a <hi>Limbeck-pot</hi> cloſe ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, 24 hours upon hot embers, and the next morning diſtil them, with a very temperate fire, and take ſpeciall care that the head of your <hi>Limbeck</hi> be kept cold continually, with <hi>freſh Water,</hi> and that the bottom there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of be faſt Luted, that none of the Vapours breath forth. Out of a Gallon of <hi>Liquor</hi> you may draw a quart of excellent <hi>Aquavitae,</hi> and if then to the Fleeces in the Pot, you will add a Gallon of ſtrong <hi>Ale,</hi> or <hi>Lees of Wine,</hi> or of them both with half a pound of <hi>Licoriſh,</hi> foure ounces of <hi>Aniſeſeeds,</hi> and one ounce of <hi>Graines,</hi> and diſtill it again, you ſhall draw an <hi>Aquavitae</hi> good for your Families, and poor Neigbours in their neceſſities.</p>
               <p>There is not a <hi>Water</hi> in uſe which can bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fortifie Life, then the aforeſaid <hi>Aquavitae:</hi>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:169737:41"/>
for it greatly comforteth a weak ſtomack, expelleth Winde, putteth off Melancholy paſſions, preſerveth the humors from Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and exceedingly prevaileth againſt ſownding. But the uſe thereof is not alike wholſome and good for all Bodies: for unto them that are Lean, and of a dry Nature, and in the Summer it is rather hurtful then good; becauſe it drieth too much the inner parts, eſpecially the <hi>Liver,</hi> and <hi>radicall Moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture:</hi> But to old men, to groſſe, and moiſt Bodies, it is very profitable, for it fortifieth the <hi>Stomack,</hi> comforteth <hi>excremental humors;</hi> diſcuſſeth <hi>Winde,</hi> and defendeth them from the <hi>Lethargie, Apoplexy,</hi> and other <hi>cold diſeaſes,</hi> unto which by reaſon of their moiſt habit of Body they are very ſubject. Wherefore the moderate uſe thereof is to be permitted to cold and flegmatick bodies, eſpecially in cold and moiſt ſeaſons, upon taking too much meat: and when the Stomack ſhall be troubled with Winde, the quantity of a ſpoonfull or two at a time, well ſweetned with <hi>Sugar,</hi> and if it be taken with an equal portion of <hi>Wormwoodw-ater,</hi> as a ſpoonfull or two of the one, and ſo of the other with <hi>Sugar</hi> alſo, comforteth the <hi>Stomack</hi> exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, helpeth the <hi>Concoction,</hi> and diſcuſſeth <hi>Winde,</hi> without cauſing any manner of hurt
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:169737:42"/>
to the <hi>Liver.</hi> And being taken in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner after a great Meal, or whenſoever the <hi>Stomack</hi> ſhall be ill-affected by reaſon of <hi>Windineſſe,</hi> or otherwiſe. It is not only good for the <hi>Flegmatick,</hi> and ſuch as are cold by Conſtitution, but agreeable and wholſome for all other Bodies: But ſuch as are inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively hot and dry in their ſtate of Body. If they ſtand in need of the help thereof, it is beſt to take two parts of <hi>Wormwood water,</hi> and one of <hi>Aqua-vitae</hi> mingled with <hi>Sugar,</hi> and ſo they may ſecurely and profitably uſe it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A <hi>Receit</hi> for making of <hi>Cynamon-water.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke of <hi>Cynamon</hi> groſly beaten 1 li. of <hi>white Sugar</hi> 1 li. one Gallon of <hi>Sack,</hi> and a quart of <hi>Roſe-water</hi> ſteeped together four and twenty houres: of this aforeſaid is drawn by diſtillation a <hi>Water</hi> of ſingular efficacy againſt ſownding, debility of the Spirits, and principall parts. Phyſicians do adviſe all that are reſpective of their healths, eſpecially ſuch as are of weak Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, never to be without it, and take now and then a ſpoonful or two, eſpecially when occaſion ſhall invite the uſe of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:169737:42"/>
               <head>A <hi>Receit</hi> for making the <hi>Pills</hi> called <hi>de tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Fernelii.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke of <hi>Maſtick, Rhubarb,</hi> of each 2 oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>Aloes</hi> 4 ounces, <hi>Agarick</hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ochiſcated <hi>Powder of Hidra,</hi> of each 1 ounce and half, <hi>Cynamon</hi> half an ounce, with <hi>Syrop of Succory,</hi> and <hi>Canary Wine,</hi> make it into a Maſſe of <hi>Pils.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A <hi>Receit</hi> for curing the <hi>Bloody Flux,</hi> and for healing the <hi>Ulcers</hi> in the <hi>Guts,</hi> cauſed thereby.</head>
               <p>TAke the <hi>inner Rind</hi> of a <hi>ſapline Oak,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 20 yeers growth, &amp; put 2 handfuls of the ſaid <hi>Rind</hi> being cut into ſmall peeces in a quart of <hi>Milk:</hi> Boyl the ſame till it be ready to run over, then ſlake it with cold <hi>Milk,</hi> and <hi>Plantine-water:</hi> So boyl and ſlake it five or ſix times, which maketh more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtringent. Let the Patient take half a pinte at a time, adding to it a little <hi>groſſe Pepper:</hi> Put the ſame back in <hi>water,</hi> and boyl it with a little <hi>Cynamon,</hi> and drink at Meals toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the aforeſaid.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An approved <hi>Remedy</hi> by many for an <hi>Ague.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke of <hi>Smalledge</hi> one handfull, and bruiſe the <hi>leaves</hi> by it ſelf, then take of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:169737:43"/>
                  <hi>white Frankincenſe</hi> 1 d. and break it ſmall with one handfull of <hi>Bay-Salt,</hi> the which mingle together with the Herbs, and make a <hi>Plaiſter</hi> thereof: And a little before the Fit cometh, apply it to the wriſts of each Arm, and likewiſe to the bowing of his Arms, ſo let them lye on till they be dry: continue ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing four or five times, and it helpeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An <hi>Almond-Milk</hi> to <hi>cool</hi> and induce <hi>ſleep.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>ſweet Almonds</hi> blanched 5 li. beat them in a <hi>ſtone-mortar</hi> by ſprinkling them now and then with a little <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-water,</hi> at laſt put a quart of <hi>Barly-water</hi> to them, and four ounces of <hi>fine Sugar;</hi> Then ſtrain it, adding two ounces of <hi>Roſewater:</hi> this may be drawn out with <hi>Chickin broth,</hi> and ſweetned with <hi>Sugar-candy,</hi> inſtead of other <hi>Sugar.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To make a <hi>Barly Cream.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke 3 ounces of <hi>Barly</hi> boiled till it break off, <hi>blanched Almonds</hi> 2 ounces, draw it out with half a pint of <hi>Barly-water,</hi> and ſtrain it: And put ſo to it 1 ounce of the <hi>Julip of Roſes,</hi> and a little <hi>ſugar.</hi> Make a draught of <hi>Barly Cream</hi> to be taken bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:169737:43"/>
to bring ſleep in Fevers, and to cool hot and ſharp Urine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An excellent approved <hi>Water</hi> for <hi>Sore Eyes,</hi> to preſerve the <hi>Eye-ſight,</hi> and to recover it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hindred by any cauſe or means whatſoever.</head>
               <p>TAke 3 dr: of <hi>Tuttia</hi> beaten into ſmall powder, and as much <hi>Aloe Epaticum,</hi> 3 dr. of fine <hi>Sugar,</hi> 6 ounces of <hi>Roſe water,</hi> and as much <hi>White wine:</hi> Mingle all together, and put them into a glaſs, and ſtop it cloſe, and let it ſtand in the Sun for the ſpace of a moneth (ſtirring it together once every day) then take the ſame and diſtill it, and when you will uſe it, take the quantitie of 5 or 6 drops at a time of the ſame <hi>Water,</hi> and drop it into your <hi>eyes</hi> both morning and evening, and ſo continue it for a ſhort ſpace, and it will preſerve your ſight, and cauſe it to come again being hindred and gone, and to be as clear, and as perfect as ever it was before. This hath been truly proved by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers that have loſt their <hi>Eye-ſight</hi> for a good while together, and by uſing this means (by the bleſſing of God upon it) have recovered the ſame again, and ſeen as clearly, and as perfectly, as ever they did before.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:169737:44"/>
               <head>Another approved <hi>Medicine</hi> to clear the <hi>Eye-ſight.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MAke a Powder of <hi>Fennel, Aniſe,</hi> and <hi>Elicampany,</hi> and temper them with <hi>Aquavitae,</hi> and then dry them again, and eat hereof every morning and evening a pretty quantitie, and it will not onely clear your <hi>Sight,</hi> but alſo purge <hi>Winde,</hi> and make one that is old ſeem young a long time after.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another excellent <hi>Remedie</hi> for the <hi>Eyes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke pure new <hi>White-wine,</hi> and infuſe therein the herb called <hi>Eye-bright,</hi> and <hi>Wood betony,</hi> of each a ſmall handfull, and ſo let it remain for the ſpace of 3 days toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then ſeeth it with a little <hi>Roſemary</hi> in it, and drink hereof a good draught both morning and evening, and it will help you, and cauſe you to have your <hi>ſight</hi> both per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and good. Accuſtome your ſelf alſo to eat every morning a new laid <hi>Egg</hi> rear roſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and put therein ſome of the powder of <hi>Eye-bright,</hi> and that will likewiſe do you much good to the clearing and perfecting of your <hi>ſight.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:169737:44"/>
               <head>An excellent <hi>Medicine</hi> to preſerve the <hi>ſight,</hi> and to clear the <hi>Eyes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke a handful of <hi>Eye-bright</hi> bound to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, put it into a gallon of <hi>Beer,</hi> when it is newly cleanſed, let it hang in the midſt of the drink, and let all work together, until the drink be clear and ripe to be drunk, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the common uſe; and then drink as oft as you will. It were not amiſs to every handfull of the herb (to avoid windineſs) to add 2 drachms of <hi>Fenel-ſeed</hi> well duſted, and a little bruiſed. This hath been truly proved.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For a <hi>Web</hi> or <hi>Pearl</hi> in the <hi>Eye.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke the <hi>White</hi> of a new laid <hi>Egg</hi> beaten to an <hi>oil,</hi> and the <hi>juice</hi> of <hi>Daſie-roots</hi> and <hi>leaves,</hi> and of the <hi>juice</hi> of the roots &amp; leaves of brown <hi>Fennel,</hi> and of the juice of the leaves and roots of the white <hi>Honey-ſuckle,</hi> with the 3 leaves: take of theſe joices two good ſpoonfuls, and put it to the <hi>White</hi> of the <hi>Egg,</hi> and a little ſpoonfull of pure <hi>honey,</hi> and a ſpoonful of womans <hi>milk,</hi> and one ſpoonful of <hi>Roſewater,</hi> and a half penyworth of <hi>Spermacaeti,</hi> and as much <hi>White-ſugar-candy</hi>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:169737:45"/>
beaten, and as much white <hi>Coporas</hi> as a good <hi>Nutmeg</hi> made into fine Powder: labour them all well together with a ſilver ſpoon, and ſcum off the foam, and put it into a glaſs, and keep it cloſe ſtopt, and lying on your back with a feather drop 2 or 3 drops at a time into your <hi>Eye,</hi> uſe it 3 times a day till it be well.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the <hi>Rheum</hi> in the <hi>Eyes,</hi> and to cure the <hi>Redneſs</hi> of them.</head>
               <p>ANoint the <hi>Eyes</hi> 3 nights together with thin <hi>Cream,</hi> and then anoint them other three nights with live <hi>Honey,</hi> and it helpeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A marvellous good <hi>Remedie</hi> for the <hi>Tooth Ach.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke a little <hi>Honey,</hi> and ſet it on the fire, and put there into ſome of the <hi>bark</hi> of a tree called a <hi>White Bullace-tree,</hi> or elſe the <hi>bark</hi> of the <hi>Elder-tree,</hi> either of them will ſerve being cut into very ſmall pieces; take alſo a little quantitie of <hi>Ginger,</hi> and ſome <hi>Bay-Salt:</hi> Mingle theſe together, and apply it warm to your <hi>Tooth,</hi> and you will finde pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>Remedie.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:169737:45"/>
               <head>A marvellous good <hi>Medicine</hi> to drive away the <hi>Itch.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke, ſomething to make you ſweat 2 nights, one after another, <hi>viz: Mithri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date</hi> with water of <hi>Carduus Benedictus</hi> After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards purge your ſelf with this <hi>Purgation</hi> following, <hi>viz:</hi> half an ounce of <hi>Diaphenicum</hi> and <hi>Hamech,</hi> mingled with <hi>Honey</hi> or <hi>Syrop of Roſes,</hi> alſo with a little <hi>Fleſh broth</hi> (as the <hi>Broth</hi> of a <hi>Chickin,</hi> or knuckle of <hi>Veal,</hi> or the like) taken in onely in the morning, and ſo continue your going to ſtool by often taking in ſome warm broth or caudle. Afterwards uſe this cooling Drink, <hi>viz:</hi> Take 2 good handfuls of <hi>Sorrel,</hi> of the herb called in the ſhops <hi>Fumus terrae, Agrimonie, Scabius Cinque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foil, Endive, Succory, Harts horn,</hi> of each a good handfull; boil them all in ſome quantitie of <hi>Buttermilk</hi> or <hi>Whey;</hi> and when it hath well boiled, take it off from the fire; and to make you purge wel, take a pinte thereof, &amp; add to it half an ounce of <hi>Sena.</hi> Take hereof every morning a good draught, and it will give you every day a ſmall purge; and by this means (with the bleſſing of God thereupon) you ſhall in a very ſhort time be cured.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:169737:46"/>
               <head>A preſent <hi>Remedie</hi> for the <hi>Itch.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BOil the Roots of <hi>Elicampany,</hi> boil them very ſoft, and mix them in a Mortar with <hi>freſh butter,</hi> and with the powder of <hi>Ginger,</hi> of theſe make an excellent Ointment againſt the <hi>Itch, Scabs,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To take out a <hi>Burning.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Lambs-blood</hi> if you have it, or <hi>Chickins-blood,</hi> warm from the Lamb or chickin if you can; &amp; if not, warm it, and ſo bathe the place burnt therewith.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another excellent <hi>Remedie</hi> for a <hi>Burning.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Caſſel-ſope,</hi> and ſtir it on the fire un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till it be as thick as Salve, and make plaiſters thereof and lay them on the place that is burnt, or anoint the ſame therewith, and it will take away the heat or burning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the <hi>Bloody Flux.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>STill <hi>Frogs</hi> as you do Herbs, or Flowers, or any thing elſe; but you muſt put no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing unto them but the <hi>Frogs:</hi> take 2 or 3
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:169737:46"/>
ſpoonfuls of this <hi>Water</hi> in any thing that you will drink, and you ſhall finde preſent caſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An excellent Medicine for the <hi>Stone</hi> or <hi>Gravel.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke ſome quantitie of <hi>White wine, Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megs,</hi> a ſmal quantitie of <hi>Oil</hi> and <hi>ſugar,</hi> alſo <hi>Limons</hi> (if they may be had) mingle theſe together, and take it in. It is alſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding good for the <hi>Collick.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An excellent <hi>Meath,</hi> to cleanſe the <hi>Stomack,</hi> preſerve the <hi>Liver,</hi> and very good againſt the <hi>Stone.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke fair <hi>Spring-water,</hi> and put as much <hi>honey</hi> to it, that when it's warm and well ſtirred together, it will bear an egg the bredth of a groat above the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: let it ſtand ſo all night cloſe covered, the next day ſet it on a clear fire and boil it, ſtill ſcumming it as long as any will riſe: then put into it 3 handfuls of <hi>Agrimony,</hi> and 2 handfuls of <hi>Pellitory of the wall, Cynamon</hi> 3 ounces, <hi>Ginger</hi> 2 ounces, and 4 or 5 <hi>Nutmegs</hi> groſly bruiſed: put the Spice into a little bag, with a bullet of lead or a ſtone to make it ſtick: put the herbs and ſpice in a kettle
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:169737:47"/>
together, and let them ſeeth about half an hour: then take out the herbs when you take off the <hi>Meath</hi> from the fire: let the bag of Spice be put into the barrel with it, but it muſt ſtand till it be quite cold before you tun it. This quantity of herbs and ſpice will ſerve 10 or 12 Gallons of <hi>Meath,</hi> which is an excellent thing to cleanſe the <hi>Stomack,</hi> preſerve the <hi>Liver,</hi> and wonderfull good againſt the <hi>Stone.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſoveraign <hi>Remedie</hi> for the <hi>Mother,</hi> and <hi>Winde</hi> about the <hi>Heart.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Licoriſh, Fennel-ſeed, Aniſe ſeed, Alexander-ſeed,</hi> of each a like quanti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie, beat them together; then take <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon</hi> and <hi>Saffron,</hi> and beat them to powder and temper it with <hi>clarified Honey</hi> or <hi>Sugar,</hi> and make thereof an <hi>Electuarie,</hi> and eat thereof morning and evening.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An excellent <hi>Medicine</hi> for the <hi>Wind-Collick.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Saſſafraſſe, Parſley, Lime,</hi> and <hi>Archan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel,</hi> of each a like quantitie, boil them in <hi>ſtale Ale,</hi> from a quart to a pinte; then ſtrain them, and let the Patient drink there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of morning and evening, and faſt an hour after it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:169737:47"/>
               <head>Another approved <hi>Receit</hi> to expell <hi>Winde,</hi> and to comfort the <hi>Stomack.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Cynamon, Ginger, Mace, Cubes, Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingall, Aniſe-ſeeds, Comin-ſeeds,</hi> and <hi>Parſley-ſeeds,</hi> with <hi>powder of Bays, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>momile-flowers, Wormwood, Mints,</hi> and <hi>Rue,</hi> mix them together, and put them in a cup of <hi>Beer,</hi> drink hereof morning and evening, and you will finde ſpeedie remedie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A marvellous good <hi>Remedie</hi> for the <hi>Palſie.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke the diſtilled water of <hi>Daffodils,</hi> bathe and rub the Patient with the ſaid Liquor by the fire, and it will cure him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An approved Remedy for <hi>heat</hi> in the <hi>Mouth</hi> or <hi>Throat.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke a quart of <hi>Spring-water,</hi> and put it into a Pipkin, and put thereto 2 ſticks of <hi>Licoriſh,</hi> and ſome <hi>Violet-leaves:</hi> then boyl it to a pinte, and ſtrain it, and gargle there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with often.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the <hi>Heat</hi> of the <hi>Back.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Oyl of Roſes</hi> 6 ounces and an half, and put to it a little <hi>Wax,</hi> &amp; 4 drops of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:169737:48"/>
                  <hi>Vineger,</hi> and anoint the back therewith.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An excellent <hi>Receit</hi> for the <hi>heat</hi> in the <hi>Face.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Campher,</hi> and lay it in <hi>fair water</hi> 4 or 5 hours, then take a peece of <hi>Campher,</hi> and ſome of the <hi>Water</hi> which it lyeth in, and a ſpoonful of <hi>Capons greaſe,</hi> and ſtir them wel together half an hour, then anoint the face therewith 20 times a day, and it will drive away the <hi>heat.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An excellent <hi>Receit</hi> to cauſe <hi>ſleep.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke 1 ounce of <hi>Conſerve of red Roſes,</hi> half a drachm of <hi>Alkirmis,</hi> and one drachm of <hi>Diuſcordium:</hi> mingle theſe together, and eat them when you go to bed, the quantity of a Nutmeg at a time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An approved Remedy for the <hi>Cough.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Brimſtone</hi> beaten to powder half an ounce, put it in a <hi>new-laid Egg</hi> ſoft roſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, mingle it well together: then drink it in the morning at your breakfaſt, make as much again at night when you go to Bed, and you ſhall be well at the ſecond or third time, but if the <hi>Cough</hi> hath holden you long, you muſt take it ſo much the oftner.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:169737:48"/>
               <head>A ſoverain <hi>Medicine</hi> for the <hi>Cramp.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke the little bone of the knee-joynt of the hinder leg of a <hi>Hare,</hi> and touch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he grieved place therewith, and it doth ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way help the <hi>Cramp.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An excellent <hi>Receit</hi> for an <hi>Ague.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Dragon, Salendine, Burrage, Bugloſſe, Angelica, Succory, Endive, Sorrell, Betony, Pimpernell, Scabius, Agrimony, White honey-ſuckles</hi> that grow among the graft a and <hi>Red honey-ſuckles</hi> of the ſame ſort, of each of theſe a handfull, of <hi>Carduus Benedictus</hi> 2 handfuls dryed or green; ſhred them and boyl them very ſmall, then ſet them to ſteep in a pottle of <hi>White-wine</hi> over night, and ſtill it the next day in a dry ſtill, the firſt is the beſt, and the ſmall Water is very good though not ſo ſtrong; then give it to the ſick party 1 hour before the fit doth come, 6 or 7 ſpoonfuls, warming it firſt, and let the ſick go into a warm bed to ſweat preſently, and he will find help hereby. This hath been truly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:169737:49"/>
               <head>To make an <hi>Iſſue.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Rie-flower,</hi> and <hi>Mustard-ſeed</hi> beaten to powder, and with water make a little paſte, and lay a Ring upon the place made of a ruſh, and apply it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An approved <hi>Receipt</hi> for a <hi>Scal'd Head.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke a <hi>Candle</hi> and let it drop upon it as hot as you can, in ſo doing it will ſcale off, then take the <hi>Stale of a Cow,</hi> and the <hi>fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of a whole Chamber-pot,</hi> boil theſe together, and waſh the place, and it will ſtraightway cure it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the <hi>Hickup.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>STop both your ears with your fingers, and the hickup will preſently leave you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An excellent <hi>Medicine</hi> for the <hi>Gowt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Ivie</hi> that grows on a Wall 2 hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls, and put it into raw <hi>Milk,</hi> and put thereto <hi>Bores-greaſe,</hi> and <hi>Oatmeal,</hi> and boyl it together, and apply it to the part grieved.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:169737:49"/>
               <head>For the <hi>Morphew.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>USe to drink the <hi>Water</hi> of <hi>Strawberries</hi> diſtilled, and it wil kill the root of any <hi>Morphew</hi> that is within the body.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A <hi>Poſſet-drink</hi> to cool the <hi>Liver.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Milk,</hi> and put therein a <hi>Succory-root</hi> well bruiſed, and boil them, then make a <hi>Poſſet</hi> thereof, with two ſpoonfulls of <hi>Vineger,</hi> and boil therein <hi>Currents, Raiſins of the Sun,</hi> and <hi>Cynamon.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To open the Obſtructions of the <hi>Liver,</hi> and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve from the <hi>Dropſie.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke every day half a drachm of fine <hi>Rhubarb</hi> thin ſliced, with a ſpoonfull of <hi>Currents</hi> ſteeped and waſhed in <hi>White-wine</hi> 2 hours, then chap them finely with the <hi>Rhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barb,</hi> and eat them faſting 9 mornings toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, at the <hi>Spring</hi> and Fall.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To ſtay a <hi>Looſeneſſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke a Pint of <hi>Milk</hi> of a Red or black Cow, ſet it on the fire; and when it Boils up, pour in a ſpoonfull of <hi>Spring-water:</hi> then
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:169737:50"/>
let the Milk boil up again, and do in the ſame manner 9 times, drink hereof when it is boil'd, in the morning, after dinner, and in the evening.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſpeciall <hi>Receipt</hi> for the <hi>Spleen.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke 3 or 4 handfulls of the <hi>Leaves</hi> and <hi>Flowers</hi> of <hi>Melilot,</hi> and put them into a pottle of <hi>Water,</hi> (but let the one half of the water be <hi>Smiths-water,</hi> and the other hal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the party grieved his own water, and let it ſeeth till it come to a quart; then take both <hi>Herbs</hi> and <hi>Flowers,</hi> and put them into a bag and then lay them to the Patients ſide, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hot as he is able to endure it: let him uſe this for 9 or 10 dayes together every day once, and it will cure him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How to make the <hi>Salſaperilla-drink,</hi> which is very good for thoſe that are troubled with the <hi>Foul Diſeaſe,</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Gallicus,</hi> or the <hi>French Pox.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke 4 ounces of <hi>Salſaperilla,</hi> and let it ſoak in 10 pound of <hi>Water</hi> a whole night, then take the <hi>Salſaperilla</hi> out of the Water, and cut it into ſmall pieces: then put the <hi>Salſaperilla</hi> ſo cut into the ſame Water
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:169737:50"/>
again, and take 1 ounce of <hi>China-roots,</hi> grate or cut them very ſmall: take alſo 1 ounce of <hi>Licoriſh,</hi> beat it with an hammer, and cut it alſo into ſmall pieces: then take 1 ounce of <hi>Aniſe-ſeed,</hi> and bruiſe it a little, and take 1 pound of <hi>Raiſins</hi> of the <hi>Sun</hi> (the ſtones being taken out of them,) put altogether into the ſaid 10 pound of Water, and put all into a large pot or Pipkin, which muſt be ſo large that the foreſaid Commodities with the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter do not fill the Pot above half full, leſt it ſhould run over in the boiling<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> keep the ſaid pot cloſe ſtop't, boiling ſome 8 or 10 hours together, untill half be boiled away: then put into it again as much Water as you conceive was boiled away, and let it boil for the ſpace of 3 hours longer: then take it off from the fire, and put therein half an ounce of <hi>Sena,</hi> and drink thereof in the morning a good draught to go to ſtool, the reſt of the drink when it's cold ſtrain through a linnen cloth, and boil again the reſt of the ſubſtance, as before, for the ſpace of 8 hours with <hi>Freſh water, freſh Licoriſh,</hi> and <hi>Raiſins</hi> of the Sun: half an hour before you take it off from the fire, put into it theſe Herbs following, viz. <hi>Fumiterie, Violet-leaves, Succory, Strawberry-leaves, Sorrell,</hi> of each a handfull; put theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the pot and let them boil half an hour;
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:169737:51"/>
then take them off fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fire, &amp; ſtrain them as before. This ſecond drink you muſt uſe in the day time when you are a dry, bui you muſt cloſe up your Stomack both after Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and after Supper with the former drink. This is a ſoverain <hi>Medicine</hi> to cure the <hi>foul Diſeaſe,</hi> or <hi>French-Pox.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An excellent <hi>Drink</hi> or <hi>Potion</hi> for ſundry Diſeaſes.</head>
               <p>TAke the <hi>Roots</hi> of <hi>Munks Rhubarb,</hi> and <hi>Red Madder,</hi> of each half a pound, <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> 4 ounces, <hi>Aniſe ſeeds,</hi> and <hi>Licoriſh,</hi> of each 2 ounces, <hi>Scabius,</hi> &amp; <hi>Agrimony,</hi> of each 1 handful, ſlice the <hi>roots</hi> of the <hi>Rhubarb,</hi> bruiſe the <hi>Aniſe-ſeeds</hi> and <hi>Licoriſh,</hi> break the <hi>Herbs</hi> with your hand, and put them into a <hi>Stone-pot</hi> called a <hi>Stean,</hi> with 4 Gallons of ſtrong <hi>Ael,</hi> to ſteep or ſoak for the ſpace of 3 dayes, and then drink this <hi>Liquor</hi> as your ordinary <hi>Drink,</hi> for 3 weeks together, and the longer you take it, it is the better; provided you have alwayes one <hi>Stean</hi> under another, being alwayes carefull to keep a good diet. It cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the <hi>Dropſie,</hi> the <hi>Yellow-Jaundice,</hi> all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of <hi>Itch, Scabs, Breaking-out,</hi> &amp; <hi>Maungineſſe:</hi> It purifieth the <hi>Blood</hi> from all <hi>Corruption,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaileth againſt the <hi>Green-ſicknes</hi> very greatly, and againſt all <hi>Oppilations</hi> or <hi>Stoppings,</hi> maketh
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:169737:51"/>
young <hi>Wenches</hi> look very fair &amp; Cherry-like, and bringeth down their <hi>Courſes,</hi> the ſtopping whereof hath cauſed the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>An excellent Remedie</hi> for a <hi>Green-wound.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe coles of a Burch-fire made into pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and put into the <hi>Wound</hi> or <hi>Sore,</hi> heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it preſently, without any other thing in few dayes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A <hi>Diet-Drink</hi> for any <hi>deſperate Diſeaſe</hi> that is curable.</head>
               <p>TAke of <hi>Hermodactiles</hi> 2 ounces, of <hi>Salſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parilla</hi> 4 ounces, of <hi>Sena Alexandrina</hi> 4 ounces, of <hi>Saſſafras</hi> 2 ounes, of <hi>Licoriſh</hi> 1 ounce, of <hi>Aniſeſeeds</hi> 1 ounce, of long <hi>Pepper</hi> half an ounce, of the <hi>leaves</hi> of <hi>Scabius</hi> a great handful, of <hi>Watercreſſes</hi> and <hi>Brooklime,</hi> of each one great handull, <hi>Sea-ſcurvygraſs</hi> 2 great handfuls, <hi>Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg</hi> 1 ounce, let all the Weeds be ſlit and cut ſmall, and the Herbs ſhred, and put it into a bag, and hang it in a barrell with 6 Gallons of new <hi>Ale,</hi> and let it ſtand and ſetle 8 dayes, then drink continually of it, and no other drink while it laſteth, and eat Bakers Bread with <hi>Corianderſeeds,</hi> and keep a good diet uſe this 6 weeks together, and doubtles you will recover.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:169737:52"/>
               <head>For a Quartane <hi>Ague.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Red-Wine,</hi> and <hi>new-Milk,</hi> of a Cow that is all of one Colour, of each of them a pottle; then take 3 or 4 handfuls of <hi>Mouſe-ear,</hi> of <hi>Lettice,</hi> and <hi>Strawberry-leaves,</hi> of each 2 handfulls, well picked and waſhed, ſtrip them into the <hi>Wine</hi> and <hi>Milk,</hi> and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per them all together, and let them ſtand ſo for the ſpace of one night; then put them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a fair ſtill, and ſo diſtill them with a ſoft fire, then take the <hi>Water</hi> and put it into a <hi>Glaſs,</hi> and ſet it where it may ſtand in the <hi>Sun</hi> for the ſpace of five dayes, and let the Patient when he is dry in his <hi>Ague,</hi> drink thereof 3 or 4 times, and he ſhall be rid of his <hi>Ague,</hi> and this <hi>drink</hi> will quench his thirſt be he never ſo drie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A moſt ſoveraign <hi>Balſam</hi> for <hi>22</hi> ſeverall <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes,</hi> with the Vertues.</head>
               <p>TAke five Pints of <hi>Sallet-Oyl,</hi> one pound of <hi>Venus-Turpentine,</hi> half a pound of <hi>Virgins-Wax,</hi> ſix ounces of <hi>Red Sanders,</hi> half a Pinte of <hi>Damask-Roſe water.</hi> Firſt put your Oyl with ſix ſpoonfuls of the <hi>Roſe-water,</hi> into a clean skellet, or new Pipkin, and let it boyl
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:169737:52"/>
a quarter of an hour, waſh the <hi>Turpentine</hi> with the reſt of the <hi>Roſe water,</hi> pare the <hi>Wax</hi> clean, and cut it into thin ſlices; and put it into an other clean Skellet, or new Pipkin, with the <hi>Turpentine;</hi> Let them be well melted and mixed together: then pour the <hi>water</hi> from the <hi>Oyl</hi> (if you can ſee any) &amp; put it into the <hi>Wax</hi> &amp; <hi>Turpentine,</hi> &amp; let them boyl upon a gentle fire, a doſen Walms: Then take it off, and put in the <hi>Saunders</hi> by two ounces at a time, mingling and ſtirring it well: Then let it boyl a doſen walms more, ſtir it to avoid burning, then ſtrain it into a <hi>Baſon,</hi> and fill it into <hi>Gally Pots.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Vertues.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Green Wound.</hi> Warm it, and pour it into the <hi>Wound,</hi> lay a <hi>dubble Cloth</hi> on it, <hi>dipped</hi> in <hi>Balſam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Burn<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or Scald.</hi> Apply it hot if the <hi>Skin</hi> be not broken, and bathe it well: but if the <hi>Skin</hi> be broken, then not ſo hot; bathe it well, and lay on a <hi>dipped Cloth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dog-Biting.</hi> Warm it and boyl the place well, and lay on it a <hi>dipped Cloth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bruiſe.</hi> If the <hi>Brest</hi> or <hi>Stomack</hi> be bruiſed, eat the quantity of a <hi>Nutmeg,</hi> and drink a little <hi>Bear</hi> after it, and lay a <hi>dipped Cloth</hi> on the place.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:169737:53"/>
                  <hi>Swelling.</hi> Bathe it well and warm, and lay a <hi>dubble dipped Cloth</hi> to it, bind it up.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aches in the Head.</hi> Anoint the <hi>Temples</hi> warm, and apply to the <hi>Nape of the Neck</hi> a <hi>hot dipped Cloth,</hi> when you go to Bed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Joints</hi> or <hi>Sinews.</hi> Eat in the morning as much of it as a <hi>Nutmeg.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gowt.</hi> Bathe the place ſcalding hot, and lay a <hi>dubble dipt Cloth,</hi> and bind it up.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wind-Collick.</hi> Eat as much of it as a <hi>Nut,</hi> and bathe the place very hot, and lay on it a <hi>dubble dipped Cloth,</hi> and bind it up.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pleureſie.</hi> After <hi>Blood-Letting</hi> eat ſo much of it as a <hi>Nut,</hi> &amp; bathe the <hi>Left-ſide</hi> very hot.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Surfeit.</hi> If you be <hi>Surfeited</hi> or have any <hi>poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonfull Diſeaſe,</hi> eat ſo much of it as an <hi>Nutmeg.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcer, Fiſtulo.</hi> Pour it into the <hi>Sore,</hi> as hot as you can endure it, and lay a <hi>dubble dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped Cloth,</hi> to it, and bind it up.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Canker.</hi> Warme it, and rub the place very well that is grieved with a Rag.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Stone.</hi> If it be in the <hi>Kidnies,</hi> take a Pint of <hi>White Wine</hi> and make it boyl (but not burn) brue it with <hi>Sugar,</hi> and drink a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a Pint of it morning and evening warm, and eat ſo much of it as a <hi>Walnut</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you drink.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wormes.</hi> Eat ſo much of it as a <hi>Nut</hi> in a poonful or two of <hi>Milk,</hi> &amp; eat a Meſſe of <hi>Milk</hi>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:169737:53"/>
after it, anoint the <hi>Navell</hi> with it, you may adminiſter it to <hi>Old-folks,</hi> or <hi>Children.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Flowers.</hi> Eat ſo much of it as a <hi>Nutmeg.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Provoke ſleep.</hi> Eat ſo much of it as a Nut, and anoint the Temples warm.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Spleen.</hi> Eat ſo much of it as a Nutmeg, and anoint the place very hot.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Running of the Reines.</hi> Make a <hi>Caudle</hi> of <hi>Eggs</hi> and <hi>Ale,</hi> and put in <hi>Sugar, Cynamon,</hi> and <hi>Nutmeg</hi> beaten to powder, and ſo much of the <hi>Balſam</hi> as a <hi>Nutmeg;</hi> drink it warm, and anoint the <hi>Reines</hi> of the Back very well, and hot, and lay to it a <hi>dubble dipped Cloth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sciatica.</hi> Bathe the place very hot, and lay on it a <hi>dubble dipped Cloth,</hi> and bind it up.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plague.</hi> Eat ſo much of it as a <hi>Nutmeg</hi> every morning, and put a little of it in your <hi>Noſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Green-ſicknes.</hi> Eat ſo much of it as a <hi>Nutmeg</hi> every morning, &amp; walk a good while after.</p>
               <p>Note that when you apply a <hi>cloth</hi> dipped to any <hi>Wound, Swelling,</hi> or <hi>Bruiſe,</hi> you muſt do it very hot.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſpeciall good <hi>Receipt</hi> for the <hi>Falling-Sicknes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke of <hi>Boxleaves</hi> 3 handfulls, of <hi>Pionie-roots</hi> ſmall and thin ſliced 2 handfulls, of <hi>Pionie-ſeed</hi> pilled 6 ounces: Boil theſe in 3 Gallons of <hi>Ale</hi> or <hi>Bear</hi> to 2 Gallons, then
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:169737:54"/>
give of this drink to the Patient, every day twice a good draught warm, and by Gods bleſſing he ſhall recover.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A marvelous good <hi>Medicine</hi> for the <hi>Deafneſſe</hi> in the <hi>Ear.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke of the pulp of <hi>Colloquintida,</hi> the ſeeds clean picked out and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t away, 1 ſcruple: infuſe it 6 hours in half an ounce of <hi>Oyl,</hi> of <hi>Bitter Almonds,</hi> and 5 grains of <hi>Civit,</hi> being well incorporated: let it ſtand in a <hi>Glaſs</hi> in <hi>Warm-Water</hi> 6 hours as aforeſaid. Reſerve this, and when you have uſe of it, with a feather, drop when you go to Bed, thrice a week two or three drops into your ear, lying upon the contrary ear, and ſo ſleep, that ear being ſtopped with Wooll.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An approved <hi>Remedie</hi> for the <hi>Plague,</hi> and to prevent infection.</head>
               <p>TAke three Pints of the beſt <hi>Malmſey,</hi> boyl therein one handfull of <hi>Rue,</hi> and one handfull of <hi>Sage,</hi> till one Pint be boyled away: then ſtrain it, after ſet it over the fire again, and put thereto <hi>Long-Pepper, Ginger,</hi> and <hi>Nutmegs,</hi> all theſe three beaten together one ounce: then boyl all theſe together a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:169737:54"/>
more: after take it off from the fire, and put therein 1 ounce of the beſt <hi>Mithridatum,</hi> and 2 ounces of the beſt <hi>Treakle,</hi> &amp; a quarter of a Pint of the beſt <hi>Aquavitae:</hi> So keep this as thy life, above all other things or Medicines, and make uſe thereof, <hi>viz.</hi> Note this well:</p>
               <p>If thou think thy ſelf to be at any time in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected of the <hi>Plague,</hi> take every Morning and Evening one ſpoonfull at a time luke-warm; if not infected, take this but once or twice a week at the moſt, and but half a ſpoonfull at a time.</p>
               <p>In any Plague-time truſt in God, and next under God truſt to this, for there was never Man, Woman, nor Child, that ever this Drink deceived, if the heart be not clean mortified, and drowned with poyſon too long before.</p>
               <p>It is not only good againſt the common <hi>Plague;</hi> but alſo the next kin to the <hi>Plague,</hi> as the <hi>Swelling-Sicknes, Small-Pox, Meaſels, Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit</hi> and ſuch like, taking a ſpoonfull of it when thou firſt falleſt ſick, and at all other times as need requireth.</p>
               <p>Aſſure your ſelves, this is better then <hi>Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zer-ſtone,</hi> to draw away all infection from the Heart.</p>
               <p>Where any ſick Party drinks thereof, they muſt lye down and ſweat, two or three hours
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:169737:55"/>
in Bed, and after be very well dried, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry warm kept, drinking nothing but warm drink and Caudles; ſo ſhall the ſicknes keep from thy Heart, &amp;c. This Drink will keep half a year good, being well covered. An <hi>Aquavitae</hi> Bottle will keep this Drink very well. This hath been proved of many, and never failed, but did good with Gods help.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An excellent and approved Medicine for the <hi>Piles.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke two handfuls of <hi>Souhern-wood,</hi> and ſtrip the leaves from the ſtalk then take new freſh <hi>Butter,</hi> (as it cometh from the <hi>Churne</hi> unſalted) and a little <hi>Saffron</hi> Bruiſe the Herbs, and fry them in a <hi>Frying-Pan,</hi> with the aforeſaid <hi>Butter,</hi> untill they are become tender: then take and ſpread them upon a fine linen Cloth, and lay them to the ſore place, as hot as poſſibly it may be ſuffered, and doubtles this will help.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſpeciall <hi>Receipt</hi> to ſtanch the bleeding of the <hi>Piles.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke a good quantity of the <hi>Juice</hi> of <hi>Milfoil,</hi> &amp; put thereto a pretty quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of the powder of burnt <hi>Garlick,</hi> and let the party grieved drink thereof, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:169737:55"/>
in <hi>Ale</hi> or <hi>Wine,</hi> and the Piles will dye in a ſhort ſpace.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Leaves</hi> of <hi>Mullet,</hi> and Leaves of an <hi>Elder-Tree,</hi> and ſtamp them very well, and mingle them with a <hi>Butter</hi> that is unſalted, and anoint the place grieved of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten therewith before a good fire, and this will cure you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To <hi>Looſen</hi> the <hi>Body</hi> of one that is hard <hi>Bound.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke a <hi>Chickin,</hi> and a pretty quantity of <hi>Caſſia Fiſtula:</hi> Boyl theſe in fair <hi>run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning-Water,</hi> and drink the Broth there of, and it will immediately procure looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes without pain.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for the ſame purpoſe.</head>
               <p>TAke the <hi>Juice</hi> of <hi>Southernwood,</hi> and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oint your <hi>Belly</hi> well therewith, and it will looſen your Body very gently.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A ſpeciall</hi> Remedy <hi>for thoſe</hi> that ſpit Blood.</head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Betony, Mints, Smalledge, Yarrow,</hi> and <hi>Rue,</hi> of each a like quantity: Boyl them
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:169737:56"/>
all together in new <hi>Milk,</hi> and let the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſup it off as hot as he can endure it, and it will help him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An approved <hi>Receipt</hi> to <hi>ſtanch</hi> the <hi>Bleeding</hi> of any <hi>Wound.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke a <hi>linnen-cloth</hi> and burn it; then take the powder thereof, and ſpread it thick upon another cloth, and lay it to the <hi>Wound,</hi> and it will ſtanch the bleeding of it imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately.</p>
               <p>Alſo take <hi>Pimpernel,</hi> and hold it between your <hi>Teeth,</hi> and you ſhall not bleed any more whileſt you hold it there.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another excellent <hi>Remedy</hi> to <hi>ſtanch Bleeding.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke a <hi>Toad,</hi> and dry him very well in the <hi>Sun,</hi> then put him into a <hi>linnen-bag,</hi> and hang him with a ſtring about the <hi>Neck</hi> of the party that bleedeth, and let it hang ſo low that it may touch the Breſt on the left ſide neer unto the Heart, and this will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly ſtay all manner of Bleeding at the <hi>Mouth, Noſe, Wound,</hi> or otherwiſe whatſoever.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:169737:56"/>
               <head>A ſpeciall <hi>Remedy</hi> to cure one that is <hi>bitten</hi> of a <hi>Mad Dog.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Night ſhade, Betony,</hi> and Wild <hi>Sage,</hi> of each a handfull, and a pint of fair <hi>Running Water:</hi> Stamp the Herbs, and ſtrain them with the ſaid <hi>Water,</hi> and then put thereto one peny-worth of <hi>Treakle,</hi> and ſo give it the party to drink 3 or 4 mornings together faſting, and apply the <hi>Herbs</hi> ſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the <hi>Wound,</hi> and this will ſhortly help.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another excellent <hi>Medicine</hi> for the <hi>biting</hi> of a <hi>Mad Dog, Adder,</hi> or <hi>Snake,</hi> or any other Venimous Beaſt.</head>
               <p>DRink in <hi>Dragon-water,</hi> the powder of <hi>Crefiſh ſhels,</hi> with <hi>Mithridat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>:</hi> and apply to the Wound <hi>Garlick,</hi> and powder of <hi>Crefiſh-ſhels,</hi> mixed and ſtrained together.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To avoid the <hi>ſtinging</hi> or <hi>biting</hi> either by <hi>Waſps</hi> or <hi>Bees.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke a good quantity of <hi>Mallows;</hi> ſtamp them, and mingle them with <hi>Oyl-Olive,</hi> and whatſoever part of your Body is anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed therewith, neither <hi>Waſps</hi> nor <hi>Bees</hi> will touch there.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:169737:57"/>
               <head>A ſpeciall <hi>Receipt</hi> to deſtroy <hi>Lice.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Frankincenſe,</hi> and beat it into fine powder, and a good quantity of <hi>Bores-greaſe:</hi> Boil them together in an <hi>Earthen Pan,</hi> and when it's boiled, anoint therewith the place where the <hi>Lice</hi> are, and you ſhall be ſuddenly rid of them</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for the ſame purpoſe.</head>
               <p>TAke two peny-worth of <hi>Staves-acre,</hi> beat it into very fine powder, then ſearſe it, and mingle the ſame with <hi>Sope,</hi> and <hi>Tobacco Aſhes,</hi> and ſo make an <hi>Ointment</hi> thereof; uſe this often, and it will ſpeedily deſtroy them all.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſingular approved <hi>Medicine</hi> for one that is <hi>burſt</hi> in the <hi>Belly</hi> or <hi>Cods.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke a handfull of <hi>Camphire,</hi> a handfull of <hi>Polypodium,</hi> (otherwiſe called <hi>Oak-Fern,</hi>) a handfull of <hi>Knot-worth,</hi> a pottle of <hi>White-wine, Knot-gras,</hi> and <hi>Solomons-ſeal,</hi> of each a handfull, half a pound of <hi>Raiſins</hi> of the <hi>Sun, Mace</hi> 3 drachms, <hi>Dates</hi> 4 drachms: Put all theſe together in an <hi>Earthen-Pot,</hi> and ſtop it cloſe: then take a Kettle of five or
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:169737:57"/>
ſix Gallons, and fill it with <hi>Water,</hi> and ſet it on the fire, then take the ſaid <hi>Earthen-pot,</hi> and ſtop it very cloſe with a little <hi>Paſte,</hi> and put it into the <hi>Kettle</hi> of <hi>Water</hi> aforeſaid, and let the <hi>Water</hi> boil continually, the ſpace of 5 or 6 hours at the leaſt, with the <hi>Earthen-Pot</hi> therein; and keep another <hi>Kettle</hi> ſtill boiling with <hi>Water,</hi> to ſupply the want of that which boyleth away, then take the <hi>Earthen pot</hi> out of it, and take out all the things that are therein, and beat them in a <hi>Mortar,</hi> then ſtrain them, and give the patient of this Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor to drink both firſt and laſt, and it will cure him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A marvelous good <hi>Medicine</hi> for thoſe that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not void <hi>Water.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Wood-Betony</hi> both the <hi>Roots</hi> and <hi>Leaves</hi> of it, waſh them very clean, and dry them in an <hi>Oven,</hi> then beat them into fine powder, and drink the ſame in <hi>White-wine, Poſſet-Ale,</hi> or any ordinary drink, and it will cauſe you immediately to void water with eaſe, although you were much troubled therewith before.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:169737:58"/>
               <head>Another for the ſame purpoſe.</head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Ivie-berries,</hi> and beat them to pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and let the Patient drink it in <hi>White-wint,</hi> or in ſtale <hi>Ale</hi> ſomewhat hot, and it will cauſe him forthwith to make <hi>Water</hi> that often could not.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſingular good <hi>Medicine</hi> to cure the <hi>Strangury.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke red <hi>Bramble-berries,</hi> (but take them before they become black) and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>Ivie-berries</hi> and <hi>Acorns;</hi> put theſe into two ſeverall pots, and let them ſtand in an Oven to dry untill they be fit to be beaten into powder: Then take <hi>Sitia Alexandrina, Perſley-ſeeds, Grommelſeeds, Broom-ſeeds, Corian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-ſeeds,</hi> and of the inward part or pith of <hi>Aſhen-keyes,</hi> of each of theſe a like quantity, add thereunto twice as much <hi>Licoriſh</hi> finely ſcraped, as the weight or ſubſtance of all theſe cometh to: Afterward beat them all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to powder, and mix them all together, and uſe to drink hereof both morning and even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Poſſet-drink,</hi> made with <hi>White-wine</hi> or elſe with <hi>Reniſh wine.</hi> Uſe this drink twice or thrice a week at the leaſt, and you will find great eaſe, and comfort thereby.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:169737:58"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>An approved</hi> Remedy for a <hi>Bruiſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Wall-wort, Smalledge,</hi> and <hi>Balm,</hi> of each a handfull, ſtamp them altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther well in a <hi>Mortar,</hi> then add thereunto a pound of <hi>May-butter,</hi> and mix them all well together, afterward make them into round <hi>Balls,</hi> and let them lie by you for the ſpace of 7 or 8 dayes; then ſtamp them again as you did before, and after you have done ſo, take it and fry it, and ſtrain it, and put it into an earthen <hi>Pot,</hi> and ſouce it, and this will cure the bruiſe, be it never ſo black.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſingular good <hi>Receipt</hi> for all manner of <hi>Bruiſes,</hi> and ſprainings of the <hi>Sinews.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke a pottle of <hi>Neats-foot-Oyl,</hi> and a quart of <hi>Ox-gall,</hi> a pint of <hi>Aquavitae,</hi> and a pint of <hi>Roſe-water,</hi> likewiſe <hi>Bay-leaves, Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary</hi> ſtripped from the ſtalk, <hi>Strawberry-leaves</hi> roots and ſtrings <hi>Lavender-cotten,</hi> of each a handfull: beat them very ſmall, and put thereunto the aforeſaid ſtuff, and let it boil on the fire in a Pot or Pipkin that holdeth two Gallons: and at your perill ſee that the flame touch not the ſtuff: Let it boyl very well, then take it off, and let it ſtand untill
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:169737:59"/>
it be almoſt cold: then ſtrain it through a courſe linnen cloth, (but not the grounds or botom of the ſaid Liquor) then put it into a Glaſſe, and ſo keep it; and when occaſion ſerveth, anoint the place grieved therewith, and it will help you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A very good <hi>Medicine</hi> for young <hi>Children</hi> that are bound in the <hi>Belly</hi> and troubled with <hi>Wormes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke one ſcruple of the <hi>pulp</hi> of <hi>Colloquin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tida:</hi> Infuſe it in pure <hi>Sallet-Oyl</hi> for the ſpace of 24 hours; or elſe infuſe 2 ſcruples of <hi>Aloes-Cicatrina</hi> pounded in warm <hi>Sallet-Oyl:</hi> Anoint the Childs <hi>Navill</hi> when he goeth to bed, with either of theſe, and it will give him 2 or 3 ſtools, and deſtroy the <hi>Worms</hi> in the Body.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſingular good <hi>Receipt</hi> to cure a <hi>Canker</hi> upon a mans <hi>Yard.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Roch-Allom</hi> one ounce, and half an ounce of <hi>Verdigreaſe;</hi> Mingle them well in <hi>Smiths-water,</hi> and put altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into ſome <hi>Glaſſe</hi> or other <hi>Veſſell</hi> cloſe ſtopped, and when they are well ſoaked, boil them for the ſpace of 2 hours, then ſtrain
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:169737:59"/>
them, and put it in again into the <hi>Glaſs</hi> or <hi>Veſſell</hi> aforeſaid, and ſtop it very cloſe: Anoint your <hi>Yard</hi> often therewith, and it will ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily deſtroy the <hi>Canker.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A marvellous good <hi>Remedy</hi> to cure the <hi>Sciatica.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke the <hi>Oyl</hi> of <hi>Neats-foot,</hi> &amp; <hi>Aqua-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſita;</hi> Mingle and incorporate both well together, when you have done ſo, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint the place grieved well therewith, then take <hi>Wooll</hi> that is newly plucked off from the <hi>Sheeps</hi> back, and lay it thereupon, and keep it cloſe wrapped in with warm clothes, and this will afford preſent eaſe and comfort.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A wonderfull good <hi>Medicine</hi> to cleanſe the <hi>Mouth,</hi> and faſten the <hi>Teeth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Woodbine-leaves</hi> and <hi>Sage,</hi> of each a good handfull, and a ſpoonful or more of pure <hi>Engliſh Honey,</hi> and a piece of <hi>Allom</hi> of the quantity of a big <hi>Wallnut:</hi> Boil all theſe together in a quart of fair <hi>Running-water,</hi> and boil them untill the one half be conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, or boiled away, then ſtrain it through a fine <hi>Linen-cloth,</hi> and waſh your mouth and teeth well therewith, (luke-warm) &amp; it wil both cleanſe your <hi>Mouth</hi> of all corruption,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:169737:60"/>
and filth, and faſten your <hi>Teeth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A marvelous good <hi>Remedy</hi> for the <hi>Gowt,</hi> which never faileth.</head>
               <p>TAke half a pound of unwrought <hi>Wax,</hi> half a pound of <hi>Roſin,</hi> and one ounce of <hi>Libanum,</hi> a quarter of a pound of <hi>Lettargie</hi> of <hi>Gold,</hi> and 3 quarters of a pound of <hi>White-Lead</hi> beaten to powder: ſearſe it through a <hi>Searſer;</hi> then take a pint of <hi>Neatsfoot-Oyl,</hi> and ſet it over the fire, in ſome ſmall <hi>Veſſel,</hi> and mingle it with the <hi>Wax,</hi> and <hi>Roſin,</hi> and when it is melted, put all the other powders therin: then ſtir it as faſt as ever you can with a ſtick, and put a litle of it into a <hi>Pewter ſaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer,</hi> and if it be hard (being ſo tried in the <hi>Sawcer</hi>) then take it from the fire, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oint ſome fair even board with ſome of the <hi>Neatsfoot-Oyl,</hi> and as ſoon as you are able to handle it by reaſon of the heat, work it as it were <hi>Shoemakers wax,</hi> and ſo make it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to great <hi>Rolls,</hi> or <hi>Balls.</hi> Make plaiſters here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of with a Chafindiſh of Coles; ſpread it upon a piece of <hi>Leather,</hi> apply it warm to the place where the pain or Grief is, and renew it ſo every morning and evening, untill the pain be clean gone, or untill it be drawn in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſome other joint, and then apply your plaiſters in like ſort where the grief is, and
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:169737:60"/>
beware of cold or hot <hi>Wines,</hi> and queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les this will help you. It hath cured many whom <hi>Doctors</hi> and <hi>Surgeans</hi> have given over as incurable.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An approved <hi>Receipt</hi> for the <hi>Swelling</hi> of the <hi>Yard</hi> or <hi>Cods.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Agrimonie-water</hi> diſtilled, and add thereunto a pretty quantity of <hi>Roch-Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom:</hi> Set them over the fire to ſoak, and let them remain there untill they be ready to boyl, then take it off from the fire, and with a fine <hi>Linnen-cloth</hi> anoint the <hi>Yard</hi> well un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the skin with the ſame <hi>Water,</hi> (but let it be warm when you uſe it) and it will aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwage the extreme <hi>Heat</hi> of the Yard, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of the <hi>Cods,</hi> if they be waſhed with the ſame, and take away the <hi>Swelling</hi> thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another excellent <hi>Remedy</hi> or <hi>Medicine</hi> to heal the hot <hi>Swelling</hi> in the <hi>Yard.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Wax, Oyl,</hi> and the <hi>Juice</hi> of <hi>Purſlane,</hi> of each a pretty quantity; Mingle them all together, and apply them to the Yard that is ſwollen, and you ſhall find preſent help.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:169737:61"/>
               <head>A ſpeciall <hi>Receipt</hi> to incarnate the skin of the <hi>Yard</hi> within.</head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Fumitary-water,</hi> and ſteep therein a good quantity of <hi>Licoriſh</hi> pared, for the ſpace of one night: then put of the ſame <hi>Water</hi> into the <hi>Yard</hi> with a <hi>Spunge,</hi> or with a <hi>Tent</hi> made of <hi>Linnen-cloth,</hi> and it will do the deed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſoveraign <hi>Remedy</hi> for one that <hi>Bleedeth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke a pretty quantity of the <hi>juice</hi> of <hi>Neep,</hi> and likewiſe of the <hi>juice</hi> or <hi>powder</hi> of <hi>Shepherds-purſe,</hi> mingle both together, and let the party grieved drink thereof, and it will cauſe the blood to be caſt up immediately.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To <hi>ſtanch Bleeding</hi> at the <hi>Noſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke of the powder of <hi>Bole-Armoniack,</hi> and with a <hi>Quill</hi> or ſome other <hi>Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> blow ſome of the ſame powder into the <hi>Noſe</hi> of the party that is given to much bleeding, and it will <hi>ſtanch</hi> the <hi>Blood</hi> immediately.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:169737:61"/>
               <head>Another approved <hi>Receipt</hi> to <hi>ſtanch</hi> the <hi>bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of the <hi>Noſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Inckle,</hi> and bind the patient about the Temples of the head very hard therewith, and let the knot be in his <hi>Neck,</hi> and this will ſtanch bleeding without any more ado.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An excellent <hi>Receipt</hi> to cure the <hi>Heart-burning.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke 5 or 6 Corns of the beſt <hi>Pepper,</hi> bruiſe or chaw them in your mouth, and then let them down your throat, and it will eaſe the <hi>Heart-burning.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A very good <hi>Medicine</hi> to cure the <hi>Hemorhoids.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke the <hi>Leaves</hi> of <hi>Mullet,</hi> and likewiſe the <hi>Leaves</hi> of an <hi>Elder-tree;</hi> ſtamp or beat them both very well together, and min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle them with freſh <hi>Butter:</hi> Anoint the place grieved often therewith before a good fire, and it will cure you without all doubt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſpeciall good <hi>Salve</hi> or <hi>Ointment</hi> to cure any <hi>Wound,</hi> or <hi>Sore</hi> whether new or old.</head>
               <p>TAke half a pint of <hi>Sallet-Oyl,</hi> 4 ounces of unwrought <hi>Wax,</hi> 1 ounce of <hi>Turpentine,</hi> 4
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:169737:62"/>
ounces of <hi>Roſin,</hi> and 1 ounce of <hi>Maſtick;</hi> Item of <hi>Smalledge, Woodbine-leaves, Plantane,</hi> and <hi>Marigold-leaves,</hi> of each one handfull, and of the <hi>tops</hi> of <hi>Hyſop,</hi> half an handfull, waſh them all very well, and then dry them in the <hi>Sun</hi> for the ſpace of half a day together: then ſtamp them in a <hi>Mortar,</hi> and ſtrain them, and take the <hi>juice</hi> thereof, and boil it with all the other things before mentioned, (except only <hi>Turpentine</hi>) and ſtir it continually un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till you find all the <hi>juice</hi> to be dried up; then put in your <hi>Turpentine,</hi> and let it boil a walm or two, then take it off from the fire, and when it hath ſtood a while, ſtrain it through a courſe <hi>Linen-cloth,</hi> and keep it in Boxes or Gally-pots, untill you have occaſion to uſe it. This ſalve cureth all manner of <hi>Sores</hi> both new and old.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſpeciall and approved <hi>Medicine</hi> for the <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitations</hi> or <hi>Beatings</hi> of the <hi>Heart.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke a pottle of the beſt <hi>Claret-Wine,</hi> that is to be had for money, and add there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto an handfull of <hi>Balm,</hi> an handfull of <hi>Burrage,</hi> 6 tops of <hi>Roſemary,</hi> half a quarter of an ounce of <hi>Engliſh-Saffron</hi> whole, and a quarter of a pound of the beſt fine <hi>Sugar:</hi> mingle all theſe well together, and put them
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:169737:62"/>
into ſome cloſe Veſſel well ſtopped, and let it ſo ſtand for the ſpace of a day or more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you uſe it. Drink hereof a good draught at a time both firſt and laſt, and continue ſo doing for 7 or 8 dayes together, or more (it will not be amiſs) and you ſhall find comfort and help thereby.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To take away <hi>Warts</hi> out of the hands or any part of the Body.</head>
               <p>TAke the <hi>Heart</hi> or <hi>Pith</hi> of a <hi>Red Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woort:</hi> ſtamp it well, and temper it well with a little <hi>Honey,</hi> and rub the <hi>Wart</hi> oftentimes well therewith, and it will take it away.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another excellent <hi>Remedy</hi> to take away <hi>Warts.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke 3 or 4 handfuls of wild <hi>Tanſie,</hi> 2 peny-worth of <hi>May-butter</hi> unſalted, and 2 peny-worth of <hi>Quick-ſilver:</hi> Mince the <hi>Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie</hi> ſmall, and then put it into the <hi>Butter,</hi> and ſet it on the fire, and let them boyl well to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; afterward take it off from the fire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and ſtrain it through a fine <hi>linnen-cloth,</hi> but put in your <hi>Quick-ſilver</hi> firſt, before you ſtrain it, and let it be well mingled and incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated with the reſt, and then anoit the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:169737:63"/>
place therewith, where the <hi>Warts</hi> are, and this will take them clean away.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſpeciall <hi>Receit</hi> to heal a <hi>Whitflaw,</hi> or <hi>Fellon.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke a little <hi>Bay Salt,</hi> ſtamp it very ſmall, and alſo a little <hi>Leven,</hi> or <hi>ſower Bread,</hi> min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle theſe well together with the <hi>Yolk</hi> of an <hi>Egg,</hi> and apply it to the <hi>Sore</hi> twice a day, and it will draw pain from the Arm, ceaſe the ſwelling (if there be any) &amp; heal it preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and with ſpeed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A very good Remedy for the <hi>Swelling</hi> of the <hi>Legs</hi> occaſion'd by cold, or otherwiſe.</head>
               <p>TAke 2 <hi>White Herrings</hi> out of the <hi>Pickle,</hi> open them, and lay the inſides of them to the ſoles of your feet, when you go to bed, and ſo let them remain all night, and in the morning apply new ones again; uſe this five or ſix times and it will help you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A very good <hi>Receipt</hi> to heal the <hi>Itch.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke eleven or twelve <hi>Dock-roots</hi> of the yelloweſt that can be gotten, &amp; ſcrape them very clean, then cut them very ſmall,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:169737:63"/>
and ſtamp them well in a <hi>Mortar,</hi> then ſet them over a <hi>Chafingdiſh</hi> of <hi>Coles,</hi> and put a pound of ſweet <hi>Butter</hi> therein, and let them boil untill the Roots be ready to ſtrain, and when they are ſufficiently boild, ſtrain them, and put into the <hi>juice</hi> a ſpoonfull of <hi>Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone,</hi> finely beaten to powder, and ſtir it well together, then let it ſtand till it be quite cold, and it will be a pure Salve. Anoint your body therewith before a good fire, and let it ſoake into the Skin: Uſe this <hi>Medicine</hi> morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and evening for 6 or 7 dayes together, and it will quite take away the <hi>Itch,</hi> be it never ſo great.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An approved <hi>Remedy</hi> for the <hi>Morphew.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke of the <hi>juice</hi> of <hi>Selandine:</hi> mingle it with powder of <hi>Brimſtone,</hi> and lay it to the place where the <hi>Morphew</hi> is, (all cold) uſe this 4 or 5 times, and it will aſſuredly help you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for the ſame purpoſe.</head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Mustard-ſeed</hi> and <hi>Salt,</hi> and ſtamp them well together in a <hi>Mortar</hi> with <hi>Wine-Vineger:</hi> Anoint the place grieved well therewith, and in a very ſhort time it will cure it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:169737:64"/>
               <head>A wonderous good <hi>Receipt</hi> for <hi>Legs</hi> that do ranckle or feſter.</head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Smallage, Southernwood, Houſe-leek, Violet-leaves,</hi> and <hi>Roots,</hi> and <hi>Waybroad-leaves,</hi> of each a good quantity, and a good quantity of <hi>Honey.</hi> Temper all well together, and ſtrain it through a fine <hi>linen cloth:</hi> Make a plaiſter thereof, and lay it to the <hi>Sore,</hi> and renew it twice every day, and alwayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you lay on the plaiſters, waſh the <hi>Sore</hi> well with <hi>White-wine,</hi> or with <hi>Oyl</hi> of <hi>Roſes,</hi> and as long as you continue this <hi>Medicine,</hi> uſe to put 5 or 6 Leaves of <hi>Sage</hi> in your drink and in a ſhort ſpace your <hi>Legs</hi> will be ſound and whole.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſoverain <hi>Medicine</hi> for a <hi>Burning</hi> ro <hi>Scalding.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke a <hi>Brake-root,</hi> and ſtamp it well in a <hi>Mortar,</hi> then ſtrain out the <hi>juice</hi> thereof clean; anoint the place burned or ſcalded well therewith, and it ſtraightway helpeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another for the ſame purpoſe.</head>
               <p>TAke of the <hi>Parings</hi> of new-liquor'd <hi>Shoe-makers-leather,</hi> boil them in <hi>Water,</hi> and let
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:169737:64"/>
them ſtand till they be cold: then ſcum off the <hi>Fat</hi> or <hi>Oyl</hi> on the top of them: Mingle t with a little <hi>juice</hi> of <hi>Houſleek</hi> and <hi>Roſewater:</hi> Beat theſe together, and make an <hi>Ointment</hi> thereof; anoint the place burned or ſcalded well therewith, and it will heal it in a very ſhort ſpace.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſingular good <hi>Remedy</hi> for the <hi>Tooth-Ach.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Red-ſage,</hi> and <hi>Betony,</hi> of each a like quantity, adde thereunto a little <hi>Roch-Allum;</hi> Boil theſe in <hi>White-wine-vneger,</hi> and rub your <hi>Teeth</hi> that ake well therewith, and you ſhall incontinently feel eaſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another excellent <hi>Remedie</hi> for the <hi>Tooth-Ach.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Vineger, Honey, Aqua-vitae, Henbane-roots, Long-pepper,</hi> and <hi>Round-pepper, Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phire, Gum</hi> and <hi>Ivie,</hi> of each a like quantitie: Boil them all together untill they be hard, and let the Patient put ſome of it between his <hi>Teeth,</hi> and this will ſpeedily eaſe him. But if his Teeth grow ſore by reaſon of the extream pain, let him take a pound of <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bane-roots,</hi> and boil them in a quart of <hi>White-wine-Vineger,</hi> and a pint of <hi>Roſe-water,</hi> and when it's well boil'd put into it a little fine
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:169737:65"/>
                  <hi>Sugar</hi> to ſweeten it withall, then ſtrain it, and waſh your mouth often therewith, and it will aſſwage the pain without all doubt.</p>
               <p>If your <hi>Tooth</hi> be hallow, take 2 or 3 drops of <hi>Aqua fortis,</hi> and dip a little lint therein, and ſtop the hollow place therewith, and for the ſpace of an hour or thereabouts, it will put you to ſome pain, but in a very ſhort ſpace after it will give you eaſe: uſe this twice or thrice, and it will quite expell the pain for ever after, without periſhing the tooth any thing at all.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To heal a ſore <hi>Mouth,</hi> or <hi>Throat.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke a good handfull of <hi>Sage,</hi> and a pret<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty quantity of <hi>Roſemary,</hi> a good handful of <hi>Honey-ſuckle leaves,</hi> and of <hi>Roch-Allom</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> quantity of half a <hi>Wallnut,</hi> and a ſpoonful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of pure <hi>Engliſh-Honey:</hi> Boil them altogether in a quart of fair <hi>running Water,</hi> for a good while together: then ſtrain forth the <hi>Wate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> from the <hi>Herbs,</hi> and the other <hi>Dregs</hi> into ſome fair Glaſs, and ſtop it very cloſe, and when you will uſe it, waſh your <hi>Mouth</hi> or <hi>Throa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> both morning and evening well therewith and it will ſpeedily help it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:169737:65"/>
               <head>An excellent <hi>Medicine</hi> for the <hi>Falling-Sickneſſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Pionie-Roots,</hi> and dry them well, then cut them very ſmall, and give it the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to eat in his <hi>Pottage</hi> at meals, and let him alſo drink it continually in his drink, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in the morning faſting, and alſo laſt in the evening, and by Gods bleſſing this will cure him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſpecial <hi>Remedy</hi> for the <hi>Gowt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke a good quantity of <hi>Flint-ſtones,</hi> break them into ſmall pieces, and heat them well on coles in the fire, then put them into a <hi>Stillitory,</hi> and put therein a good quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of <hi>Wine-vineger</hi> and <hi>Aqua-vitae,</hi> and diſtil them, and with this <hi>Water</hi> often waſh the place grieved, and it will take away the pain.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An exceeding good <hi>Receipt</hi> for the <hi>Yellow Jaundice.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke a handful of red <hi>Nettle-tops, Plantane</hi> and <hi>Saffron,</hi> and boyl them well in a pint of <hi>Ale,</hi> then ſtrain it, and drink thereof for
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:169737:66"/>
4. or 5. dayes together, and you ſhall find help.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An Approved <hi>Medicine</hi> for the <hi>Small Pox.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Milk Saffron</hi> and <hi>Engliſh Honey:</hi> boil them together, and give it the Patient to drink, and let him be kept warm, and the <hi>Pox</hi> will come forth very ſpeedily.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another excellent <hi>Receipt</hi> for the ſame purpoſe.</head>
               <p>Take <hi>Dragon-water, White-wine,</hi> and <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thridatum,</hi> or <hi>Treacle of Jean,</hi> of each of them a pretty quantity, and put ſome <hi>V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicorns horne</hi> therein. Boyl all theſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and give it to the Patient, and let him be kept warm, and it will help him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſingular good <hi>Remedie</hi> for the <hi>SCIATICA.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Ivie, Mugwort, Walwort,</hi> and the inner rind of an <hi>Elder-tree:</hi> boyl them n fair <hi>water,</hi> with a good quantity of <hi>Salt:</hi> bathe the ſore place well therewith, 3. or 4.
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:169737:66"/>
times in a day, for 9. dayes together, and queſtionleſs it will eaſe it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An approved <hi>Medicine</hi> for a <hi>Stitch</hi> in the <hi>Side.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke the <hi>Vrine</hi> of him that is ſick, <hi>Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood,</hi> and <hi>Comin;</hi> ſeeth them well toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and by the fire anoint your ſide there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and after with the <hi>Oil</hi> of <hi>Bay.</hi> Alſo <hi>Endive water, Water of Devills-bit, Water</hi> of <hi>Mallows,</hi> and <hi>Cardun Benedictus-water,</hi> are all exceeding good for the <hi>Stitch.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another approved <hi>Remedie</hi> for the <hi>Stitch</hi> in the left <hi>Side.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take a pretty quantity of <hi>Comin,</hi> and ſteep it in a Pottle of <hi>Malmſey,</hi> then take and fry it in a Pan, and put it into a linen bag, and lay it hot to your <hi>fide,</hi> and it will help you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſingular good Receipt for the <hi>Collick</hi> and <hi>Stone.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Parſley-ſeed, Fennelſeed, Aniſe-ſeeds Comin-ſeed, Plantane-ſeed,</hi> of each a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an ounce, 1. ouce of <hi>Nutmegs,</hi> 4
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:169737:67"/>
ounces of fine <hi>Sugar:</hi> beat all the <hi>Seeds</hi> into pouder, and ſearce them, and let the <hi>Sugar</hi> be beaten with <hi>Ale:</hi> then take of the ſaid powder the quantity of an hazel-nut, and let the Patient drink thereof morning and even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning 4. times a week warm with <hi>Wine</hi> or <hi>Beer</hi> (but <hi>Wine</hi> is beſt) and when the pain cometh drink it with <hi>Malmſey,</hi> and you ſhall find great eaſe and and benefit thereby.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another excellent <hi>Receit</hi> for the ſame purpoſe.</head>
               <p>FRy <hi>Pellitory</hi> and <hi>Butter</hi> together, and bind them to your <hi>Navil,</hi> and this will ſuddenly ceaſe the pain. Or take a <hi>Lapwing,</hi> and burn her in the fire feathers and all, then take the <hi>Aſhes</hi> of her, and give it the Patient to drink with <hi>Wine</hi> ſomewhat warm, and this will eaſe the <hi>Collick.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the <hi>Cough</hi> of rhe <hi>Lungs.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke a handful of <hi>Figs,</hi> and ſeeth them in <hi>Ale</hi> or <hi>Beer</hi> until they be ſomewhat tender; then ſlit them aſunder, and put them in a <hi>linnen bag,</hi> and ſo lay them on your <hi>ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach</hi> warm; and when they be cold, warm
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:169737:67"/>
them again in the ſame liquor, and apply them to your <hi>ſtomach</hi> as formerly; do this ſeveral times, and by Gods grace you will ſoon find eaſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſpecial <hi>Medicine</hi> to open the <hi>LVNGS.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Take <hi>Hyſop-water,</hi> and drink thereof twice a day, evening and morning, at every time 1. ounce and a half, or 2. ounces, and you will find help.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſoverain <hi>Medicine</hi> for <hi>Fatneſs</hi> about the <hi>Heart.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke the <hi>Juice</hi> of <hi>Fenel</hi> and <hi>Honey</hi> &amp; ſeeth them all together, until they be hard; then eat thereof evening and morning, and you ſhall be whole.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A marvelous good <hi>Remedie</hi> for the <hi>French Pox<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke 6. Gallons or more of the pureſt <hi>White-wine</hi> that may be gotten, and the like quantity of ſtale <hi>Ale,</hi> 1. pound and a half of <hi>Salſaperilla, Licoriſh</hi> and <hi>Sena,</hi> of each 1. l.
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:169737:68"/>
of the <hi>Bark of Guairarum,</hi> 2. l. <hi>Colloquintida</hi> 1. ounce: Boil all together for the ſpace of 24. hours over a ſoft fire in <hi>Balneo Mariae;</hi> and when it's well boiled, put therein 1. ounce of <hi>Mithridatum;</hi> then take it off, and put it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſome earthen pot, and ſtop it up cloſe; and when you will uſe it, take a good quantity thereof at a time twice or thrice a day, and this will cleanſe both the inward and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward parts of your body, and make you very ſound ever after.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A <hi>ſpeciall</hi> Receipt <hi>for a</hi> Conſumption.</head>
               <p>TAke a pottle of <hi>Roſe-water,</hi> and the like quantity of <hi>Goats</hi> or <hi>Aſſes Milk,</hi> if it may be had, or elſe of the <hi>Milk</hi> of a <hi>Cow,</hi> that is all of one colour, &amp; put therein 50. or 60. <hi>Yolks</hi> of new-ſayd <hi>Hen-Egs;</hi> Temper the <hi>yolks,</hi> the <hi>milk,</hi> and the <hi>Roſe-waters</hi> all well together (but let none of the <hi>Whites</hi> remain among them:) Diſtill a water hereof, and give it the Patient that is in a <hi>Conſumption</hi> to drink firſt and laſt warm, with a Cake or two of <hi>Manus Chriſti,</hi> which is made of <hi>Gold</hi> or <hi>Pearls:</hi> let him uſe this, and he ſhall find great comfort and eaſe by it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:169737:68"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>A</hi> precious and wonderful good <hi>Drink</hi> to be uſed by one that is troubled with a <hi>Conſumption.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Longwort, Liverwort, Harts-tongue,</hi> and red <hi>Sage,</hi> of each a handfull, <hi>Parſley</hi> half a handfull, <hi>Licoriſh</hi> one handfull, <hi>Aniſe-ſeeds</hi> one ounce, <hi>Cynamon</hi> finely beaten to pouder one ounce, two penyworth of <hi>white Ginger,</hi> two penyworth of <hi>white Sugar-Candy</hi> two <hi>Nutmegs,</hi> and a penyworth of <hi>Cloves:</hi> and if the Patient be bound in the body, then put a little <hi>Sena,</hi> and a dram of <hi>Rhubarb</hi> therein; if not, leave theſe two things out: Boil all theſe together in a pottle or ſomewhat more of the beſt new <hi>Wort</hi> that can be gotten (but it muſt be brewed without any <hi>Hops</hi> at all) and let it boyl untill it come to three pintes: But if you put any <hi>Sena</hi> therein, then put the quantity of three quarts of the ſame <hi>Wort,</hi> and boil it to a pottle, then put it to ſtand, and ſtrain it, and ſo uſe it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:169737:69"/>
               <head>A ſpeciall Remedy for the <hi>Plague,</hi> and how to make any kind of <hi>Swelling</hi> or <hi>Plague-ſore</hi> to break.</head>
               <p>TAke a pint of <hi>ſtrong Beer,</hi> and crums of <hi>Rye Bread,</hi> one handfull of <hi>Mallows, white Lillie-roots</hi> a great lump or knob: Beat all theſe together with ſome quantity of <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeed</hi> until it become a Cataplaſm or thick pap, and ſpread it upon a <hi>linnencloth,</hi> and lay it on the Bile or ſore. If the Swelling or Sore be ripe and continue a long while before it break, then lay ſome <hi>Corraſive</hi> upon it, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially upon <hi>Plague-ſores.</hi> When the Bile or Sore is broken through, or the Corraſive hath wrought and produced a Core, then lay thereon this <hi>Tent-ſalve</hi> or Oyntment, as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth. Take <hi>Honey</hi> and <hi>Turpentine,</hi> but let the <hi>Turpentin</hi> be ſet on the fire in a little Pip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin, and ſtir it continually, and mingle with it a ſmall quantity of <hi>Honey,</hi> and when it's melt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> take it off from the fire, and ſtir it ſtill untill it beginneth to wax ſomewhat ſtiff, and then mingle therewith the yolk of an Egg with a little flower, then ſpread it upon a flat tent very thick as broad as the hole or wound is: then lay upon it the aforeſaid
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:169737:69"/>
                  <hi>Cataplaſm</hi> or Pap, untill all the corruption or filthy matter be quite drawn out, then heal it with the <hi>hard Salve,</hi> of which we ſhall treat anon: if there be any heat in or about the ſore, anoynt it round about with a white ointment called in the ſhops <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguentum Nutritum,</hi> of which alſo we ſhall give directions anon how to make it. If any <hi>Plague-blains</hi> or <hi>ſores</hi> do appear, you muſt lay the aforeſaid <hi>Tent-Salve</hi> thereon, and anoint it round about with <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguentum Nutritum.</hi> Afterward take Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel &amp; roſte or boil it in a pan in the Embers with a little <hi>butter</hi> wrapped up in a <hi>Cabbage-leaf,</hi> lay it a little warm thereon. But when you at firſt feel the ſaid dangerous diſeaſe coming upon you, uſe <hi>Mithridatum</hi> with the <hi>Water</hi> of <hi>Carduus Benedictus,</hi> or take of <hi>Bezoar-ſtone,</hi> the quantity of 6. or 7. grains mingled with Beer or Wine, and ſweat upon it. This is a wonderfull excellent Remedie for the Plague.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Directions</hi> how to make the <hi>hard Salve,</hi> which is a ſoverain <hi>Medicine</hi> to cure all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of <hi>Sores</hi> or <hi>Wounds.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Roſin, Turpentine, Bees-wax, Mutton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue</hi> of each a quarter of a pound: Boyl
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:169737:70"/>
them together in a Pipkin with 3. handfuls of <hi>Lyn-ſeed Oyl,</hi> and ſtir it continually, til it's quite melted, and if it ſhould chance to run over, ſet the Pipkin in water, and when it's quite melted, take it off from the fire, and put into it of <hi>Frankincenſe</hi> the weight of a groat, then ſtrain it through a cloth, and when it begins to be cold, put therein <hi>Lapis Calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naris</hi> very ſmall beaten to pouder, and ſtir it till it be quite cold.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How to make the <hi>White Ointment</hi> called in the ſhops <hi>Vnguentum Nutritum.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Letargie of Gold</hi> about a thimble-full, put it into a <hi>Mortar,</hi> and add thereunto as much <hi>Oyle</hi> as will quite wet or moiſten the ſame: then pour into it 2. or 3. drops of <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neger,</hi> and ſtir it well round about, then pour in <hi>Oyl</hi> again, and twice <hi>Vineger</hi> to once <hi>Oyl,</hi> and ſtir it ſo continually, till it be quite white, that no red ſpaecks any more appear. This is wonderfull good to anoint round about any ſores or ſwellings where any heat ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:169737:70"/>
               <head>A ſpecial <hi>Receipt</hi> to put away <hi>Venome</hi> from the <hi>Heart.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Bole Armoniack,</hi> and <hi>Sanguis Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conis,</hi> of each 3. ounces, and of the beſt <hi>Cynamon</hi> 4. ounces: Mingle them all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in powder, and ſo receive it, it will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell and remove <hi>Venom</hi> from the <hi>heart.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Soverain <hi>Remedie</hi> for the <hi>Gnawing</hi> about the <hi>Heart.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Sage-leaves</hi> a pretty quantity, and as much <hi>Yarrow;</hi> grind them together, and temper them with <hi>Ale;</hi> then ſtrain them, and drink thereof, and you will find preſent aeliefe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To make a very <hi>cooling</hi> and <hi>pleaſant Water</hi> to drink in <hi>Summer.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke a Gallon of <hi>Spring-water,</hi> or as much as you will, a pint of <hi>Strawberries,</hi> two ounces of <hi>Cynamon,</hi> 3. or 4. <hi>Cloves,</hi> one gram of <hi>Musk:</hi> Still theſe with a ſoft fire, and it is a very cooling and pleaſant drink, and very fit to be uſed in Summer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:169737:71"/>
               <head>A wonderfull good <hi>Remedie</hi> for young Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, that are exceeding weak in their <hi>Limbs,</hi> and can neither go nor ſtand.</head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Sage, Sweet Marjoram,</hi> of each a like quantity: beat them a long time toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſtrain out the <hi>Juice,</hi> and put it into a double <hi>Viall Glaſs:</hi> fill the <hi>Glaſs</hi> as full as it can hold; then ſtop it with <hi>Paſte</hi> very cloſe, and cover it with thick <hi>Paſte</hi> all over: then ſet it in an <hi>Oven;</hi> and there let it ſtand ſo long as a great Loaf requires time to be thorowly baked: then take it out, and let it be cold; then break the <hi>Paſte</hi> round about it, and if the <hi>Juice</hi> be grown thick, break the <hi>Glaſs,</hi> and take it in a diſh, and keep it in a <hi>Gally-pot.</hi> When you will uſe it, take the quantity of two ſpoonfuls at a time, and as much <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row</hi> of an <hi>Ox-Leg,</hi> melt them together, and mingle them well; and both morning and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening anoint therewith, as warm as can be endured, the tender parts of the Childs thighs and legs, and alſo the knees, chafing them well with your warm hands, and ſo in a ſhort time (through Gods bleſſing) it will be able to ſtand and go. <hi>This hath been tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proved.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:169737:71"/>
               <head>An approved <hi>Remedie</hi> for thoſe that cannot hold their <hi>Water.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ROſt a <hi>ſlain Mouſe,</hi> or make it in pouder, and drink it off at one draught, and it will preſently help you, eſpecially, if you uſe it 3. mornings together.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſoverain and approved <hi>Receipt</hi> for thoſe that cannot void <hi>Water.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Saſſafraſs, Perſley,</hi> and <hi>Archangel,</hi> of each a like quantity: boyl them in ſtale <hi>Ale</hi> from a quart to a pint; then ſtrain them, and let the Patient drink thereof morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and evening, and faſt one hour after it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An excellent <hi>Remedy</hi> for a <hi>Woman</hi> that hath great <hi>Breſts.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF a <hi>VVoman</hi> anoint often her <hi>Paps</hi> with the <hi>Juice</hi> of <hi>Succory,</hi> it will make them round and hard: if they be hanging or bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, it will draw them together, whereby they ſhall ſeem like the <hi>Paps</hi> of a <hi>Maid.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:169737:72"/>
               <head>A ſingular good <hi>Medicine</hi> for a <hi>Womans ſore Breſt,</hi> occaſioned by cold or otherwiſe.</head>
               <p>TAke a <hi>Cole-wort-leaf,</hi> and cut away the veins of it, and then anoint the <hi>leafe</hi> it ſelf with <hi>May-Butter,</hi> firſt boiled with <hi>Roſe-water,</hi> and then lay it to the <hi>Womans ſore breſt,</hi> and it will aſſwage both the ſwelling and pain in a ſhort time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How to increaſe <hi>Milk</hi> in a <hi>Womans</hi> Breſt.</head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Cryſtall,</hi> and beat it into fine pouder and mingle it with as much <hi>Fennel-ſeed,</hi> (likewiſe beaten into fine pouder) and a little fine <hi>Sugar:</hi> let the woman uſe to drink here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of often ſomewhat warm, with a little <hi>White-wine,</hi> and this will cauſe great ſtore of <hi>Milk</hi> to increaſe in her <hi>Breſts;</hi> yea, it will reſtore her <hi>Milk</hi> again, although it be clean gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from her.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:169737:72"/>
               <head>An excellent <hi>Remedy</hi> to take away <hi>Freckles</hi> in the <hi>Face.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke the <hi>Blood</hi> of a <hi>VVhite Hen,</hi> anoint your <hi>Face</hi> therewith, and after three or four times dreſſing, it will take away all the <hi>Spots</hi> and <hi>Freckles.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A moſt precious and approved <hi>Medicine</hi> to make the <hi>Face</hi> both <hi>fair</hi> and <hi>clear,</hi> even as white as <hi>Milk.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Bloſſoms</hi> of <hi>VVhite-Thorn,</hi> and of <hi>Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, Bloſſoms</hi> of <hi>Beans,</hi> and <hi>Bloſſoms</hi> of an <hi>Elder-Tree,</hi> of each a like quantity, and a <hi>Lemon</hi> thin ſliced, diſtill them, and put the <hi>water</hi> into a <hi>Glaſs;</hi> and ſtop it cloſe; and when you will uſe it, take two ſpoonfulls thereof, and waſh your face with it twice or thrice a day for 4. or 5. dayes together, and your skin will be exceeding clear and fair.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An excellent <hi>Gargle</hi> for a <hi>furred Mouth</hi> or <hi>Throat.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Barley-water, Strawbury-leaves, Cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quefoile,</hi> a ſtick of <hi>Licoriſh,</hi> and half a pinte
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:169737:73"/>
of <hi>VVhite-wine-Vineger,</hi> &amp; let it run through a double <hi>Linen cloth</hi> twice or thrice, after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hath been well ſteeped the rein: take this and you will find preſent help.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſolid form of <hi>Naſals.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>dry VVormwood, Marjoram, Morſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Galinae, Betony, Sage, Dictamne,</hi> of each two drams, and the ſeed of <hi>Nigella, Muſtard, Rue</hi> 1. dram, <hi>trochiſhes of Athandall</hi> 4 ſcruples, with the <hi>Juice of Beetes</hi> and <hi>Mercury:</hi> Boyl them till the <hi>Juices</hi> be conſumed; then Incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate them with a little <hi>Turpentine,</hi> and make <hi>Tents</hi> of a finger long, covering them with red ſilk and a threed at them: So put it into the <hi>Noſe,</hi> and it will cauſe a ſnotty Noſe, and Sneeſing, and cleanſe the brain very well.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An approved <hi>Receipt</hi> to heal a <hi>Fellon.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke the <hi>grounds</hi> of <hi>Ale,</hi> and a handfull of <hi>Groundſel,</hi> with a peece of <hi>ſoure Leven:</hi> Boil them together to a <hi>Salve,</hi> and apply it, and it healeth the <hi>Sore.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:169737:73"/>
               <head>A ſpeciall <hi>Receit</hi> to preſerve one from the <hi>Plague.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke of <hi>Aloes Hepatica,</hi> and of pure <hi>Cyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> and <hi>Myrrhe,</hi> of each 3 drachms, of <hi>Cloves, Mace,</hi> and <hi>Wood</hi> of <hi>Aloes</hi> (uſually cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Lignum Aloes) Maſtick,</hi> and <hi>Bole Oriental,</hi> of each 1 ounce, mingle them, and make thereof a fine powder; and drink thereof every morning faſting, either in <hi>White-wine</hi> allayed with <hi>water,</hi> or in <hi>Ale,</hi> and this by Gods help will preſerve you from being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the Plague.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another excellent <hi>Remedie</hi> to preſerve one from being infected with the <hi>Plague.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke of the <hi>Powder Imperial</hi> one drachm and an half, and one drachm of <hi>Treacle,</hi> of <hi>Dragon-water,</hi> and <hi>Sorrel-water,</hi> of each 1 ounce: Drink it with <hi>Ale</hi> in the morning faſting, and by Gods grace you ſhall eſcape the danger of the Plague.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſpeciall good <hi>Medicine</hi> to heal, and cure the <hi>Canker</hi> in a Womans <hi>Breſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke the <hi>Juice</hi> of <hi>Selandine,</hi> and <hi>Gooſe-dung</hi> of each an equal proportion; then take
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:169737:74"/>
                  <hi>Pellitory</hi> of the <hi>Wall, Garlick,</hi> and <hi>Rie-meal:</hi> ſtamp them in a <hi>Mortar,</hi> &amp; fry or boil them all together in good pure <hi>Wine vineger,</hi> and let it boil untill it be thick like a <hi>Salve:</hi> then make a <hi>Plaiſter</hi> thereof, and apply it to the <hi>Sore,</hi> and ſo let it continue untill you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that it be white: then take a good quantity of <hi>Pimpernel,</hi> and grinde it very ſmall, and adde thereunto a good quantitie of <hi>Engliſh honey,</hi> and make a <hi>Plaiſter</hi> thereof, and lay it to the <hi>Sore,</hi> and it will heal it in a very ſhort time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A ſpeciall</hi> Remedy <hi>to deſtroy a</hi> Canker <hi>in any part of the body.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke a good quantity of the <hi>Bark</hi> of a <hi>Slowe-Tree,</hi> chop it very ſmall, and boil it in ſome fair <hi>running Water,</hi> and let it boil till it be black, then temper it with a little <hi>Rie-meal,</hi> a little burnt <hi>Allom</hi> powdered, and a little <hi>Honey:</hi> Make a plaiſter thereof, and lay it to the place grieved, and it will ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily heal it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A wonderfull good <hi>Medicine</hi> for a <hi>Canker</hi> in the <hi>Mouth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Penny-royall, red Fennell, red-Sage, Roſemary-tops,</hi> and <hi>Maiden-hair,</hi> of each
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:169737:74"/>
a good handful, and a little <hi>Hyſop.</hi> Boil them together in a quart of <hi>White-wine,</hi> and put thereto the quantity of 2 <hi>Wallnuts</hi> of <hi>Roch-Allom,</hi> and as much <hi>Honey</hi> as will make it ſweet: then take it, and ſtrain it through a fine <hi>linen-cloth,</hi> and waſh the parties mouth well therewith, and it will cure him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another approved <hi>Receipt</hi> for a <hi>Canker</hi> in the <hi>Mouth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke a good quantity of <hi>White-wine-Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neger,</hi> and as much <hi>Honey:</hi> ſet them over the fire to boil, with a little <hi>Allom,</hi> and when you think it is well boiled, take it off, and waſh your mouth often well therewith, and it will help you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For the <hi>Kings-Evill.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke of pure <hi>Yellow Wax</hi> 1 ounce or bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, alſo 1 ounce of <hi>Turpentine,</hi> and a good quantity of <hi>Sheeps-ſuet</hi> clarified, (<hi>viz.</hi> both pure and ſweet,) Boil all theſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and when they are well boil'd, put therein 2 good handfulls of the pureſt and fineſt <hi>Barley-flower,</hi> that poſſiby may be got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, then temper the ſame <hi>Flower</hi> and the other things together, and put therein 3
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:169737:75"/>
ſpoonfuls of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rin</hi> of a Man-Child, (he being not above 3 years of age) then boil it again with the reſidue of the things, before mentioned, and put it into ſome <hi>Earthen-pot</hi> or <hi>Gally-pot,</hi> &amp; ſo ſtop it and keep it cloſe, untill you have occaſion to uſe it, and as oft as occaſion ſerveth for the uſe thereof take ſome of the ſaid <hi>Salve</hi> or <hi>Ointment,</hi> and ſpread it upon a fine <hi>Linen-cloth,</hi> or upon a peece of <hi>Leather,</hi> and lay it plaiſterwiſe upon the <hi>Sore,</hi> and it will cure it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For an <hi>Impoſtume</hi> in the <hi>Head.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke a good quantity of the <hi>Juice</hi> of <hi>Mints,</hi> put it into a <hi>Quill,</hi> and ſo let it run into the patients ear upward, and this will cauſe the <hi>Impoſtume</hi> to break ſuddenly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another excellent <hi>Receipt</hi> to deſtroy any <hi>Impoſtume.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke of the Roots of <hi>Flower-deluces,</hi> and <hi>Roots</hi> of <hi>Lillies,</hi> of each a like quantity, ſtamp them together, and put therein a quart of <hi>Honey:</hi> Boil them all together, either in <hi>Wine</hi> or <hi>Ale;</hi> and when they are well boil'd then take the <hi>Liquor</hi> thereof, and ſtrain it
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:169737:75"/>
through a fine <hi>linen-cloth,</hi> and when occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſerveth for uſe thereof, let the Patient drink thereof 2 or 3 ſpoonfuls at a time, eſpecially in the morning and evening firſt and laſt, and this will ſpeedily cure it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A very good <hi>Medicine</hi> to cure the <hi>Deafneſs</hi> of the <hi>Ear.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Bay-Berries, Bay-laves, Betony,</hi> &amp; <hi>Stica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>does,</hi> of each a handfull: Boil them in <hi>Whitewine,</hi> untill the one half be conſumed; but if it be for one that is aged, it muſt be in <hi>Malmſey:</hi> then put it into a <hi>Narrow-mouthed-Veſſel,</hi> &amp; hold your ears over it, the Veſſel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unſtopped as hot as you may ſuffer it: then take <hi>Oyl</hi> of <hi>Bitter-Almonds,</hi> &amp; let 2 or 3 drops thereof fal into your Ears; then take a <hi>lock</hi> of <hi>Wooll</hi> that grows betwixt the <hi>Sheeps</hi> legs, and ſtop your <hi>Ears</hi> cloſe therewith, and if you put a little <hi>Musk</hi> in, it will be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Uſe this, and you ſhall find cure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another approved <hi>Receipt</hi> to cure the <hi>Deafneſs</hi> of the <hi>Ear.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke an <hi>Ox Gall,</hi> and the <hi>Stale</hi> of a <hi>Male-Goat;</hi> mingle them together, &amp; put ſome
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:169737:76"/>
of the ſame into the deaf ear of the Party grieved, and he ſhall forthwith find help.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An excellent <hi>Remedy</hi> to take away a <hi>Weft</hi> from the <hi>Eye</hi> that is grown over it, and darkneth the <hi>Sight.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke the <hi>Juice</hi> of <hi>Fennel,</hi> and pour ſome few drops of it into your Eye, and it ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth away the <hi>Weft</hi> immediately, and reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the <hi>Sight</hi> clear and perfect as it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, without all doubt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſpeciall <hi>Receit</hi> for the <hi>Corns</hi> on the Feet or Toes.</head>
               <p>FIrſt pare away the <hi>Corn;</hi> then take a black <hi>Snail,</hi> and bruiſe it, and put a drop or two of the <hi>Juice</hi> thereof into the place grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, &amp; put thereto a little powder of <hi>Sand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phere,</hi> and it will take away the Corn very ſpeedily.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another approved <hi>Remedie</hi> for <hi>Corns.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke a knife, and pare the <hi>Corn</hi> as neer the quick as it may be ſuffered; then take the inner part of a <hi>Fig,</hi> and a
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:169737:76"/>
prettie quantitie of <hi>Verdigreaſe:</hi> mix them both together, and lay the ſame to the <hi>Corn,</hi> and binde it faſt thereunto with a linen cloth, and this will in a ſhort time eat out the very root of the <hi>Corn.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſoveraign <hi>Receit</hi> to cure the Foul Diſeaſe, or <hi>French Pox.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke half a pound of <hi>Guiacum Capium,</hi> 2 ounces of <hi>Salſaperilla,</hi> 2 ounces of the <hi>Bark</hi> of <hi>Guiacum; Licoriſh, Anniſe-ſeeds, Fennel-ſeeds,</hi> and <hi>Sena,</hi> of each one ounce; <hi>Betony, Scabius, Smallage, Pellitory</hi> of the <hi>Wall, Peny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>royall, Harts-tongue, Maiden hair, Wilde</hi> or Red <hi>Mints,</hi> Red <hi>Sage, Oculus Chriſti, Liverwort,</hi> and the herb called <hi>Mercury,</hi> of each of them a good handfull: Pick them all clean and waſh them; then take them and put them all together into three Gallons of fair <hi>running-water</hi> to ſteep for the ſpace of one whole night; or elſe put it into 2 Gallons of pure <hi>White-wine,</hi> and one gallon of ſtrong <hi>Ale,</hi> and then boil them well together, untill ſuch time as the one half of the Liquor be conſumed: Then take it, and ſtrain it through a fine <hi>linen-cloth,</hi> and put it into a cloſe <hi>Veſſell,</hi> and ſo let it ſtand to ſettle, and
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:169737:77"/>
when it is ſetled, let the diſeaſed perſon uſe none other drink, but this broth both morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and evening and at meat: and into eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry three quarts of <hi>Water</hi> put a quarter of an ounce of <hi>Colloquintida,</hi> and ſo let the patient uſe this, untill he hath ſcoured his body marvelous well, and if it do not cauſe him to purge well, then let him uſe this, or the like Purgation.</p>
               <p>Take half an ounce of <hi>Sena,</hi> a ſpoonful of <hi>Aniſe-ſeeds,</hi> half an ounce of <hi>Licoriſh,</hi> one ſpoonful of <hi>Fennel-ſeeds,</hi> and 20 <hi>Raiſins</hi> of the <hi>Sun,</hi> the ſtones clean picked out. Boil them altogether in a quart of fair water, and let the ſame boil untill the one half be conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; then ſtrain it, and put thereto an ounce and a half of <hi>Diaphenicon,</hi> and ſhake the ſame well together, and let the Patient drink a pretty quantity thereof every morning faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (blood-warm) and it will cauſe him to purge exceeding well. This <hi>Receipt</hi> is won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull good for the afore-mention'd <hi>Diſeaſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A marvellous good <hi>Remedie</hi> for the <hi>Pleuriſie.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Brook-lime, Sheeps-ſuet,</hi> and a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle fair <hi>Water:</hi> fry them together in a <hi>Frying-Pan,</hi> and make a plaiſter there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:169737:77"/>
and lay it to the ſide of the patient, and it will draw forth all the corruption, and give eaſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A marvellous good Remedie for a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke the beſt <hi>Raiſins</hi> of the <hi>Sun</hi> half a pound, ſtone them, and put thereto 2 ounces of the pureſt brown <hi>Sugar-Candy;</hi> then put them into a wooden or ſtone Mortar, and beat &amp; incorporate them together, and in the beating of them over and again, put in the quantity of half a ſpoonfull at a time of <hi>Oyl</hi> of <hi>Sweet-Almonds,</hi> until you have put in ſo much as wil ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently moiſten them, and when the matter is beaten fine like a <hi>Conſerve,</hi> take thereof the quantity of a <hi>Nutmeg</hi> at a time firſt and laſt, and it will do you much good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another excellent <hi>Remedy</hi> for a <hi>Conſumption,</hi> or for any <hi>decay</hi> in the <hi>inward</hi> parts.</head>
               <p>TAke 2 pound of <hi>Dates,</hi> pick out the ſtones and skins, and the white that is in them, and beat them in a ſtone <hi>Mortar,</hi> as ſmall as can be, then take a quart
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:169737:78"/>
of fine clarified <hi>Honey;</hi> alſo long <hi>Pepper, Mace, Grains, Cloves, Nutmegs,</hi> of each a quarter of an ounce: Beat them fine to pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, then put your <hi>Honey</hi> and <hi>Dates</hi> together well mixed on the fire, and let them boil to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, alwayes ſtirring it for fear it burn too, and in your ſeething ſtir in your pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der by little and little till all be in; (you muſt not boil it ſo thick as you would boil <hi>Marmalade,</hi> for then you ſpoil it) then take half an ounce of fine <hi>Ginger</hi> beaten to pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and ſtrow it on, and alwayes ſtir it till it be cold, put it in a Box, as you do <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malade,</hi> and uſe to eat the quantity of a <hi>Cheſnut</hi> firſt and laſt: it cauſeth ſleep, and refreſheth health.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An exceeding good <hi>Receipt</hi> for a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke a handfull or two of <hi>Clary-leaves,</hi> and pick them clean, and 4 or 5 <hi>Yolks</hi> of <hi>Hen-Egs,</hi> newly laid: Make a <hi>Tanſie</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and uſe it 8 mornings together with <hi>Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megs</hi> and <hi>Sugar;</hi> then take <hi>Saffron</hi> and dry it upon a <hi>Tile ſtone,</hi> or ſome ſuch thing, and grind it very ſmall, and put all theſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and fry them in <hi>Freſh-Butter,</hi> and let
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:169737:78"/>
the Patient eat it firſt in the morning for 8 dayes together, and it will do him exceeding much good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another excellent <hi>Medicine</hi> for a <hi>Conſumption.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke a <hi>Cock</hi> that is of a reddiſh colour, and about the age of 4 or 5 years: kill him, and dreſs him very fair, and divide him into 4 quarters, and bruiſe him; then pick out all the fat very clean, and take half a handfull of <hi>red-Mints,</hi> and a handful of <hi>Harts-tongue,</hi> put them into a <hi>Pot,</hi> and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it cloſe, then put thereto half a pint of fair <hi>Running-water,</hi> and as much pure <hi>Malm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey,</hi> 6 crops of <hi>Hyſop,</hi> one root of <hi>Parſley,</hi> one root of <hi>Fennel,</hi> one root of <hi>Endive,</hi> drie <hi>red-Roſe-leaves, Raiſins</hi> of the <hi>Sun,</hi> and <hi>Pruines,</hi> of each 15. and 4 or 5 <hi>Maces:</hi> diſtill all theſe together, for the ſpace of 12 or 13 hours, and keep the <hi>Pot</hi> cloſe covered with <hi>Paſte,</hi> that none of the <hi>Liquor</hi> or <hi>Moiſture</hi> run out: Let the patient drink hereof every morning faſting, and by Gods help he ſhall recover.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:169737:79"/>
               <head>An experienced <hi>Medicine</hi> for the <hi>Tiſick.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Parſley-roots, Fennel-roots, Hyſop,</hi> and <hi>Succory-roots,</hi> of each an handful: pick all the piths clean out of them, and then waſh the <hi>Roots</hi> well, that there do no gravel or ſand remain in them: then ſeeth them in a pottle of <hi>White-wine</hi> untill they be ſoft, and if you can get any <hi>Ginger-berri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> boyl them therein with the reſt, and when it is well ſodden, ſtrain it, and put thereto a little <hi>Pellitory</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> a ſpoonfull of <hi>Engliſh-Honey,</hi> and a penny-worth of <hi>Saffron:</hi> Let the pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent drink it both morning and evening, for the ſpace of 8 or 9 dayes together, and this will help him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another approved <hi>Medicine</hi> for the <hi>Tiſick,</hi> and ſtopping in the <hi>Breſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke <hi>Rae</hi> and ſeeth it in <hi>Eyſel,</hi> and let the patient drink it; and let him alſo drink <hi>Nettle ſeeds</hi> brayed, and it will cauſe him to avoid great ſtore of <hi>gravel</hi> from the <hi>Stone</hi> in the <hi>Reines</hi> of the <hi>Back.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:169737:79"/>
               <head>A <hi>Phyſical Courſe</hi> to be obſerved in <hi>Plague-time,</hi> by thoſe that are viſited with the <hi>Sickneſſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SO ſoon as any apprehend themſelves ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with the <hi>Plague,</hi> let them go into their warm bed, and take this enſuing <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, viz:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take of <hi>Verben</hi> with the <hi>Root</hi> dried and powdred 2 drachms, and of the <hi>Juice</hi> of <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ben</hi> 3 ounces, half a ſpoonful of <hi>White-wine-vineger,</hi> mingle all together, and let them drink it warm, and ſweat for 2 or 3 hours. But let them not ſleep during the time of their ſweating: And whileſt they ſweat, let them hold under their <hi>Arm-pits,</hi> and upon the either <hi>Enunctories,</hi> eſpecially the <hi>Groyns,</hi> a <hi>Radiſh-root,</hi> divided into 2 parts: the ſame <hi>Root</hi> is to be tyed unto the <hi>Plants</hi> or <hi>hollow</hi> of their <hi>Feet,</hi> when they have ſweat well, for 2 or 3 hours, according to the ſtrength and age of the <hi>Patient:</hi> drie their bodies well with warm and clean linen-cloths, begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with the <hi>Arm-pits</hi> and <hi>Groyns,</hi> then the <hi>Breſt,</hi> whereon after the ſweat is well wiped away, lay a freſh and clean <hi>linen Napkin</hi> doubled. That done, let them waſh their
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:169737:80"/>
                  <hi>mouth, face</hi> and <hi>hands</hi> with <hi>water</hi> and <hi>vineger,</hi> and drink a good draught of <hi>Mutton-broth</hi> made with <hi>Roſemary, Thyme, Sorrel, Cicorie.</hi> If their ſtomach wil give them leave, they may eat a little <hi>Mutton</hi> or <hi>Veal</hi> at dinner, but they are to forbear <hi>Fleſh-meat</hi> at ſuppers. Inſtead of broth, <hi>Water grewel</hi> with <hi>Roſemary</hi> or <hi>Burnet</hi> will do well, or thin <hi>Pannada.</hi> For their drink, let it be ſmall or 6. ſhill: <hi>Beer</hi> warmed with a <hi>Toſte;</hi> or <hi>water</hi> boil'd with <hi>Carduus-ſeed,</hi> and <hi>Caroway ſeed,</hi> and the roots of <hi>Scabius</hi> and <hi>Verben,</hi> with a cruſt of <hi>bread.</hi> Then let them reſt, or ſleep, waſhing their <hi>mouth</hi> often with <hi>water</hi> and <hi>vineger.</hi> They may likewiſe make a <hi>Quilt</hi> with <hi>Balm, Mint, Roſemary, Sage, Sweet-marjoram</hi> dried: and ſprinkling it with <hi>vineger</hi> of <hi>Worm wood</hi> or <hi>Herb-grace,</hi> or ordinary <hi>wine vinegar,</hi> apply it to the region of the <hi>heart</hi> warm.</p>
               <p>After 8 hours from the firſt invaſion of the <hi>Plague,</hi> let them take another ſweating <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, viz:</hi> Take of the <hi>Powder</hi> of the <hi>Root</hi> of <hi>Dictamne, Scabius, Gentian,</hi> of each half a drachm, of the <hi>ſeed</hi> of <hi>Carduus Benedictus,</hi> 1 ſcruple, the <hi>Juice</hi> of <hi>Marigold flowers,</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils-bit,</hi> of each 2 ounces, half a ſpoonful of <hi>Vineger,</hi> of <hi>Rue</hi> or <hi>Wormwood,</hi> or, in want of them, of ordinary <hi>White-wine-vineger.</hi> Let
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:169737:80"/>
the ſick parties drink this warm, and ſweat again (as at the firſt time) 2. or 3. houres, keeping in the mean time a <hi>Radiſh-root</hi> at the <hi>Emunctories,</hi> as before. Then let them dry off the ſweat, waſh the <hi>mouth, face</hi> and <hi>hands,</hi> and take ſome convenient nouriſhment, and carry themſelves as in the firſt <hi>interim</hi> of 8. hours.</p>
               <p>Again the third time, after the like pauſe or interval, let them take another ſweating, and <hi>Cordiall Medicine</hi> in this manner, <hi>viz:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take of the <hi>Seed</hi> of <hi>Rue</hi> or <hi>Herb-grace</hi> a ſcruple and a half, of the <hi>roots</hi> of <hi>Enula Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pana, Valerian, Fullers Teaſels, Ariſtolochia</hi> the round, of each half a ſcruple, of the Juice of three-leaved <hi>Sorrel</hi> called <hi>Allebia</hi> two oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, of the <hi>juice</hi> of <hi>Rue,</hi> and <hi>Scabius,</hi> of each an ounce, and a little of the fore-named <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neger.</hi> Mix all theſe together, and let the ſick parties take it warm, and ſweat as before; and let them demean &amp; behave themſelves in all points as before, and continue this courſe for 4 or five days.</p>
               <p>But if any be in that extremity of pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that they cannot procure theſe eaſie and cheap <hi>Medicines,</hi> let them drink twice a day a draught of their own <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rin, viz:</hi> in the morning, and at 5 a clock in the afternoon.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="144" facs="tcp:169737:81"/>If in the firſt, 2d, or third day the <hi>Botches</hi> or <hi>Carbuncles</hi> appear, then follow the directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on given in pag. 120. and by the help of God you ſhall undoubtedly recover, unleſſe the poyſon have too much already poſſeſſed the Heart.</p>
               <p>But as a <hi>Corollarie</hi> and <hi>concluſion</hi> to the whole, take this caution along with you: ſee that you tamper not too ſoon with the <hi>Bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches</hi> or <hi>Blains,</hi> before they be well come forth, and nature well cleared and relieved; but rather continue in the taking of inward <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dials,</hi> and ſweating Medicines. The over-haſtie applying of <hi>Topical</hi> and outward <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies,</hi> eſpecially if they be forcible and ſharp, (which is too uſually practiſed by ſome <hi>Phyſicians</hi> and <hi>Chirurgians,</hi> and by <hi>Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents</hi> themſelves) do oft-times by cauſing <hi>pain,</hi> increaſing the <hi>Fever,</hi> and weak'ning <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> drive back and ſcatter <hi>the Venom</hi> into the inward parts, which ſuddenly by a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond aſſault, and encounter, ſurpriſeth the <hi>Fort</hi> of <hi>Life,</hi> the <hi>Heart,</hi> and carrieth away the <hi>Patient.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>—Si quid noviſti rectius iſtis,</l>
                  <l>Candidus imperti: ſi non, his utere mecum.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
